<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The inhumane cardinal, or, Innocence betray'd a novel. / Written by a gentlewoman, for the entertainment of the sex.</title>
            <author>Pix, Mary, 1666-1720.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 240 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 126 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90728</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2329A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R181820</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43077564</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43077564</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151648</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90728)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151648)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2269:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The inhumane cardinal, or, Innocence betray'd a novel. / Written by a gentlewoman, for the entertainment of the sex.</title>
                  <author>Pix, Mary, 1666-1720.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 237, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Harding, at the Bible and Anchor in Newport-street, and Richard Wilkin, at the King's-Head in St. Paul's Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Mary Pix.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: [3] p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Newberry Library, Chicago, Illinois.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151648:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Inhumane CARDINAL, OR, Innocence Betray'd.</p>
            <p>A NOVEL.</p>
            <p>Written <hi>By a Gentlewoman, for the Entertainment of the Sex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Harding,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Anchor</hi> in <hi>Newport-ſtreet,</hi> and <hi>Richard Wilkin,</hi> at the <hi>King's-Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-Yard,</hi> 1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:151648:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151648:2"/>
            <head>TO HER Royal Highneſs THE PRINCESS <hi>ANN,</hi> OF <hi>DENMARK.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>GReat is my Confuſion when I wou'd ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach; an humble Awe checks my Ambition; and I am afraid to lay ſo mean
<pb facs="tcp:151648:3"/>
a Trifle at the Feet of Your <hi>Royal Highneſs.</hi> But as with Heaven, a devoted Heart at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tones for a worthleſs Offering; ſo Moſt Excellent <hi>Princeſs,</hi> let the fervent Zeal, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines me towards your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, excuſe this too too bold an Undertaking.</p>
            <p>You are a <hi>Princeſs</hi> whoſe Preſence creates an Univerſal Joy and Veneration in all your pleas'd Beholders. We view in your Majeſtick Lineaments, the Auguſt Air of <hi>Royal Anceſtors:</hi> Whilſt with this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming Majeſty, ſomething ſo agreeably affable is join'd, that your humble Creatures find their Acceſs both eaſy and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful:
<pb facs="tcp:151648:3"/>
And thoſe who have the Honour and Happyneſs to attend your <hi>Royal Perſon,</hi> plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcover thoſe Moral and Princely Virtues, refin'd with ſincere Chriſtian Piety, which Beautify and Reign in your <hi>Heroick Soul:</hi> and the unequal'd Character they give, raiſes the love of Virtue in the Breaſt of the moſt ſtupid.</p>
            <p>'Tis ſaid Example goes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Precept; and that of all Examples we are fondeſt of thoſe our Princes ſet before us. How incorrigible then are theſe polluted Times, when <hi>You, Illuſtrious Madam,</hi> ſtand a Pattern moſt Excellently Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious?</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:151648:4"/>The Prayers of all good Men daily importune Heaven on your behalf, nor are their Prayers in vain; nor do the bounteous Powers barely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold ſuch worth, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; Bleſſings crowd around, and leave (I hope) no wiſh unſatisfied.</p>
            <p>Bleſt in the Royal Partner of your Bed, that Great Good Man; words that but ſeldom truly join; Bleſt your Self, and bleſſing all, in that Lovely Blooming Prince, the <hi>Duke of Gloceſter;</hi> whoſe forward Youth Wings the breath of Fame; and were her Tongues innumerable, when ſhe reports of him, ſome wonder muſt be
<pb facs="tcp:151648:4"/>
left untold. Joy of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Age, and Darling hopes, on which the future one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends. Oh may he Inherit the Extracted Virtues of all our <hi>Brittiſh Kings;</hi> the Courage of our Preſent Soveraign; but a Fortune peculiarly Great, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly his own; Conſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and far above whatever went before: that Succeeding Worlds, may to his Glorious Name, juſtly add the Epithet of Happy.</p>
            <p>I ought now to ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, in reference to the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Sheets; but my ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh'd Pen hath been enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd upon ſo ſublime a Theme, that it diſdains to deſcend;
<pb facs="tcp:151648:5"/>
and my heart full of Rapture, that is, full of your <hi>Royal Hig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> will only give me leave to endeavour the expreſſing, how much I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
               <signed>Your Royal Highneſs's Devoted humble Servant, <hi>Mary Pix.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:151648:5"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:151648:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151648:6"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Inhumane Cardinal,</hi> OR Innocence Betray'd.</head>
            <p>ALL that are converſant in Hiſtory, muſt remember the unbecoming Sway <hi>Donna Olimpia</hi> held in the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> during the Papacy of <hi>Innocent</hi> the Tenth. The Fiction of <hi>Hercules</hi>'s changing Cloaths with his beloved Miſtreſs, ought here to have been practis'd; for that Pope gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felf wholly up to Lazineſs and Effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minacy, whilſt <hi>Olimpia</hi> govern'd both in Church and State.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:151648:7"/>If any perſon wanted Eccleſiaſtical preferment, <hi>Donna Olimpia</hi> receiv'd their Preſents and Addreſs; if an Ambaſſador was earneſt for diſpatch, her Intereſt alone could obtain it. Thus ſhe remain'd courted, adored by all; Careſſing few, unleſs it were the Cardinals. Thoſe ſhe was very fond of making her Creatures, that her Power might rule in all their Councils.</p>
            <p>And amongſt that Scarlet Frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, <hi>Antonio Barbarino</hi> was the Man ſhe moſt affected. He was wicked, as her vileſt Wiſhes; and cunning as her ſubtleſt Thoughts, when they formed Revenge; <hi>Revenge</hi> which was her darling Pleaſure; Witneſs the Rage ſhe, for years, maintain'd againſt her own Son, only becauſe his Wife was great and beautiful.</p>
            <p>But to return to our matter: This Cardinal <hi>Antonio</hi> was ſomething cold, and did not follow her Meaſures ſo exactly as ſhe deſired; much ſhe would have done, to have obtained
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:151648:7"/>
the abſolute Aſcendant over him; and Fortune, at laſt, became obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to her Wiſh: She had obſerv'd the Cardinal, in ſome of his late Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits, to appear very ſad and thought<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; ſhe often preſs'd him to know the Cauſe, whilſt he for ſome time continued to evade her Importunity; at length, being alone with her, and ſhe becoming again inquiſitive, he uſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ering his Diſcourſe with a Sigh, began thus.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Madam, the fear that I ſhall ſtand wholly corrected, and condemned, by your ſeverer Vertue, has thus long deterr'd me from diſcloſing my Tortures. I know, Madam, you have Deſigns which you would give the World to effect; prove but then indulgent to thoſe dear guilty Wiſhes I am going to diſcover: and here I ſolemnly ſwear to aſſiſt you with my utmoſt power, in all your Commands, of what nature ſoever.</q> This Promiſe was too kind, not to gain the like Aſſurance from <hi>Donna
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151648:8"/>
Olimpia;</hi> and the Cardinal proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Ambition only fired my Youth, and led me on to Greatneſs; but now a gentler Flame hath filled my Heart, yet more tormenting. I am in Love, O <hi>Olimpia;</hi> raging mad with Love, to that degree poſſeſs'd, that if I enjoy not the Object of theſe violent Deſires, life it ſelf will become a burthen inſupportable.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Though <hi>Olimpia</hi> was declining in Age, and never any exact Beauty, yet ſo vain is Woman; that ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to hope for a declaration of Love; ſets her Face in the beſt order; puts on affected Looks; turns her Eyes from <hi>Antonio's:</hi> and ſeems in great expectation. But he quickly unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd her, by adding: <q>It is the beautiful <hi>Melora,</hi> Daughter to the Marqueſs of <hi>Coure,</hi> now Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor from <hi>France.</hi> Fair, charming as an Angel; her Eyes ſhoot amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Fire, yet are repleat with Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty; and much I fear, no Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151648:8"/>
though dreſs'd with allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Pleaſure, or dazling Wealth, will o'recome her. 'The vicious, anſwer'd wicked <hi>Olimpia,</hi> yield of themſelves; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>or were it worth your care or mine, were ſhe not virtuous. 'Leave this buſineſs, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſhe, to my conduct; and, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded your ſpoil not my Deſign with unſeaſonable Frugality; I'le ingage to bring <hi>Melora</hi> to your Arms.</q> The paſſionate Prieſt was tranſported, fell at her Feet, embraced her Knees, and promiſed her ineſtimable Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, if ſhe made good her Word. She asked him, if <hi>Melora</hi> knew him: he aſſur'd her, No; for there had been a miſunderſtanding betwixt her Father and him; and he was the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Perſon of his Rank, that did not frequent the Ambaſſador's Houſe, nor had ever ſeen her but at Church; where, added he, thoſe lovely un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heeding Eyes have never mark'd me with a fixt regard; the brighter Stars that now alone muſt rule my
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151648:9"/>
Fate. After other Diſcourſes to the ſame purpoſe, the Cardinal took his leave, and that night ſent <hi>Olimpia</hi> a Dreſſing-table cover'd with Plate, valu'd at eight Thouſand Crowns; for he knew <hi>that Woman</hi> avari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and took the right way to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten her Endeavours for his ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Soon after, this bribed Deſigner did the French Ambaſſador a ſignal piece of Service, in a buſineſs of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance; and when he would have made her a Preſent for that Favour: ſhe refus'd it, ſaying, all ſhe deſired in return, was: That he would ſend his Daughter, the fair <hi>Melora,</hi> to ſee her; for though a Woman, that Lady's Face had ſo charm'd her: ſhe even long'd to contract a Friendſhip with her. The good Marqueſs was tranſported to hear what an Honour was deſign'd his dear lov'd Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and delay'd not ſending her to wait upon <hi>Olimpia,</hi> who careſs'd her at an unuſual rate; diſcover'd all her little inſinuating Arts of Fondneſs,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151648:9"/>
whilſt the deluded Maid was, beyond expreſſion, pleaſed to hear her talk ſo kindly; to ſee all her rich Cabinets, and thoſe Millions of Curioſities ſhe was Miſtreſs of. Many pretty Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, (at the firſt Viſit) <hi>Olim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia</hi> forc'd <hi>Melora</hi> to accept; nor would ſhe part with her without a firm Promiſe of her coming every day to ſee her; which this innocent Virgin moſt willingly agreed to, and perform'd. Nothing now was more talk'd of, or envy'd amongſt the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, then this new Friendſhip: they appear'd at every publick place toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and <hi>Melora</hi> having a Garb ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to that Greatneſs, quickly add<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the number of her Adorers: but that was the only Reſtriction <hi>Olim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia</hi> gave her, not to entertain the Addreſſes of any, ſtill hinting at ſome wonderful Deſign ſhe had for her; and always ſaying to her, That Heaven had ſure ordain'd that lovely Face, that auguſt Mien, for Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty. Nor could <hi>Olimpia</hi> (as much
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151648:10"/>
as ſhe was inclin'd to it) flatter, in commending her, for ſhe was really amiable to a Miracle.</p>
            <p>She was of ſtature tall, ſhap'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Art of a Deſcription, and mov'd with a Majeſtick Air. Her Eyes were black and ſhining; and aw'd the trembling Lover from ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing long. Her Hair ſeem'd to vie with them for Charms and Luſtre; then her Skin was of that amazing whiteneſs, 'twould raiſe emotions in the moſt retired Recluſe. In fine, her Hands, Arms, and every agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Lineament of that exact Frame, her Body, forc'd from the moſt envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of her own Sex, the Appellation of a perfect Beauty. Nor did the bounteous Powers ſtop with theſe Graces; but gave alſo a Mind com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of Harmony: wiſe, as experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced Age; witty, as Youth, inſpired with Poetry: and innocent, as harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Childhood.</p>
            <p>Oh <hi>Melora!</hi> after-Ages ſhall with pity read, even to the end of Time,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151648:10"/>
that ſuch an Angel ſhould be given to the Guardianſhip of a Devil; for ſo curſt <hi>Olimpia</hi> prov'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Olimpia</hi> us'd a moſt ingaging way to all Perſons, where her Intereſt was concern'd; and though to the indifferent World, and thoſe beneath her, ſhe ſeem'd haughty, and full of pride; yet her inward Converſation was affable, and to a wonder plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; the higheſt Charms of which ſhe had even induſtriouſly beſtow'd upon <hi>Melora;</hi> and ſo perfectly was that young Creature indear'd to her, that ſhe would as ſoon have dy'd, and as willingly, as diſoblig'd her.</p>
            <p>The impatient Cardinal complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and told <hi>Olimpia,</hi> ſhe mov'd not half ſo faſt as his Deſires. But this cunning Artificer reſolv'd to lay a ſure Foundation before ſhe began ſo difficult a work. And the firſt ſtep towards it, was the deſiring <hi>Melora</hi> to let a famous Florentine Painter take her Picture in Miniature; which was granted, as ſoon as asked. The
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151648:11"/>
Piece was exquiſitely done, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to <hi>Olimpia.</hi> All ſeem'd now to favour her Deſigns; and ſhe only wanted an obliging Opportunity to introduce her well-laid Story to <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lora.</hi> Which thus happen'd: <hi>Olim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia</hi> coming from the Pope's Palace, call'd for her dear Companion (as ſhe term'd <hi>Melora</hi>) who was at her Father's Houſe, entertaining <hi>Donna Brandina,</hi> a Roman Lady of Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; but of a fantaſtick Humor: the chief Buſineſs of her Life, being to find out all the loving Affairs amongſt the great Ones, either in Court or City. Nay, ſo eager was ſhe at this inſignificant Curioſity, that ſhe kept a Correſpondency even with Chamber-maids. After <hi>Olimpia</hi> came in, <hi>Brandina</hi> began again to tell over all the impertinent amorous Adventures ſhe had lately heard; but perceiving them not much delighted with her fooliſh Relations: ſhe, at length, took her leave, to the wiſh'd deſire
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151648:11"/>
of the two friendly Ladies, who long'd to enjoy themſelves privately. For the accompliſhment of which <hi>Donna Olimpia</hi> propos'd taking the Air a few miles out of Town: <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lora</hi> being her perfect Devotee, with chearfulneſs agreed. As ſoon as their Coach was diſengag'd from the Hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Rome,</hi> that ſweet French Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, looking upon <hi>Olimpia</hi> with a Smile: Madam, ſaid ſhe, <hi>Donna Brandina</hi> came to me to day with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant News; and hath told me a Story, which hath extreamly diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me. What is't, for Heavens ſake, anſwer'd <hi>Olimpia,</hi> that talka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Creature could ſay to pleaſe thee, my Dear? It ſeems, reply'd the fair one, your Highneſs, out of your immenſe Goodneſs, ſetting a value upon the Trifle you command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (my Picture) has order'd a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidary to ſet it in Diamonds; which this inquiſitive Lady finding out, concludes a piece of Gallantry done by ſome Lover; and has plac'd me
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151648:12"/>
amongſt her Virgins, that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in Heroick Amours, as yet to her undiſcover'd. For (continu'd <hi>Melora</hi> laughing) ſhe keeps a dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Journal of all the Intrigues that paſs, and is now almoſt diſtracted to know my humble Servant.</p>
            <p>
               <q>It is ſtrange, ſaid <hi>Olimpia, that</hi> empty Creature ſhould gueſs at hidden Truths; for ſince Chance hath broke the Ice, I will own to thee, my deareſt Girl, 'tis an illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Lover, is giving that deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Ornament to thy charming Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture. 'How, Madam, ſaid <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lora!</hi> nay, if you reſolve to rally your Servant, I muſt remain dumb, and only anſwer with confuſion and Bluſhes.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>No, reply'd <hi>Olimpia,</hi> in a grave Tone, this is as true as you are fair and good; there is a Perſon in the World is in Love with you. In Love with you! Oh weak Expreſſion! added ſhe vehemently; is dying for you; ſuffers all the violent
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151648:12"/>
pangs, Poetry e're feigned, or man e're felt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>His Quality is Supream; yet his Ambition terminates in being your Slave; then be not angry that I have given him your Picture: For though you are bright as an Angel, and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs of unequal'd Charms; yet he deſerves, my Faireſt, even you, end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Olimpia,</hi> embracing her. <q>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is acted by my Divineſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troneſs, ſaid <hi>Melora,</hi> bowing low, by me, with ſtricteſt Obedience and higheſt Pleaſure ſhall be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; and when you, my ever ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Friend, grow weary of my faithful Heart: diſpoſe of it as you pleaſe, your Commands muſt needs be eaſie. 'Be aſſured, Charmer (anſwer'd this deſigning Lady) I will never part with that ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Jewel, but upon Terms that ſhall wholly redound to your Advantage.</q>
            </p>
            <p>She paus'd upon this, and left the Subject for <hi>Melora</hi> to conſider ſome few days without farther explaining
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151648:13"/>
her ſelf. <hi>Then</hi> ſeeming in a very pleaſant Humor, ſhe takes <hi>Melora</hi> into her Cabinet, and ask'd her ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, if ſince their laſt private Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, ſhe had not dream'd of an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh'd Cavalier ſighing at her Feet, and dying for her Love? <q>My Thoughts, reply'd that modeſt Maid, ſo ſeldom frame an Idea of Mankind, that it is almoſt impoſſible that they ſhould diſturb my Dreams.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>But methinks, ſaid <hi>Olimpia,</hi> one recommended by me, ſhould make a little deeper impreſſion on that frigid Heart. of yours. 'Behold here, added ſhe, (taking out a gold Box, and opening it) your Picture which with much ado I obtain'd from the Amorous Prince for an hour or two.</q> 
               <hi>Melora</hi> took it in her hand, and view'd it with wonder; nor could ſhe chuſe; for it was a dazling Object, being ſet Oval fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion in large Diamonds: Round the faireſt, which was uppermoſt, theſe words were ingraven;</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:151648:13"/>
            <q>Dim, to the Luſtre of her Eyes.</q>
            <p>
               <q>Now, Madam, cry'd <hi>Melora</hi> ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly, you muſt forgive my Curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, and permit me, like my Sex, to be wondrous inquiſitive: For the Title of Prince, which you have given this <hi>unknown,</hi> and the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of theſe Jewels, ſtrike me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to amazement; I cannot believe your Goodneſs would abuſe my Credulity with fictitious Stories; nor can I have Pride enough to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine a Prince my Lover. 'What I told you before, I ſolemnly confirm, ſays <hi>Olimpia,</hi> he is not only your Lover, but Slave; yet over part of the World an Abſolute Soveraign: All this is truth; but 'tis a Truth of ſuch a conſequence, that I muſt lay upon you wonderful Injunctions e're I venture to unravel it, your faithful Breaſt muſt lock this Secret up as ſafe as if my Life depended upon diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſing it; or if there is any thing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151648:14"/>
you hold dearer, by <hi>that</hi> I conjure you, let not your own Father now the leaſt Circumſtance of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery; and if you dare truſt me wholly with the Management of your Fortune, which 'twould break my Heart to doubt; in earneſt you ſhall ſuddenly appear the moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, as well as the moſt beautiful Princeſs in <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>So perfectly did <hi>Melora</hi> confide in <hi>Olimpia,</hi> that ſhe made no ſcruple to rely upon her Conduct, and promis'd even with Imprecations, a moſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and exact Secrecy, to whatſoever ſhe would relate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Olimpia</hi> gave order not to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb'd, and began thus: <q>You muſt arm your ſelf with Patience to hear a Story, that will be of a long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance before it points at <hi>you. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lora,</hi> by a graceful bow, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing ſilent, let <hi>Olimpia</hi> know her Expectation, and Attention; when that cruel Princeſs, ſeeming a while to recollect her ſelf, dreſs'd up a true Story in the following words.</q>
            </p>
            <div type="history">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:151648:14"/>
               <head>The Hiſtory of <hi>Alphonſus</hi> and <hi>Cordelia.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Otho</hi> Duke of <hi>Ferrara</hi> and <hi>Modena</hi> had an only Son nam'd <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> who was above what I am able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe; all the World acknowledging him accompliſh'd to the higheſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree. His Father was yet luſty, and ſtirring in State-affairs, which gave <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus</hi> liberty to follow many youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Adventures.</p>
               <p>Amongſt the reſt, he propos'd to a Favourite of his, call'd <hi>Don Caſtro</hi> (the beginning of a glorious Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer) taking a Ramble in the adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Countries under borrow'd Names: the Prince was very young and very brisk, when this was men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd, and his Companion being ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for years and Temper, they ſoon agreed, and put their Deſign into Action. <hi>Alphonſus</hi> calling him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>Don Pedro;</hi> and <hi>Castro, Philippo.</hi> The morning they began their Fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151648:15"/>
                  <hi>Alphonſus</hi> left a Letter upon his Table for his Father, the Contents of which, only wiſhed him long life, health, and happineſs, begging his Pardon for a youthful Excurſion; which ſhould tend neither to his own, nor any perſons prejudice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Court was at firſt mightily alarm'd; but <hi>Otho</hi> recollecting the Humors of his own Youth, was at length content to hope this was only an innocent Folly.</p>
               <p>Theſe noble Rovers had paſt ſome weeks, and were got a great diſtance from <hi>Ferrara,</hi> before any extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Occurrence happen'd to them. They had viſited ſome Cities; but were now retir'd into the Country, where <hi>Don Pedro</hi> (for by that Name you muſt underſtand the Prince) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to complain to his Friend of the dulneſs of their Ramble, and inveigh againſt the fair Sex, for their Civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in ſparing them their Hearts and Liberty. <q>It was ſuch melancholy
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151648:15"/>
Reflections as theſe, reply'd <hi>Philippo,</hi> caus'd me, at break of day, to fetch a penſive Walk ſome diſtance from hence, where I met with a ſmall Intrigue that gave me a proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Diverſion. 'Oh Churl, cry'd out <hi>Don Pedro,</hi> how could you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal it one moment; Be not ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient, anſwers the other; for I think it ſcarce worth your hearing: however thus it was, I enter'd a large Foreſt, and after I had walk'd ſome time, liſtning only to the Harmony of the Birds, and viewing the Verdure of thoſe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Shades, I ſaw through the Trees, walking a ſwift pace, a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier well dreſs'd. After I had a while obſerv'd him, I fancy'd by his haſte, and the time of the day, he was upon ſome private Deſign; therefore not to interrupt him, I left the path that led me after him, and wandred into another. But Fortune reſolv'd <hi>that</hi> ſhould not be my laſt interview; for in a quarter of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151648:16"/>
an hour's ſpace, I was come to a high Wall where I percev'd my Spark ſome yards from me, waiting in a diſconſolate poſture, and ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to expect ſomething from thence. I ſhould he had not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd me; and my curioſity was ſuch, I could not forbear obſerving the Event. To that end I conceal'd my ſelf behind a Shrub, where I could with eaſe view what paſs'd. The Gentleman began to grow ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry impatient, as I perceiv'd by his Geſtures: ſometimes he whiſtled, which I gueſs'd to be the ſign; then walk'd with a perturbed pace. At length, quite tyr'd, he cry'd out: Perfidious Creature! falſe as thou art fooliſh! to ſquander away thy Patrimony only to ſatisfie thy curſt curioſity! After he had rav'd thus, and vex'd himſelf above an hour: away he walks, ſtill curſing his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auſpicious Stars, and thoſe greater Plagues, deceitful Women. I laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and hug'd my ſelf, for being
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151648:16"/>
free from all the Snares of that inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuating Sex. Entertain'd with theſe pleaſing Thoughts I haſten'd home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards; but e're I was got half way, a Fancy ſeiz'd my Noddle to return back, and viſit the afore-mention'd Wall again, making ſuch a ſign as I had already heard. The Whim pleas'd me; and methought I was aſſur'd, I ſhould finiſh the Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which this too haſty Gallant had left. Accordingly I turn'd my ſteps, and having reach'd the place, I had no ſooner whiſtl'd, but my expectation was anſwer'd; for over the Wall came a Key ty'd to this Billet, which he gave to the Prince who read theſe words.</q>
               </p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>The LETTER.</head>
                     <p>THE ſight this Key procures you, I doubt not, will amply recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>enſe your Bounty and long Waiting; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ome before day, and creep cloſe along <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he thick Arbours; if through any ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151648:17"/>
accident, you ſhould be diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: rather ſay, you ſcal'd the Walls, or dropt from the Clouds, than own a Correſpondency with</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Your humble Servant</hi> Luſetta.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>There was a Poſtſcript to this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect:
<q>
                     <hi>I</hi> Suppoſe you have been ſo long view<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing the Wall, that I need not in form you the little door, whereof this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Key, is on the West ſide.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Well, ſaid <hi>Don Pedro</hi> ſmiling, and what Advantage do you intend to reap by this pretty Miſtake? 'Tru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, anſwer'd <hi>Philippo,</hi> I heartily wiſh the Gentleman, it belongs to had it; for I have no mind to ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>zard my Life in our Italian Fami<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lies to ſee novel Sights. 'Nay, if yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> are ſo indifferent, reply'd the Princ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:151648:17"/>
you ſhall quit your Right in this Adventure to me; for I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent there is a fair Lady in the Caſe, and am reſolv'd, if you deſiſt, to ſee her.</q>
               </p>
               <p>In vain <hi>Philippo</hi> us'd a thouſand Arguments, and talk'd till the Prince commanded his ſilence. He was obſtinate, nor could a fond Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom long more for the night's ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, than this raſh Noble Youth did for the morning. As ſoon as ever the firſt ſtreaks of day appear'd, he begins his Walk. Poor <hi>Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po</hi> parts with much reluctancy and fear, reſolving to follow him, and watch thereabouts, till his Return. <hi>Don Pedro</hi> carefully obſerv'd the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections he had forc'd from his Friend, whom he would not ſuffer to go with him; his Fate ſeeming to whiſper the Prize he was to gain, would admit no Sharers. When he had found the place, he ſoftly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locks the door, which he perceiv'd was left unbor'd on purpoſe, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151648:18"/>
a lovely place, beholding both to Art and Nature for its beauty. He takes the firſt cloſe Walk, which brought him to the pleaſanteſt Grotto, your Fancy can poſſibly repreſent. It was exactly four ſquare; and in every corner the knots of Trees were thick, mingling their Boughs over delicate Marble Seats, whoſe backs were painted with ſeveral Hiſtories. Long Walks, with leavy Screens, that ſhut out the Sun's fierce Beams, conducted you from every of theſe delightful Seats to the other. In the midſt was a large ſpace adorn'd with a curious Fountain; that which made this Fountain ſo admirable, was the Statue of <hi>Venus:</hi> at the head of it there was the Goddeſs figur'd in Marble, with <hi>Adonis</hi> ſlain at her Feet, whilſt from her Eyes ſtreams inceſſantly ran down, bath'd the lov'd Youth, and ſeem'd to fill the vaſt Ciſtern underneath, which with an agreeable murmur ſtill receiv'd them. Beyond all this was an exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151648:18"/>
Garden enamel'd with choiſeſt Flowers and Fruits.</p>
               <p>The Prince had entertain'd himſelf a conſiderable time in this Charming place, and began to fear the Sight the Letter promis'd, was only theſe Rarities; though, to comfort him, he could at a great diſtance eſpy a fair well built Houſe; and hop'd a fairer iſſue from it. Nor was he diſappointed; for e're he had waited much longer, he through the Trees, diſcovers a Woman bringing four crimſon Velvet Cuſhions, which ſhe lays, two upon the ground, and two upon one of the Marble Seats. After ſhe was gone, our Hero ſeeks out a place, as near this Arbour as he could that would conceal him. There was no poſſibility of looking into it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being ſeen; ſo that he is forc'd to go behind, and be a Hearer only of what the Perſons would ſay, that were to poſſeſs thoſe Seats.</p>
               <p>He had ſcarce time to fix himſelf before he heard the ruſling of Silks,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151648:19"/>
and ſweet ſmall Voices: which made him conclude his Neighbours, Ladies. After general Diſcourſes, not material, one of them ſaid: <q>I cannot but wonder, my charming Couſin, that the wiſe <hi>Sulpitia</hi> ſhould take delight to bury ſo much Beauty as yours in obſcurity, and confine your Youth to theſe melancholy Shades; when but appearing at Court with you, would ſoon raiſe your ancient Noble Family to its priſtine Splendour. For I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd no Prince, of what Rank ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, could look upon ſo lovely a Creature, without laying his Heart and Crown at her Feet. 'Fy, Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin, ſaid the other, with a charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Voice, I muſt needs chide you for your flattery, and condemn your blaming my Mother's conduct. You are ſenſible, the riotous living of ſome of my Anceſtors has ſo impai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red our Fortunes, that this Seat and a ſmall Revenue, is all remains. In this deprav'd Age, without Gold,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151648:19"/>
what can I expect by this little ſtock of Beauty, which you talk ſo much of but vicious Adorers? Would you have my Mother then expoſe me to Courts? The thought ſhocks my Virgin Soul, and makes me ſtart when no danger's near. Oh! rather, let <hi>Cordelia</hi>'s Name paſs ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurely to the Grave, forgotten, than be remembred, and Diſhonour affix'd to it.</q>
               </p>
               <p>A noble Reſolution, thought our Liſtener, who now long'd to ſee her Face. Some time after, they roſe to walk, the Prince then crept near as poſſible, and putting the leaves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, beheld the brighteſt Beauty upon Earth. He ſtood immoveable, and if the Ladies had look'd that way, with half his Attention, they muſt have diſcover'd him. <hi>Cordelia</hi> was dreſs'd in a Gown of green Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mask; the Sleeves were becomingly tucked up to her Shoulders; and trim'd round with white and red Knots, like Roſes. Her ſhining Hair, in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151648:20"/>
careleſs Curls, partly cover'd her lovely Neck; the reſt exactly puff'd: adorn'd with many pretty Ribons, and ſome Jewels.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>I have deſcrib'd her Garb (ſaid <hi>Olimpia</hi> ſmiling, and pointing to a large Looking-glaſs that hung in the Cloſet) but you muſt look in yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Mirrour to ſee her Perſon. <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lora</hi> bluſh'd, and <hi>Olimpia</hi> went on.</q> The Prince, at this moment, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd from his Breaſt the Idea of all the Court-Beauties he had ever ſeen, and gaz'd on this Maſter-piece of Nature ſo long, till he had imprint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Cordelia</hi>'s Image too deep for time ever to deface. Whilſt the Ladies, far from gueſſing at an Obſerver, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd their Walk, and went in, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>Alphonſus</hi> like one who had ſeen a Viſion, all ſurpriz'd. When he began to think, he ſummons his ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling Humour to his aid, and the improbability of obtaining his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires. This, and much more, he thought, but all in vain; her Shape,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151648:20"/>
her Mien, her charming Face; then her noble Mind ſurpaſſing all, ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him her Slave for ever. He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd a thouſand Projects in his working Brain, which way to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain acceſs to her. Sometimes he tormented himſelf, becauſe he had not ſpoke to her when ſhe was there; now pleas'd with the hopes ſhe would return. In theſe reſtleſs Cogitations he ſpent moſt part of the day. As the Evening began to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, <hi>Don Caſtro</hi> who had often viſited the outſide of the Wall, was in a great Conſternation; he fear'd ſome miſchief had befaln the Prince; and knew not what Method to take to be ſatisfy'd. At laſt not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to remain longer in ſuſpence of his ſafety, he went boldly to the Front of the Houſe, and knock'd at the Gate: the Porter came, and when he had open'd it, ſays <hi>Don Caſtro;</hi> 
                  <q>Pray, Friend, what is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of a Gentleman that came this morning into your Garden? If you
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151648:21"/>
have done miſchief to him, all your Lives, even to the higheſt of your Family, muſt anſwer it.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The Fellow all amaz'd, cry'd out; <q>I ſuppoſe, Sir, you are either mad, or have miſtook the Houſe; for we have no Gentlemen ever come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe Walls, ſince my Honour'd Lord is gone to Heaven (at the mention of whom, the Lowt began to make a Face, as though Tears would follow). <hi>Don Caſtro,</hi> whoſe Fears were augmented by this Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low's, as he thought, pretended ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance: charged him in a furious Tone, to be his Conductor to his Friend, or he would ſend him to a place juſt contrary to that he ſaid his Maſter was in. At this Noiſe the other Servants came about them. One diſcreeter than the reſt, ran and acquainted <hi>Sulpitia</hi> with this ſtrange ſtory. <hi>Sulpitia,</hi> whoſe Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was the deareſt Jewel ſhe had on Earth, hearkned to it with an emotion of Spirit, and deſir'd the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151648:21"/>
Gentleman might be brought to her. When <hi>Caſtro</hi> came, he told the whole matter, juſt as I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore related, as much as poſſible, excuſing the Curioſity of his youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Friend. <hi>Luſetta</hi> was inſtantly call'd, who when ſhe had heard her Accuſation, trembling confeſs'd, That ſhe was ſeduc'd by a Kinſwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man for a Summ of Money, to let one <hi>Don Ferado</hi> ſee the beautiful <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delia: Sulpitia</hi> only bid her retire, deferring her puniſhment to another time, and haſtened into the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Now whilſt this had been acting in the Houſe, the Ladies who were gone to take their evening Walk, were not free from their ſurprize; for <hi>Alphonſus</hi> ſeeing them return, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to appear and ſay, what his fierce Love ſhould dictate. Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly he walk'd towards them, <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delia</hi> lifting up her Eyes at the noiſe he made in walking, and ſeeing ſo brave a Cavalier in that prohibited
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151648:22"/>
place, ſhriek'd aloud, and would have fled: but he putting one Knee to the Ground, took hold of her Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, viewing her with a piercing Air: <q>Divineſt Creature, ſaid he, Heaven e're made, or Man e're worſhipp'd! Fly not; your Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian Angel as ſoon will hurt you as your kneeling Slave. Fate, prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Fate, brought me hither, and now a greater Power tyes me at your Feet for ever.</q>
               </p>
               <p>As he would have proceeded, they heard people talking, and <hi>Cordelia</hi> ſaw <hi>Sulpitia</hi> juſt by her: <q>Oh Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, cry'd that lovely Maid, my Mother will think me culpable, and that with conſent I have entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Diſcourſe with this Intruder.</q> 
                  <hi>Alphonſus</hi> roſe aſtoniſh'd to ſee his Friend there, and turning his Eyes with anger upon him, was about to ſpeak, when <hi>Sulpitia</hi> interrupted him, in ſaying: <q>Whatever your Deſigns were, this Gentleman (pointing to <hi>Castro</hi>) hath told ſuch
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151648:22"/>
a plauſible ſtory, that I am content to diſmiſs you without farther Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination, provided you inſtantly retire, and trouble our Repoſe no more.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Though you were a Goddeſs, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> as being Mother to this Lady, I eſteemm you little leſs (bowing to <hi>Cordelia</hi>) I would not ſtir till this bright Fair com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded; let her but ſpeak; let her but ſay my Preſence is an Offence, and I'le fly faſt as I would do, if Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour call'd; ſwift, as Cowards fly, when Death purſues, elſe I am root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed here.</q> 
                  <hi>Cordelia</hi> bluſh'd; but the curious might perceive it was not with anger. Her Mother bid her command him thence, and ſhe obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; yet not quite ſo readily as was expected. He reſpectfully took his leave, told <hi>Cordelia,</hi> with his Eyes that he had left his Heart; turn'd back, and ſeem'd to wiſh ſhe would uſe it kindly.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Oh, <hi>Caſtro,</hi> ſaid the Prince, when
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151648:23"/>
they were diſengag'd, and walking homewards, Thou haſt undone me. Thy officious Love hath prov'd my ruine; rob'd me of the only happy moments my life will ever know: now I muſt wander o're the World the verieſt Wretch that eye of time e'er ſaw, whilſt this bright Image I have thus tranſitorily view'd, wracks my captivated Heart, and takes repoſe for ever from my Soul.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>I hope, ſays <hi>Caſtro,</hi> this Roman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick ſpeech is only to ſhow your Highneſs's Parts, and amuſe me; for certainly no Idea, how beautiful ſoever, can ruffle the calmneſs of your Royal Temper. 'Dull Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, reply'd the Prince, couldſt thou behold the Miracle, and after that remain ſo ſtupid, to believe I am in Jeſt? No, I ſwear it is unal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terably fix'd by Fate. I muſt neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect Intereſt, Ambition, Glory, and all the noiſy Pomp the World af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords, ſince now the ſtudy and buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151648:23"/>
of my life is only to obtain the ador'd <hi>Cordelia.</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>Caſtro</hi> ſeeing him in this Rapture, thought 'twas to no purpoſe to interrupt him; and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to hear the ſtory of the day, which the Prince related, and concluding with new Proteſtations of his endleſs Love, they went to their Lodgings. But no Reſt had the amorous <hi>Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> plainly telling his Friend, if he did not contrive ſome means, that he might ſee her again, he muſt expect to ſee him dead. <hi>Caſtro</hi> at laſt began to believe it; for he ſcarce eat or ſlept, nor ever ſeem'd pleas'd, but when he was talking of <hi>Cordelia.</hi> In vain did his faithful Servant remonſtrate the neceſſity of returning to Court: nay, he could not mention it without putting the Prince in a paſſion; who ſolemnly vow'd he would never ſee <hi>that,</hi> or his Father more, till he had again bleſt his longing Eyes with the ſight of the beloved charming <hi>Cordelia.</hi> When <hi>Caſtro</hi> ſaw all Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, all Endeavours to reduce his
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151648:24"/>
Reaſon, fruitleſs: he thought the only Expedient muſt be, to procure this much deſir'd Happineſs; and in order to it, made inquiry very ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly about the Village, what Perſons reſorted to <hi>Sulpitia</hi>'s Houſe. But could hear of none, except a Fryar who was a conſtant Gueſt there. He then examin'd into the Temper of that Holy man; heard it was jolly, free from care; that he liv'd the life of Senſe himſelf, how ſevere ſoever his Doctrine was; though before <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitia</hi> he carry'd himſelf with a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming Gravity.</p>
               <p>This Man <hi>Caſtro</hi> reſolves to get ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with; and underſtood the way was eaſie, only two or three good Treats, and he was yours for ever: he ſoon effects his firſt deſign; grows wondrous intimate with the Fryar, his only Favourite; and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his opportunity, cunningly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terweaves his Diſcourſe with many particular Queſtions: amongſt the reſt, becoming inquiſitive about <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitia</hi>'s
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151648:24"/>
Family, asking what her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions were, concerning her beaute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Daughter the fair <hi>Cordelia;</hi> At which the Fryar bleſt himſelf, won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring how he had ſo much as learnt that Lady's name; in ſuch ſecure Retirement her Mother kept her; nay even he, whoſe Tongue ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times run of all things, ſeldom men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd them. However this was too dear a Friend to be deny'd any ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction his Knowledge would afford; and he immediately, at large, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints <hi>Castro,</hi> how nicely vertuous; and withal, how high <hi>Sulpitia</hi>'s Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per was; that ſhe rather choſe to keep the unimitable Maid immur'd in the moſt ſecret privacy, than marry her below her Birth, though equal to her ſcanty Fortunes. Next that, ſhe carefully avoided Courts and publick Places, fearing the cenſorious World, which always fixes its faſcinating Eyes on the moſt lovely Faces.</p>
               <p>This Information <hi>Caſtro</hi> commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicates to the Prince; yet both their
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151648:25"/>
induſtry could imagine no advantage by it. At theſe difficulties <hi>Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> abandons himſelf to Deſpair; threatens to be rid of life, ſince no fairer Proſpect was in view to eaſe his Heart of Love's tormenting Fires. The young compaſſionate Lord, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted with his Maſter's griefs, propos'd the Fryar's making the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Marriage, under the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row'd Name of <hi>Don Pedro.</hi> But the Heroick Prince declin'd that Offer; reſolving firſt to endeavour the inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging <hi>Cordelia</hi>'s Heart, and not force the gentle Maid to Bonds, ſhe might think uneaſie. He told <hi>Caſtro</hi> he diſcover'd ſmall incouragement from his Acquaintance with the Fryar; unleſs his Intereſt could prevail ſo far, as to ingage the ſociable Gown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to introduce him in ſome Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe into the Family: then he might hope to ſound <hi>Cordelia</hi>'s Inclinations, and alſo tell his own, in Terms mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving enough to touch her. <hi>Caſtro</hi> promis'd to undertake it, though he
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151648:25"/>
fear'd the Task would prove hard to accompliſh. In order to this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, he deſires privacy with that Fryar, and in the firſt place genteely forces a conſiderable Summ of Gold upon him, beginning his Diſcourſe with the Merit, Riches, and an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented Title of Quality for his Friend; adding his deſperate Condition aſſures him, unleſs he inclines to pity, and aſſiſt, Death muſt certainly be the Cataſtrophe of his Miſery. The Fryar conſider'd all theſe Reaſons, and chiefly the Preſent; yet ſhrug'd, and ſaid, 'Twas difficult, 'twas dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly difficult, deſiring time for his Anſwer; which <hi>Caſtro</hi> allow'd.</p>
               <p>When they met next, the Prieſt tells him, there was but one poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of obtaining the Freedom of the Houſe, and that did neither agree with the good Man's Conſcience, nor was conſiſtent with his Friend's ſafety. <hi>Caſtro</hi> ſtarts at this; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever was eager to know the dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Contrivance. You muſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151648:26"/>
then (thee obliging Fryar goes on) I have often mention'd, at <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitia</hi>'s, that I expected a Relation of the Dominican Order very ſuddenly. Now if <hi>Don Pedro</hi> could perſonate him, which is Death by the Law, if diſcover'd, he may have admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with me as often as I pleaſe; and I think it is impoſſible, they, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had ſo ſhort an Interview, as you ſpeak of, can ever remember him in the diſguiſe of a Hood. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtro</hi> agreed to that; but could give no further Anſwer, till he had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted the Prince, who ſeems to ſwallow his words, and with ſwifteſt haſte returns with him to the Fryar: gives the Prieſt more Gold to molli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his Scruple of Conſcience: and inſtantly prepares for his Diſguiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>In my Opinion (ſaid <hi>Melora,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupting <hi>Olimpia</hi>) a religious Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit is both unhandſom and unfit to carry on an amorous Intrigue.</q>
                  <q>It is ſo, my pious Maid (anſwers that Diſſembler) and, for ought I know,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:151648:26"/>
the many Troubles that are inflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on their Poſterity, may be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments for this firſt mockery of the Divinity.</q>
               </p>
               <p>However the Deſign ſucceeded to their Wiſh; for <hi>Don Pedro</hi> was with the Fryar, receiv'd free from all ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicion, and enjoy'd often the agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Converſation of the amiable <hi>Cordelia.</hi> Their Diſcourſe was of various Subjects; he never having had opportunity to ſpeak to her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. All Occaſions he watches, which may in the leaſt advance his deſires: and Love being mention'd by chance, our diſguis'd Prince falls into a Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, calling it, if a vertuous Flame, the higheſt Perfection humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is capable of; a reſemblance of Heaven; adding a thouſand Fineries on that delightful Theme.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>You always ſpeak with much Rhetorick (ſays the fair <hi>Cordelia</hi> ſmiling) but on this Subject ſeem inſpir'd, and I ſhould gueſs, did not your Habit contradict it, Love has
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:151648:27"/>
been no Stranger to your Heart; 'tis ſo familiar on your Tongue.</q> He only fetch'd a deep ſigh, and ſtole an amorous Glance towards her; which ſhe not obſerving, went on. <q>Pray, ſince you underſtand this paſſion ſo well, oblige me with a deſcription of it; tell me in what manner people are, when poſſeſs'd with the Frenzy: for the grave and wiſe give it no better Title.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>The Task you enjoyn (Madam) ſaid the Prince, is none of the eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt; for divers ineffectually, tho' they felt its Torments, have eſſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. I have the greateſt Reaſon then to fear falling amongſt that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, being the moſt incompetent. However I will venture, rather than diſobey your Commands.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>It is an Inclination, which being throughly fix'd in the Heart, gets predominant over all others. 'Tis the whole Employment of our Thoughts; for the paſſionate Lover has not one intervening moment;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:151648:27"/>
his breaſt is for ever fill'd with the beloved Idea. If they are aſunder, a violent deſire is join'd to this Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to be with the charming Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. Theſe eager Wiſhes render nights and days inſupportable. If they are together, a trembling Fear, leſt any word or action ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe is ever preſent. Then too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Jealouſie ſteps in. Thus abſent or preſent, ſtill in fears. Such unea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs attends the moſt happy Lovers. But what Wrecks, what Tortures unexpreſſible ſeize the Wretch who loves, and yet deſpairs! Who doats, yet has no room for hope.</q> 
                  <hi>Cordelia</hi> ſighed, and cry'd, <q>Alas! that's ſad indeed.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Why, Madam, ſaid the Prince, haſtily; I hope ſuch Miſery hath no relation to your ſofter hours; 'Not much, ſhe anſwer'd, with a Bluſh that increas'd our Lover's fears to diſtraction.</q> He was eager to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue the Diſcourſe, though it might diſcover what he moſt dreaded; but
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:151648:28"/>
ſhe prevented him, by going to the Company.</p>
               <p>His Reſentment and Grief was too great not to be perceiv'd; therefore he took his leave ſomewhat abrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and when he had ſhifted his Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe (which he always did at the Fryar's) he haſtens to his dear Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident <hi>Caſtro,</hi> immediately tells him his Misfortune, how <hi>Cordelia</hi> was prepoſſeſs'd, had given that ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Jewel her Heart to a Rival, a Rival belov'd: there was the wound! This obliging Friend ſaid all that might aſſwage his Sorrows; yet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could allay them: he paſs'd that night in terrible Inquietudes, goes the next day, without reſolving any thing, to <hi>Sulpitia</hi>'s: his inward vexations had made a viſible altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in his Countenance, and he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd with an Air of melancholy diſorder. <hi>Cordelia,</hi> who was allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but little Converſation, finding the Prince very ingenious, took great delight in it. She immediately ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:151648:28"/>
this alteration, and ask'd him the occaſion. <q>Herein, Madam, ſaid he with a Sigh, forgive the forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of my devoir, and permit me to diſobey you. 'I will, reply'd <hi>Cordelia</hi> pleaſantly, provided you quickly reaſſume your good Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, and thereby give me cauſe to think, that this fit of Dulneſs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from ſome ſlight Affliction of ſmall moment. 'Of far leſs moment is my Life, return'd the Prince paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionately, obſerving none near them, nor, if my fears be true, can Time obliterate theſe Sentiments of woe, though it were poſſible that I were forc'd to live ten Thouſand years. Since nothing can mitigate your ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, reply'd that Charmer, the beſt Wiſh your Friends can make is, your fears may prove falſe.</q> 
                  <hi>Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> had neither courage nor opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to ſay more; for the Fryar and <hi>Aminda</hi> came up to them. <hi>Aminda</hi> was of a facetious humour; <hi>Cordelia</hi>'s Relation left to <hi>Sulpitia</hi>'s care; The
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:151648:29"/>
ſame Lady that was in the Garden, when the Prince firſt ſaw the lovely Idol of his fond Deſires. <hi>Aminda</hi> briskly challenges the Fryar, and bid him maintain his Opinion, if he could. <q>What novel Diſpute is it, for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven's ſake, cryes <hi>Cordelia,</hi> you two are ingag'd in? 'I aver, anſwers her Couſin, that no where but in Romances, Perſons fall in Love at the firſt ſight; and only Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and a long Acquaintance can produce a violent Affection. 'I grant you, replies the Fryar, that Love increaſes, and grows to a height by continual Converſation; but ſtill I ſay, a beautiful Idea ſeen once, may make an impreſſion ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Man or Woman, ſufficient to take away their Repoſe. 'Ay, take their Hearts away alſo, to my knowledge, ſaid the Prince earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</q> The Ladies both laughed at that; and <hi>Cordelia</hi> told <hi>Aminda,</hi> ſhe muſt now acquieſce, ſince the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman declar'd againſt her Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:151648:29"/>
upon his own knowledge.</p>
               <p>The Fryar haſtened the Prince to take his leave, ſeeming impatient to talk with him. When they were walking homewards, his Introducer told him, that the time he had limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for his Kinſman's ſtay, was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt expir'd; and ask'd what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs he had made with this deſir'd Freedom, which his Induſtry had procur'd? <q>Alas! ſaid the Prince ſighing, Love hath made a far grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter progreſs in my Heart, than I in my Deſigns.</q> Adding his Reaſons, to believe <hi>Cordelia</hi> was already in Love with another, which was a Thought oppreſs'd him more than he could expreſs. <q>I believe you are miſtaken, reply'd the Fryar; for I have this day heard from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minda</hi> the whole ſtory of the Garden-Rencounter. She tells me her beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Couſin hath often ſigh'd ſince, and mention'd the Cavalier, ſhe there ſaw, with advantageous com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations.</q> This Diſcourſe occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion'd
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:151648:30"/>
the beginning of that Diſpute you heard part of, of loving at firſt ſight.</p>
               <p>No News ever ſurpriz'd, and pleas'd <hi>Alphonſus</hi> like this Kind hope, which, like its contrary, deſpair, is a Lover's attendant; began now to give him great aſſurances. He em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brac'd, careſs'd, and bounteouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Fryar; then flies to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate his Joyes to his Friend. When <hi>Caſtro</hi> had heard him out, and diſcover'd there would be no great obſtructions to a Marriage: he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to conſider the weight of the Concern, and take the freedom his friendſhip allow'd to tell the Prince, that though, when he ſaw him ſo paſſionate, that his life ſeem'd to be at ſtake, he had fooliſhly enough talk'd of a Marriage; yet now, in cooler thoughts, reflecting upon <hi>Otho</hi>'s Temper, who was ambitious beyond meaſure: it muſt needs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volve him in endleſs troubles. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, his long abſence from Court
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:151648:30"/>
would give nouriſhment to ſuch Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, whoſe growth might entan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle him, paſt his beſt skill to diſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage himſelf. But <hi>Alphonſus</hi>'s heart was too deeply prepoſſeſs'd by Love, for ſuch ſaving Counſel to enter; and if the loſs of one muſt be ventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the Dukedom would be in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of running the hazard before <hi>Cordelia.</hi> However to ſooth his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite, he alledged ſome State-Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for his abſence, minding him of his Father's jealous Nature, who abhorr'd his Subjects ſhould make their Court to his Son, whilſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was ſo well able to wield the Reins of Government.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>This you know (went the Prince on) broke the heart of my elder Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whoſe Actions ſtill our Royal Parent frown'd on, becauſe the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple admir'd them too much. Then it follows; whilſt I am abſent from <hi>Otho,</hi> I am nearer in his Affection; Therefore, dear Friend, ſays the Prince, embracing him tenderly,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:151648:31"/>
aſſiſt me to obtain my Miſtreſs; and I will return time enough to my Father.</q> Princes eaſily perſwade, though their Reaſons are weak; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all are willing to oblige them.</p>
               <p>He found it hard to ſpeak alone with <hi>Cordelia,</hi> ſo that he reſolves to write, and get the Fryar to deliver it. The way was eaſie to purchaſe his conſent; Gold and noble Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments did all things with him. After a thouſand alterations, <hi>Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> under the borrow'd Name of <hi>Pedro,</hi> ſent theſe words.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>To the Charming <hi>Cordelia.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>O</hi> Love! plead my Cauſe, and tell the Charming cruel Fair, ſhe muſt forgive the Effects of the moſt violent Paſſion Mortal ever felt! If I have took a Diſguiſe, which becomes me not, ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r'd <hi>Cordelia,</hi> impute it to Love's boundleſs force; and wonder only at the Influence of your Eyes; that with their firſt Glances, could wound ſo ſure, as to fix
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:151648:31"/>
me your Slave for ever. The ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon who beheld you in the Garden, long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to gaze nearer at that reſplendent Light; and now, like the Moth, my liberty is loſt, to fly. Since then my lovely Captivator, you have laid me in ſuch faſt Fetters, make them eaſie with your Smiles; lest your Rigour deſtroy one, who only lives to approve himſelf the</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Faithfulleſt of your Servants,</hi> Pedro.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The Fryar takes charge of it; and as ſoon as he comes to <hi>Sulpitia: Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delia</hi> ask'd him, if his Kinſman was return'd to the Monaſtery? He anſwer'd her only with a ſign to ſpeak with her unobſerv'd: ſhe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding what he meant, goes to a bay Window, and beckon'd to him to follow her, examining what he had to ſay. That Kinſman is not the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:151648:32"/>
                  <q>Perſon you take him for, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed any Kin to me, begins the Fryar, though in you he repoſes a mighty Truſt, when he ventures his Life in your hands. 'Tis true, he has prevailed with me, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nive at things which neither ought to have been done; nor, when done, reveal'd; as I ſuppoſe this Paper will inform you, giving her the Letter.</q> She paus'd at firſt, and was about not to receive it, till con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering her Ghoſtly Father was the Deliverer: ſhe condeſcended, and with an amazing Look retir'd into her Cloſet to peruſe it. When ſhe came back, ſhe told the Fryar, with a compos'd Countenance, he was culpable in a high degree, and that his guilt tranſcended the Genleman's; for the ſevereſt part of the World ſometimes winks at youthful Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagance: but that <hi>He,</hi> whoſe buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs it ought to have been to deterr men from folly, ſhould incourage them in it, was unpardonable. Then
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:151648:32"/>
ſhe urg'd his Infidelity, in ſo horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly betraying that great Truſt her Mother repos'd in him.</p>
               <p>When the poor Prieſt had patiently heard his Charge; for his Excuſe he alledged the danger the Cavalier was in, of making ſome deſperate At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon his Life; how aſſured he was of the Honour of his Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the ſincerity of his Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Then he fell to extolling the Nobleneſs of his Temper, the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Nature; not forgetting the greatneſs of his Eſtate: and in concluſion, preſs'd hard for a favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Anſwer. But <hi>Cordelia,</hi> whoſe Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom far exceeded her years, would return none; only ſaid, ſhe was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to conceal their Crime, becauſe they had made Love of <hi>Her,</hi> the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text for it. With this cold Comfort, the Fryar returns to the impatient Prince; who with a Diamond had juſt wrote this Diſtich in the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:151648:33"/>
                  <l>How ſlowly do the tedious minutes paſs,</l>
                  <l>That drop through expectation's nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row glaſs!</l>
               </q>
               <p>Our Meſſenger out of breath with haſte, and heart-broken, his News was no better, in a ſorrowful Tone delivers his ſtory. But the Prince, who receiv'd it more contentedly than the Fryar durſt hope for; ſince his Miſtreſs neither baniſh'd him her ſight for ever, nor was inrag'd to exceſs, did not wholly deſpair of kinder moments. Then in his Arms he hug'd the dear Procurer of his Happineſs, and told him he long'd again to view that fair one's Eyes, now ſhe knew their Power. <q>That Longing ſhall ſoon be ſatisfy'd an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers the pleas'd F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yar, conſult your Pillow what to ſay, and to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>morrow we will be ſure to attend her.</q> When they came the next day, the young Ladies were both in
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:151648:33"/>
the Garden, and they, being privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd Perſons, went both to them. <hi>Cordelia</hi> bluſh'd at the ſight of the Prince, yet in her heart could ſcarce harbour wrath, when ſhe ſaw his Countenance turn pale, and the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble pangs his fears put him into; ſo that in ſpight of all his Courage, he had like to have fallen.</p>
               <p>There was a ſilent Meeting; eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one being buſily entertain'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. The obliging Fryar call'd <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minda</hi> aſide, to behold the growth of a young Orange-tree they had plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome time before. She obſerv'd the hint, having underſtood the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry from her Couſin: and knowing that, however ſhe diſſembled, ſhe had an inclination to hear him. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus</hi> took this opportunity to caſt himſelf at her feet, and tell her with what a zeal he worſhipp'd her; that ſhe was the perpetual Image of his thoughts, the Object of his deareſt Wiſhes, the Center of all his earthly Happineſs. Whilſt he ſpoke, Love
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:151648:34"/>
trembl'd in his Eyes, and falter'd on his Tongue, giving greater power to his broken Language, than choi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt Eloquence. <hi>Cordelia</hi> forc'd him to riſe; then told him he had already been an Impoſtor, and that in the moſt ſerious matter in the World; therefore he muſt give her leave to doubt him long; and alſo be very cautious of ingaging in an Amour, which ſhe could hardly ever think would be fortunate: it being begun with prophaning a Habit that ought only to be wore by ſacred Perſons. Beſides, ſhe added, ſhe gave up her Will and Actions in a perfect reſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to her Mother, and without her approbation ſhould never proceed in ſo weighty a matter, having no other Friend ſhe durſt rely upon.</p>
               <p>In his Excuſe for his Habit, he ſaid, he hop'd the purity of his Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, with came near to Religion, would in ſome meaſure extenuate his Crime; and for her Mother's content, Heaven had ſo largely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow'd
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:151648:34"/>
him with the Goods of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, he had great reaſon not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair of it: But her Love was wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he beg'd to obtain, ſince withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that, even injoying the World o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Beauty ſhe poſſeſs'd, would prove unſatisfactory; and though no thoughts were ſo terrible, as thoſe which repreſented living withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> her; yet he would ſooner undergo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that exquiſite Torment, than endea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vour to procure <hi>Sulpitia</hi>'s conſent without firſt knowing, whether he gentle Breaſt was compaſſionate e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to receive ſentiments of Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cordelia</hi> gave him a Look, which ſeverely check'd him, for prying ſo narrowly into her ſecret Thougths and told him, ſhe had already im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair'd her Duty in liſtening to ſuch ſtories from a Stranger; nor could ſhe, under much time, digeſt thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> odd beginning, if ever perſwad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> her ſelf to proceed further. At <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> end of theſe words ſhe went to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:151648:35"/>
Company, not giving <hi>Alphonſus</hi> time to anſwer. All the day after, the Prince could not perceive one favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Regard, which terrify'd him to a high degree; and returning to <hi>Caſtro,</hi> he unloads his Boſome with Complaint. Tells him how cold that Sun of Beauty ſhone upon his hopes, and ſuch Romantick ſtuff, as Lovers talk. <hi>Caſtro,</hi> the raiſing of whoſe Fortunes depended upon the favour of his Prince, ſeeing he was too poſitively bent to be perſwaded, reſolv'd to concur with him, and contrive all means poſſible for the obtaining his deſires. The firſt Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in order thereunto (becauſe the Prince would not diſcover himſelf even to <hi>Cordelia;</hi> ſo fearful was he, leſt his Greatneſs ſhould tempt her, without Love, to be his Wife) was the buying an Eſtate ſome miles di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, to ſatisfie the Mother. This <hi>Alphonſus</hi> approv'd of; and he alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hought it convenient the Fryar <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ld go alone, to give <hi>Cordelia</hi> op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:151648:35"/>
to examine him, whilſt his Inſtructions were often repeated to him, That he ſhould ſay <hi>Don Pedro</hi> (as the Prince call'd himſelf) was of a noble Family in <hi>Ferrara;</hi> had an honourable Place in the Duke's Court, and came into that Country to view an Eſtate he had lately pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chas'd. All This for much lov'd Gold, the Fryar went and affirm'd with the greateſt confidence imaginable. <hi>Cordelia</hi> liſten'd to it with much at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, and, bluſhing, ſaid, the Stranger had the Aſpect of a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and muſt make his Addreſs like one, if his Deſires were ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent as he expreſs'd: that being the only way to obtain them. Great were the Aſſurances the Fryar gave <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> at his Return, of the good Inclinations <hi>Cordelia</hi> had for him.</p>
               <p>But 'twas impoſſible at preſent the Prince ſhould follow her Advice, in appearing undiſguis'd at <hi>Sulpitia</hi>'s, both for want of Money to purchaſe an Eſtate, as alſo his returning to
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:151648:36"/>
Court, which was now grown abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary. Therefore he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves to leave <hi>Caſtro</hi> with Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to inquire out an Eſtate; viſit <hi>Cordelia</hi> once more, then haſte to <hi>Ferrara.</hi> When <hi>Cordelia</hi> ſaw him come again in Prieſt's habit, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the item ſhe had ſent him, ſhe turn'd pale, and fear'd he had deceiv'd her. He gueſs'd the cauſe why her countenance chang'd, and bluſh'd, which augmented her Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie. The Fryar obſerv'd their diſorder, and quickly ſet all right again, by taking <hi>Sulpitia</hi> away to conſult of buſineſs, whilſt <hi>Alphonſus</hi> told <hi>Cordelia,</hi> ſuch preſſing occaſions call'd him to Court, that he could not poſſibly evade, without hazarding his utter ruine. He expreſs'd this, and the inviolable Affection he had for her, with ſo becoming a tenderneſs, that he obtain'd from the charming Maid many words and looks of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and as an inſtance of it, ſhe promis'd to repair early to a Lodge
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:151648:36"/>
over the Gate, that ſhe might ſee him paſs Mounted, <hi>en Cavalier.</hi> He ſaid, the longeſt time of his ſtay ſhould not exceed a Month. Obligingly ſhe gave her lovely hand, to preſerve him in her Memory, which he having ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently kiſt, took his leave. The next Morning he appear'd, attended by <hi>Caſtro,</hi> before the Lodge; and <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delia</hi> at a little Window; a place pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited her; though now by ſome contrivance, ſhe had ſtollen to it.</p>
               <p>The Prince look'd extreamly grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; being a Man of an extraordinary make. He ſent up whole Volleys of Sighs to his fair Spectator; who in pitty return'd many; and kindly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving to beſtow a mark of her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour; took a blue Ribbon from her Waſt, that Colour being the Emblem of Conſtancy; and threw down to him. He paſſionately kiſs'd it; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning his Obeiſance with an admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable mien, and fixing his Eyes upon her, full of Love and Tears, he ſeem'd immoveable; till ſhe, fearing ſome
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:151648:37"/>
miſhap, firſt held up her hands to Heaven, for his ſafety: then wav'd them in ſign ſhe would have him go; her ſelf alſo retiring, forc'd him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingly to move forward. <hi>Caſtro</hi> accompanied him part of the way, and taking all needful Inſtructions, return'd, viſited the Friar; and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving what money with him he could conveniently ſpare, gave him a great Charge to obſerve all proceedings at <hi>Sulpitia</hi>'s: and if any thing happen'd prejudicial, to give <hi>Don Pedro</hi> notice at <hi>Ferrara,</hi> by directions they had contriv'd; which ſtill kept them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd. The grateful Friar faithfully promis'd his utmoſt aſſiſtance, and <hi>Caſtro</hi> began his Perigrination, to ſeek an Eſtate that wanted a Purchaſer. In this time of abſence, there happen'd a Contrivance at <hi>Sulpitia</hi>'s, that was very near ruining all their Deſigns.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luſetta,</hi> whom I mention'd at the beginning of the ſtory, being diſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for her infidelity, repairs to the Kinſwoman who had ſet her at
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:151648:37"/>
work, and meets again with <hi>Don Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rado;</hi> where diſcourſing of theſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointments, ſhe gives ſuch a lively Deſcription of the Beautiful <hi>Cordelia,</hi> that rekindles his Curioſity. So no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing now will ſatisfy him, without ſeeing her. But the means, there was the difficulty. After many ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſolutions, <hi>Luſetta</hi> remember'd a humour of <hi>Cordelia</hi>'s, how ſhe was always very fond of ſeeing the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles, ſtragling Women carry about to ſell.</p>
               <p>In this dreſs <hi>Don Ferado</hi> is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis'd; buys a world of litte Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, fine Beads, and ſuch Trin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets; goes with them, and hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately admittance into the Houſe. The young Ladies, having notice, come about him; the was not a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſeek, which was <hi>Cordelia,</hi> but ſo amaz'd at her Beauty, that he ſtood gazing without power to move. <hi>Cordelia</hi> bluſh'd to ſee the Woman, as ſhe took her to be, look ſo earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtly, and minded her of her Things.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:151648:38"/>
This rous'd the Spark a little from his Contemplation; yet ſtill his Eyes could fix on no other Object. When ſhe had furniſh'd her ſelf with the Toys ſhe fancy'd moſt; he was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs'd. He returns in love, to that degree, that he thought of nothing but propoſing a Marriage; though it was abſolutely inconvenient; his Circumſtances requiring a Fortune; having many Siſters to Portion. Yet ſo amiable, <hi>Cordelia</hi> appear'd; that whatever Conſideration intereſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd, Love turned the Scale; and he follows his deſires, with precipitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; employing a Friend the very next day, to ſolicite <hi>Sulpitia;</hi> who approves of the matter; gives leave to his Seranades; ſeveral of which were perform'd before <hi>Cordelia</hi> knew from whom, or ſo much as gueſs'd her Mother was conſenting. Till that diſcreet Lady, thinking it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to ſound her Daughter's inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, began to break the deſign to her. Firſt commands her to follow
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:151648:38"/>
into the Lodge, and ſhows her <hi>Don Ferado,</hi> bravely accoutred; prancing upon his great Horſe. Words cannot expreſs <hi>Cordelia</hi>'s ſurprize; her Mind was already fill'd with an Idea, too admirable for <hi>Ferado</hi> ever to hope an Entrance; and compar'd to the Prince her partial Heart, being prepoſſeſs'd with Love; made him appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath her regard; much leſs eſteem. She pretends indiſpoſition; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tires to her Chamber. <hi>Sulpitia</hi> ſaw her much diſturb'd; but was wholly ignorant of the cauſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cordelia</hi> inſtantly acquaints the Friar with this affair; declares her averſion, and deſires him to inform <hi>Don Pedro.</hi> The good Man goes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it with ſpeed, and diſpatches his Intelligence to <hi>Ferrara,</hi> according to his directions. This information comes to the Prince, juſt as <hi>Caſtro</hi> had ſent word of an Eſtate, he had pitch'd upon. The Prieſt's news heartily tormented <hi>Alphonſus;</hi> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he was infinitely pleas'd, <hi>Corde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:151648:39"/>
order'd he ſhould know of it. The careful Friar had writ every circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of <hi>Don Ferado</hi>'s Fortunes; and the Prince, with reaſon, look'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, as a formidable Rival; being a Neighbour, which, in all probability would induce <hi>Sulpitia</hi> to embrace his Intereſt, before the Prince's; who muſt of neceſſity be often abſent, that is, if he kept his Quality conceal'd; which he could not, without running great hazards, avoid. Therefore he reſolves to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move this <hi>Don Ferado;</hi> and to that end gets, by other hands, a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion for a Regiment of Horſe, and ſends to him; with Orders, that he ſhould ſpeedily repair to Court. <hi>Ferado</hi> could not imagine what ſecret Friends had done him this favour; however he was advis'd by all his Acquaintance, to embrace it: they convincing him, how much it would conduce, both to his profit and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. Great was the Conflict; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and Glory were powerful Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments;
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:151648:39"/>
but eager wiſhes, and fierce deſires all centr'd in <hi>Cordelia,</hi> were more pleaſing. Theſe dear tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting Flames he nouriſh'd; but <hi>Cordelia</hi> blaſted; for there he could diſcover only frowns, diſdain, and freezing coldneſs. All that love him, urge his going; and flattering hope perſwades he may return Crown'd with Lawrel; at which the Cruel Maid, overcome by Conſtancy and Courage, may yield to longing love. Such thoughts at length prevail with him; and he ſets forward to the Court of <hi>Ferrara,</hi> juſt as <hi>Alphonſus</hi> had left it; who poſts away to <hi>Caſtro;</hi> takes care for the payment of the Money that was to be given for the Eſtate; puts ſervants into it, with orders to furniſh the Houſe neatly, and with riches, ſuitable to his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Quality: though he ſpar'd Magnificence.</p>
               <p>He had made himſelf very fine, and brought many conſiderable Preſents for <hi>Cordelia;</hi> and having put all
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:151648:40"/>
things at his new Manſion, in their deſign'd Poſture; he haſtens, with <hi>Caſtro,</hi> to his Belov'd Miſtreſs. As ſoon as ever they arriv'd at the Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, the Friar was acquainted with it, who flies with the news to <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delia;</hi> and humbly deſires her from her Subject, yea and Slave, <hi>Don Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dro,</hi> to prepare <hi>Sulpitia</hi> with a full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of all the foregoing adventure. The young Lady trembl'd at the Task; but Love mann'd her Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and ſhe, on her Knees, relates the ſtory to her Mother. <hi>Sulpitia</hi>'s Amazement, when ſhe heard theſe unexpected Practices, is ſcarce to be conceiv'd; however being a Woman largely indowed with Wiſdome, and Deſcretion; ſhe perceiv'd her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter's Inclination, by her palliating the crime of his diſguiſe, and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting every action favourably of this cunning Lover's. Therefore ſhe conſider'd, being ever indulgent to her Daughter, if ſhe ſhould now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe her Authority; ſhe might
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:151648:40"/>
ſooner break her heart, than bend it. Theſe thoughts induce her to give way to his coming; ſetting her ſelf to inquire after his Eſtate; which finding according to his word, and being afterwards, by his Converſation, acquainted with his Merit, grew very fond of him; freely giving her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent towards the obtaining his ador'd <hi>Cordelia.</hi> Whom he, with all love's Oratory, purſues; falls on his Knees, embraces hers, weeps, and talks till he forces a Confeſſion; till ſhe, bluſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, acknowledges her Affection; owns ſhe hath lov'd him from the firſt moment ſhe ſaw him. The Tranſported Prince longs for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation of his deſires, and preſſes with his utmoſt Rhetorick a ſpeedy Marriage. Which is at length agreed to, and perform'd, in <hi>Sulpitia</hi>'s Chappel, by the often-mention'd Friar, before <hi>Sulpitia, Aminda,</hi> and <hi>Caſtro.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>None ever appear'd over-joy'd or fond, like this Amorous Prince, his
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:151648:41"/>
doting ſtill increas'd, every time he ſaw her, he ſeem'd captivated anew; and, as in a well drawn Piece, the longer we gaze, the more graces we eſpy; ſo her charms to the admiring <hi>Alphonſus</hi> were endleſs; yet ſtill his intereſt bound him to keep his Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity conceal'd being a ſecret, he durſt not divulge to her. Thus privately they liv'd and enjoy'd themſelves for two years, the Prince being often abſent, and long; which he always ſaid was occaſion'd by his place at Court. Juſt as the firſt Year of Wedlock was expir'd, <hi>Cordelia</hi> Crown'd the enſuing, with the birth of a Son, to whom the pleaſed Prince gave his own Name <hi>Alphonſus.</hi> A continu'd ſeries of uninterrupted Happineſs attended theſe Ladies for the preceeding years; <hi>Sulpitia</hi> never parting from her Daughter, and <hi>Caſtro,</hi> the example of his Prince, Lov'd, Courted, and married <hi>Aminda;</hi> a Lady of a deſirable Beauty, and agreeable Converſation. By the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:151648:41"/>
borrow'd name of <hi>Phillipo,</hi> he wedded her, and ſhe ſtill continu'd with her much Lov'd Couſin.</p>
               <p>But Fortune now grew aſham'd of longer confining ſuch Illuſtrious Perſons to ſo dull a Sphere, as the Country. For <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> coming to the Dukedome, by the death of <hi>Otho,</hi> after the firſt hurry of his affairs was over; diſpatches <hi>Caſtro</hi> to fetch the beloved <hi>Cordelia, Sulpitia,</hi> and his own Wife <hi>Aminda,</hi> to Court. The Faithful Friar, no doubt would have attended them, and been ſufficiently advanc'd but unkind Death prevented his preferment; he deceaſing, to all their griefs, a little before. <hi>Caſtro</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives acquaints <hi>Cordelia</hi> with her Husbands deſires, to ſee her, and <hi>Sulpitia</hi> at <hi>Ferrara;</hi> ſtill concealing, by the Duke's Order, his Quality. The Ladies willingly embrace the offer, and aſſoon as poſſible, begin their journey; and in good time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded it. He brings his fair Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers to a Houſe, near the Court,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:151648:42"/>
where, at night, the new Duke comes; leaving the Court privately, and going to them in his uſual dreſs, ſo that they had not the leaſt umbrage of ſuſpition.</p>
               <p>The only deſign the Duke had in this, was, the pleaſure of ſurprizing <hi>Cordelia;</hi> which is thus effected. On the morrow, <hi>Alphonſus</hi> leaves them betimes on pretence of extraordinary buſineſs, but he tells them, to make amends for his abſence, <hi>Don Phillipo,</hi> when they are dreſs'd, ſhall have them to Court, and ſhow them the Duke's Palace; which they are much pleas'd with. They prepare for this fine ſight, and <hi>Caſtro</hi> attends them. Through all thoſe richly furniſh'd Apartments, he conducts his wandring ſpectators; where they behold the Chairs of ſtate, the Tables, Andirons, Pictures, Frames, Glaſs-Frames; all either Gold, or Silver. They admire this Magnificence, and alſo are aſtoniſh'd to ſee, with what reſpect, all that paſs ſalute <hi>Caſtro.</hi> After they had
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:151648:42"/>
tir'd themſelves with viewing va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious objects of Majeſtick Glorious Finery, he leads them to a Garden; where in a lovely Banqueting-Houſe, a Breakfaſt is prepar'd of all manner of varieties, and delicate cool Wines; which, whilſt they are entertain'd at, <hi>Cordelia</hi> diſcourſes of the bravery they had ſeen; and ſmiling upon <hi>Caſtro,</hi> ſaid, <q>I believe my husband, and you are Courtiers; but I begin to doubt yee for Politicians: for now you have diſcover'd to your Wife, and me, the gawdy ſplendor of a Court: ſuppoſe we ſhould fall in love with it, and with reluctancy return to our Country habitations. We are prepar'd for that, anſwers <hi>Caſtro;</hi> your ſtation, Madam, being to Reign here; nor will <hi>Aminda,</hi> I hope, diſlike hers. I know not what you mean ſays <hi>Cordelia,</hi> with a ſurpriz'd look. I mean, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies cunningly turning it; that where e'er Beauty, like yours, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, it, of neceſſity, muſt Reign,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:151648:43"/>
ſince all muſt quit their claims, for ſoveraignity, when you approach. So, Daughter, cries <hi>Sulpitia</hi> pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, you believ'd <hi>Don Philippo</hi> a Courtier, and now I think he hath prov'd himſelf a great one, by his compliment.</q> When their repaſt and diſcourſe was ended, <hi>Caſtro</hi> begins a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen to endeavour ſatisfying their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied Curioſity, in ſhowing them the delightful Gardens that belong to the Palace, which <hi>Italy</hi> can ſcarce equal; though <hi>Italy</hi> is the Garden of the World. He tells them, that he hath yet a ſight which exceeds all they have ſeen; that is the Duke at Dinner. This they are wondrous deſirous of, <hi>Cordelia</hi> grows very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitive, what mighty affair detains her Husband, grieving much that he doth not participate in this Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and Entertainment. <hi>Caſtro</hi> promis'd to ſatisfy her in that alſo, in a little time. When Dinner was near, he brings them to a Cloſet, where, unobſerv'd, through a Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:151648:43"/>
they might plainly ſee, all the Ceremony. After they had a while admir'd the melodious Muſick, and ſtately order of the Preparations: the Duke appear'd inviron'd with Nobles, ſo that at firſt, they could not eaſily diſtinguiſh him.</p>
               <p>But when they came to have their full views, each look'd amazedly on the other. At length, ſaith <hi>Sulpitia,</hi> either we are in one of thoſe enchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Caſtles, we read of in Romances, where all ſeen is Illuſion, or <hi>that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> in the Duke's Chair is really my Son in Law <hi>Don Pedro.</hi> Did not I tell you, Madam, ſaid <hi>Caſtro,</hi> ſmiling, and addreſſing to <hi>Cordelia,</hi> that I would ſhow you your Husband preſently? What does he mean, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers that fair one gravely, to dazle thus ones Eyes, with Pageant-Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? Why doth he uſurp the place of his Sovereign? It is no Uſurpation, nor are you deceiv'd, replies <hi>Caſtro,</hi> for the ſame Prince that has prov'd an indulgent Husband under the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:151648:44"/>
borrow'd name of <hi>Pedro,</hi> no doubt will continue ſo; when he owns him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> Duke of <hi>Ferrara,</hi> and <hi>Modena. Cordelia</hi> could not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt this unexpected ſcene of great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, without a viſible alteration, both in her Countenance, and health; ſo that <hi>Caſtro</hi> was forc'd to Conduct her back to her Lodging. <hi>Sulpitia</hi> and <hi>Aminda</hi> accompany'd her. When the ſurprize was over, and they were all deſcanting on theſe proceedings; <hi>Aminda</hi> comes up very ſeriouſly to <hi>Don Castro;</hi> pray my dear, ſaid ſhe, what muſt I call you? for I hope you have follow'd my Lord <hi>Alphonſus</hi>'s Example, and are ſome great perſon in diſguiſe? This ſet them all a Laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and <hi>Caſtro</hi> told her ſhe would time enough know his Quality; his greateſt happineſs being to have ſo kind a wife as her ſelf, and ſo good a Maſter as the Royal <hi>Alphonſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That Afternoon, ſeveral rich ſuits of Cloaths and Cabinets of Diamonds were brought to the young Dutcheſs.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:151648:44"/>
The next day, ſhe was, with great Pomp, receiv'd at Court, and by <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus</hi> own'd, lov'd, carreſs'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond meaſure. That great reſpect and kindneſs, the Duke always ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour'd <hi>Cordelia</hi> with, taught all the Court to do the ſame. And this Beautiful Lady was ſo fram'd, and compos'd for her greatneſs; that ſhe became it to a Miracle. Young <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus</hi> was quickly ſent for, and nurtur'd according to his Quality. Eighteen years <hi>Cordelia</hi> grac'd the Court of <hi>Ferrara,</hi> and bleſt the Arms of good <hi>Alphonſus.</hi> But then, to ſhow us that Worldly happineſs is ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom permanent, that Inſatiate Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Death, whoſe inhumanity ſpares neither the Fair, the young, or brave, raviſhes from the fond <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> this ſoft Wife. Which irreparable loſs, it being impoſſible for time or nature to repay, the Duke mourns to that exceſſive rate, that the enſuing Year he alſo dyes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> the only Son and Heir
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:151648:45"/>
to this departed Hero; the perſon who hath occaſion'd this relation, is Proclaim'd Duke of <hi>Ferrara,</hi> and <hi>Modena.</hi> He had not long been in poſſeſſion of it: before <hi>Ferado,</hi> who was now grown a popular Man, and had a ſettl'd picque againſt the Royal Family, for the loſs of <hi>Cordelia,</hi> (ſo implacable and immovable is the hatred which proceeds from love re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd) ſtarts a Queſtion concerning <hi>Alphonſus</hi>'s Legitimacy; and boldly affirms, the late Duke was never marry'd. He knew well, all the Witneſſes were dead, except <hi>Aminda;</hi> and one Woman's word, would never convince a World; that is generally fonder of lies than Truth. This ſtrange aſperſion alarm'd the whole Court, and moſt of the Neighbouring Princes. In all Courts there are factious perſons, &amp; perſons deſirous of change; though they were ſure 'twere for the worſt. Many of theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oin with <hi>Don Ferado,</hi> and demand a clear proof of the Marriage, which <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> not
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:151648:45"/>
being able to give, they appeal to Pope <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the Eighth; Who, willing to ingroſs the Soveraignty himſelf, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares againſt the preſent Duke; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels him to retire to his ancient Dutchy of <hi>Modena;</hi> which their utmoſt malice could not pretend to deprive him of.</p>
               <p>This is the Prince, who, remaining privately at <hi>Rome,</hi> to ſolicite his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Holyneſs for the regaining his right in <hi>Ferrara,</hi> has ſeen you: and left his heart and liberty at your Feet. His many applications to me, for the furtherance of his affairs, have given me opportunity to be throughly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with him: and I have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd ſuch a Noble goodneſs in his temper that he does truly excel all others of his Sex. From him I had the foregoing ſtory, which perhaps to you might ſound Romantick, becauſe I ſo punctually related each particular; but my hearing it often from this Prince <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> had deeply impreſs'd every circumſtance in my memory. I would not undertake to be his
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:151648:46"/>
Advocate, eſpecially, my Dear to you, (went <hi>Olimpia</hi> on, with the kindeſt aſpect in the world:) did I not know him well; and alſo know that my intereſt with his Holyneſs, is of that large extent, as to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſh this Prince, in the Throne of his Anceſtors. But I am convinc'd, he is in love to that degree; that all the Kingdoms of the Earth can never make him happy, without your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.</p>
               <p>The Trouble his Father hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved him in, (anſwers <hi>Melora</hi>) by matching privately, and below his dignity, ought, in common Prudence, to deterr this Gentleman, from any ſuch deſign. Oh, my fair one! (replies <hi>Olimpia</hi>) who can behold you and be deterr'd from loving, by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of intereſt? But however repugnant it is to his intereſt (ſhe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded gravely) I am ſure it is very conſpicuous, it agrees with yours, to liſten kindly to the propoſals of a Prince, who offers his Heart and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:151648:46"/>
Crown, without any other conditions, than your acceptance of it. Yet with cloſeſt Secrecy, this muſt be manag'd: for many of the Italian Princes will be drawn to aſſiſt him, in hopes of his Matching into their Families. And I believe you your ſelf would tax any perſon with egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious folly, that ſhould refuſe to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept an ineſtimable preſent, becauſe given in the dark: when afterwards they'd have privilege to make uſe of it before all the World.</p>
               <p>A Scene of greatneſs ſtrait appear'd to <hi>Melora;</hi> and ſhe with the Eye of Fancy, beheld her ſelf ſeated in a Palace, attended by perſons, born above her. Women are generally ambitious, and opinionated of their own merit; and though <hi>Melora</hi> might juſtly boat ſhe had one of the largeſt portions of Wit, and Diſcretion: yet ſhe was a woman pertook of the frailty of her Sex; was willing to believe this fine ſtory; and let theſe Glorious thoughts appear pleaſing.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:151648:47"/>
Which <hi>Olimpia</hi> perceiving, augments theſe towring Joys, deſcribing the pleaſures of Pomp, and Splendor; extolling the happineſs of being plac'd where Ten Thouſand admiring Eyes would be fix'd upon her; all watching the Motion of hers; to fly at her commands. Thus ſhe cunningly turns the gawdy ſide of greatneſs to this young Creature's view, hiding the thorns and fatal viciſſitudes, which too too often attend power, had her Lover been Duke of <hi>Modena.</hi> But (alas!) Unhappy Beauty, thy Malicious Stars have pointed Thee a ſad and gloomy Fate; which ſhe is thus conducted to. <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limpia</hi> takes <hi>Melora</hi> to a fine village of hers, near <hi>Rome,</hi> after ſhe had prevail'd with the deceiv'd Lady to ſee this pretended Prince. The Cardinal, whoſe luſt gave him Ideas, that every moment, put him into raptures, comes, by <hi>Olimpia</hi>'s ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, in the night, to this Country Houſe, attended only by a
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:151648:47"/>
young Gentleman, whoſe ſcanty fortunes the Cardinal had augmented, and thereby indear'd him to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. This Perſon is acquainted with the whole deſign; which he brooks not well, being a Gentleman, and hating ſuch diſhonourable proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. But intereſt overcomes theſe Heroick ſentiments; and <hi>Franciſco</hi> (for that was his name) promiſes his utmoſt aſſiſtance. <hi>Antonio Barbarino</hi> is adorn'd with a World of finery to appear amiable; his Hatband is of Diamonds of almoſt an ineſtimable value, and every <hi>particular</hi> expreſſes as much magnificence, as poſſible. He keeps himſelf conceal'd, by <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limpia</hi>'s advice, till next day; who thus contrives his appearance.</p>
               <p>She takes this day to ſhow <hi>Melora</hi> the fineries of the Houſe, and Gardens. In the midſt of the Garden, ſtood a Banqueting-Houſe, painted by the moſt famous of that ingenious Art. One ſide was <hi>Ida</hi>'s Plain, and <hi>Paris</hi> the lovelieſt youth, that pencil ever
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:151648:48"/>
drew, ſtanding with his ſheephook, before three contending Goddeſſes. He had juſt preſented <hi>Venus</hi> with the Apple; who, by her pleaſing ſmiles, adds to the vaſt Beauty the Painter had given her. Then in <hi>Juno,</hi> Envy, and threatning was ſo plainly deline<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, that you could ſcarce view her without fear. <hi>Pallas</hi> look'd with a noble ſcorn, as ſhe knew her own Merit, and deſpis'd the Opinion of her Judge. When the Painter pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd this ſtory to me, ſaid <hi>Olimpia,</hi> I forbad him doing it; remembring in the Fable, the Goddeſſes appear'd naked. The Limner gueſs'd my ſcruple, and told me, I was miſtaken in his deſign: for he would dreſs them all in Garbs, ſo becoming, that ſhould ſooner bribe a Judg, than naked Beauties. I think he hath been as good as his word, anſwers <hi>Melora,</hi> for that looſe Sky-colour'd Robe of <hi>Juno's</hi> is admirable, nor is <hi>Venus</hi>'s Crimſon of leſs finery; it gives a Luſtre to her Skin. In my fancy, replies <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limpia</hi>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:151648:48"/>
the ſilver Armour of <hi>Pallas,</hi> which reaches to her knees, and thoſe ſhining Buskins, that diſcover her Graceful Legs, exceed far the other. But behold here, added <hi>Olimpia,</hi> tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the other ſide of the room; and give me your opinion of this.</p>
               <p>It was the Fable of <hi>Iphis</hi>'s mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage; who, by his Mother's Prayer, was Metamorphos'd into Man. Firſt you beheld the Mother, devoutly kneeling; whilſt in <hi>Iphis,</hi> you began to diſcover the effects of her Prayer. His Looks ſhow'd amazement, and his lovely Hair turn'd upon one Cheek, in ſhort Curls, the other hung down diſhevel'd a little farther. He appear'd jocund; his Face Manly; with his fair Bride, and all the ſplendour of a ſolemn Nuptial. Theſe excellent pieces were incompaſs'd with Feſtoons of Flowers, incomparably done. After <hi>Melora</hi> had ſufficiently prais'd, and admir'd this ſurprizingly fine Painting; <hi>Olimpia</hi> deſires her to ſit down, in this delightful place, and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:151648:49"/>
requeſts her to ſing the ſong, ſhe lov'd; ſaying there was an excellent Eccho; which mightily helpt the voice. <hi>Melora,</hi> amongſt her numerous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, had this in the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree: for all the judicious that ever heard her, own'd her skill and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs unequal'd. The Cardinal was conducted by <hi>Beatrice, Olimpia's</hi> woman, to the door of the Room; where he ſtood. No Princeſs liv'd greater in <hi>Rome,</hi> than the Princeſs <hi>Olimpia,</hi> and the had ſeveral Perſons of good Quality her Attendants: but this <hi>Beatrice</hi> ſuited beſt her incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and was her chiefeſt Favorite. When the Friendſhip firſt began between <hi>Olimpia</hi> and <hi>Melora,</hi> this ſubtile Woman grew very uneaſy, fearing a Rival in her Lady's Heart. But when the Cruel <hi>Olimpia</hi> intruſted her with the whole matter, and ſhe ſaw this height was only the Prologue to her ruine, the malicious Wretch was infinitely pleas'd; and the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal's Preſents following, made her
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:151648:49"/>
very aſſiduous in theſe wicked practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. <hi>Melora,</hi> ignorant of any unſeen hearer, immediately obey'd <hi>Olimpia</hi>'s Commands; and, with a charming Air, ſung the following words.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="song">
                           <head>A SONG.</head>
                           <lg>
                              <l>AS young <hi>Aminta</hi> ſtood and view'd</l>
                              <l>The Beauties of th' approaching Year,</l>
                              <l>She ſigh'd to think how ſoon they would</l>
                              <l>Wither, grow old, and diſappear.</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Strephon,</hi> who long had ask'd relief,</l>
                              <l>But always beg'd and pray'd in vain;</l>
                              <l>Hop'd more Advantage from her grief</l>
                              <l>Than he before could er'e obtain.</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg>
                              <l>Beware ſaid he, my Life, my All,</l>
                              <l>Deſtroying Time comes on apace</l>
                              <l>Your faireſt Charms muſt one day fall,</l>
                              <l>And Age and Wrinkles fill their place.</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg>
                              <l>Improve your Youth now that remains,</l>
                              <l>For Age does too too faſt purſue;</l>
                              <l>
                                 <pb n="88" facs="tcp:151648:50"/>Be kind at laſt, requite my pains,</l>
                              <l>And give to Love, and me their due.</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg>
                              <l>Then fly fair Nymph into any Arms,</l>
                              <l>Whilst Youth, and Wit, and Beauty laſt;</l>
                              <l>The Spring and Summer have no Charms,</l>
                              <l>Which envious Winter will not blaſt.</l>
                           </lg>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Juſt as ſhe ended, the Cardinal ſteps forth; only bowing to <hi>Olimpia,</hi> whilſt he eagerly addreſſes to <hi>Melora;</hi> and fixing his Eyes upon her, cries in a Paſſionate Tone; <q>Ah Madam! I was enough your ſlave before; and in my raviſh'd fancy, call'd you all divine, but now I heard your Angelick Voice, I am convinc'd you came into the World ſome extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary way; and are really one of the bright Inhabitants of Heaven. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, with Juſtice, you may deſpiſe the ſighs of groveling Mortals.</q> 
                  <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lora</hi> was ſtrangely ſurpriz'd at his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing without the leaſt warning; and turning to <hi>Olimpia,</hi> her face being
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:151648:50"/>
cover'd with bluſhes ſaid; <q>This is unkind, dear Princeſs, to let a ſtranger be Witneſs of your Servants fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and unprepar'd receive ſuch palpable flattery. Nay, Madam, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns <hi>Olimpia,</hi> bend all anger againſt the Prince, and I will join with you; for I think 'tis inexcuſable in his Highneſs to ſurprize us thus without notice.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>All Meſſengers ſeem'd too ſlow for my impatiency, replies that Impoſtor, nor could my own feet, though wing'd with deſire, and love, conduct me half ſo faſt as my wiſhes, to throw my ſelf before this ador'd Beauty. Ceaſe Prince, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupts <hi>Olimpia,</hi> for I read diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in <hi>Melora's</hi> Eyes; this new ſtrange Theme diſturbs her. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert us with the news of Rome; ſure that great City cannot live a day without follies, ridiculous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to make us laugh. If my Tongue muſt, (anſwers <hi>Barbarino</hi>) leave the dear delightful ſubject of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:151648:51"/>
my Life <hi>my Love;</hi> I hope you'll give my Eyes and ſighs the liberty to ſpeak the Language of my Heart. That we may venture to allow, I think, replies <hi>Melora;</hi> becauſe wee can have the privilege, not to obſerve them, and only liſten to your news; which we both expect (adds <hi>Olimpia.</hi>) The freſheſt; I know, (begins the Cardinal very gravely) is of a great judgment, that is lately fallen on a fair young Lady. This Lady had an humble ſervant, whom the World call'd very deſerving, but the Cruel Maid thought otherwiſe; and, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Days, and Nights, and Months, ſpent all in Sighs and Prayers and Tears; yet her obdurate Heart feels no compaſſion. Nothing the Amorous Youth neglected, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſay, or act, that might have gain'd a kinder doom, though all in vain; which when he plainly found, o'rewhelm'd with love, and deep deſpair, he languiſh'd a
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:151648:51"/>
ſhort time; then made his Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Exit. Still the remorſeleſs Maid was unconcern'd; only Civility and Honour obliged her to attend him to his Grave. And leſt her Spectators ſhould there cenſure her guilty of Barbarity, ſhe cunningly conveys an Onion into her Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerchief, to ſupply the defect of Natural Tears. But now obſerve the Juſtice of her Fate; for, from that moment, ſo violent a conflux of Rheum follow'd, that ſhe, for ever weeps, ſpight of all the Phyſician's Art. And if in any Company where Mirth prevails, then the ſtreams run down, enough to fright them with the apprehenſions of a ſecond Deluge.</q> Is not <hi>this,</hi> Ladies, (concluded the Cardinal) a ſufficient warning to deterr you from Cruelty? They both laugh'd at the Roman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick News, and <hi>Melora</hi> ſaid pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the greateſt Miracle ſhe found in the ſtory, was, the Gallant dying for Love; that being, in theſe Ages,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:151648:52"/>
altogether unpractis'd, and out of faſhion. In ſuch Converſation they in ſecret paſs'd their hours, whilſt the Cardinal forgot not to improve them; but by a Thouſand Glances, Sighs, and Whiſpers, told <hi>Melora,</hi> that he dy'd, unleſs ſhe in gentle pity ſav'd him. Such great Perſons wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted nothing, that either Art or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture could afford, for their Pleaſure, and Diverſion: What they had told <hi>Melora</hi> of the Duke's being <hi>incognito</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> took off her miſtruſt when ſhe ſaw him cautious to appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any, but <hi>Olimpia</hi> her ſelf, <hi>Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice,</hi> and <hi>Franciſco.</hi> Every thing contributed towards the deceiving this poor Lady; the general diſcourſe of <hi>Rome;</hi> which was, of the Duke of <hi>Modena</hi>'s pretenſions to the Dukedom of <hi>Ferrara;</hi> and that Princes abſence from his own Court, being often in the Courts of other Princes, ſolliciting Aid, in caſe the Pope deny'd him Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: But theſe many circumſtances were needleſs; for though <hi>Melora</hi>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:151648:52"/>
had a Vivacity in her Wit, peculiar to her ſelf; a Judgment perſpicuous and clear; yet ſo cunningly had <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limpia,</hi> by her ſeeming Fondneſs, and artful Inſinuations, wrought upon the goodneſs of her temper; that ſhe believ'd whatever that falſe one af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd, ſtedfaſtly, as an Article of her Faith.</p>
               <p>After two days the Cardinal takes leave with all the paſſionate dearneſs Man can expreſs; returns to <hi>Rome,</hi> whither the Ladies quickly follow: <hi>Olimpia</hi> ſtill preſſing her fair Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite to be kind to this deſerving Prince, as ſhe always terms him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Melora</hi> was now wholly in the Princeſs <hi>Olimpia</hi>'s Palace, only going every day to viſit her Father; and every Night the Love-ſick Cardinal paid his devoir to her. Yet ſpight of all theſe conſtant Viſits, and reitera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Oaths of continual Love; <hi>Melora</hi> appears but cold, and expreſſes her ſelf with a World of caution and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation. This Torments the Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:151648:53"/>
Prieſt beyond meaſure. Now, though <hi>Melora</hi> abſolutely confided in <hi>Olimpia,</hi> her good Education had perfectly taught her to obey her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Will; and to undertake ſo great a Concern, without his Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, ſhock'd all her reſolves, and daſh'd her with a Thouſand Fears. <hi>Olimpia</hi> ſtrives her utmoſt to incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the beauteous trembling Maid; and in perſwaſive Arguments lays down the inconveniency of acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her, Father: for he being a Loyal Man, and in a publick ſtation, would certainly diſcover it to the King his Maſter; which would at preſent ruine the Prince <hi>Alphonſus</hi> in all his deſigns. <hi>Melora</hi> liſten'd to whatever <hi>Olimpia</hi> urg'd; gave obliging An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, but delay'd complying. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was ſo hateful to the Cardinal and <hi>Olimpia,</hi> as this protracting time, becauſe they lay liable to a hundred accidents that might betray them; by which the Cardinal would irrevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cably loſe his Fame; and, what
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:151648:53"/>
was much dearer, <hi>Melora.</hi> Therefore the next time they are together, he pleads with all his Loves Eagerneſs and Oratory; tells his fair Miſtreſs, his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires were grown to ſuch a height of Violence, that without her conſent to the fulfilling them, they would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly prey upon his Life, and from her Adorer he ſhould become her Martyr. <q>Ah Madam! (went he on, ſighing paſſionately, and graſp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Knees) Why are you thus Cruel? Why do you force me to live in theſe Inſupportable Agonies, when 'tis in your power to raiſe me to endleſs Worlds of Bliſs? Is not the Appellation of Kind and Pitiful more pleaſing to you, than the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage Names of Cruel and Rigorous? With what reaſon (reply'd that Charmer ſweetly) My Lord, can you Complain, or ask me more? Have I not already broke the Sacred Laws of Duty, which I us'd to hold Inviolable, and receiv'd you here Clandeſtinely: heard all the ſtories
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:151648:54"/>
of your Love, and only reſolv'd to take ſuch time as may confirm the Conſtancy and Faith, which you, with ſo much Rhetorick, have Vow'd.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>In that reſolve you give me Death (ſaid he, with a ſad Air) and e'er my probation ends, you'll be convinc'd, by the ſublimeſt Proof, that I am yours.</q> When he ſaid this, he takes his leave, and before he left the Houſe, relates all this to <hi>Franciſco;</hi> ordering him to ſtay, till <hi>Olimpia</hi> was at leiſure to hear it; and ſend him her advice in theſe perplexities. Through the Gardens, and Walks of <hi>Donna Olimpia</hi>'s Palace, the Cardinal always went home, only paſſing a narrow Lane, he came to a back door of his own, where a Servant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly attended: <hi>One,</hi> who, many Years, had been acquainted with his Debauchees, and Night Rambles, though he was not truſted with the ſtory of this Intrigue. <hi>Barbarino</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Melancholy through the before
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:151648:54"/>
mention'd Lane was ſurpriz'd, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the darkneſs of the Night, and lateneſs of the hour, to perceive the glittering of Swords; and ſtepping haſtily to avoid them, one immediately ruſh'd upon him, and gave him a Wound in his Breaſt; at which the amaz'd Cardinal cry'd out, Villains! Aſſaſſinates! Hearing his Voice they fled; only ſaying, Damn it, we were miſtaken in our Man.</p>
               <p>'Twas very near the Cardinal's private Door, this accident happen'd, and the Servant that waited for him, having skill in Surgery, he truſted him to ſearch the Wound; who aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd the frighted Prieſt, that there was no danger; only the loſs of Blood would, for ſome Days, confine him to his Bed, and Chamber. He then began to revive his Courage, and Commanded the Servant to ſay, his Illneſs proceeded from a violent bleeding at the Noſe; which took him in the Night: this paſs'd upon
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:151648:55"/>
his Phyſicians; who only order'd him comfortable Cordials to renew his Spirits.</p>
               <p>The next Morning, the Cardinal found himſelf at eaſe enough, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider his Love affair, and accordingly diſpatches <hi>Franciſco,</hi> to acquaint <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limpia</hi> with his Misfortune; and to beg, her Almighty Wit would make ſome advantage of it with his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs. One would have thought, the Heavens ſending the Miſchief, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd another, on the Cardinal's Head, might have deterr'd them from pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing further the ruine of that ſoft <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent,</hi> the fair <hi>Melora;</hi> but they were harden'd, and <hi>Olimpia,</hi> reſolving to fulfil the deſires of the Friend of her darling Luſt, Ambition, manag'd with Woman's Cunning, her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Melora</hi> obſerv'd <hi>Olimpia</hi> Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly; and her fondneſs and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularity to her, laid aſide; and for three days only Complacency, and cold Civility remain'd. This per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex'd
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:151648:55"/>
her ſtrangely; fain ſhe would have ask'd the reaſon; long'd to know the cauſe of the Duke's (as ſhe thought him) abſence; but Modeſty, the Virgin's conſtant neceſſary uſeful Gueſt, witheld her Queſtions a while. At length, impatiency prevail'd, and ſhe deſir'd <hi>Beatrice</hi> to let her know, when the Princeſs <hi>Olimpia</hi> would be alone in her Cloſet. The ſame day, word was brought her ſhe was ſo, and wiſh'd to ſee her. <hi>Melora</hi> attends her the very inſtant; and found that ſubtle Lady ſitting upon a Couch, leaning her head upon her hand, with an unuſual ſadneſs in her Face. Aſſoon as <hi>Melora</hi> enter'd, ſhe bid her ſit down; then, fetching a deep Sigh, continu'd ſilent. The poor young Creature ſurpriz'd with this counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited ſorrow, remain'd alſo dumb, for ſome time, till her Tears made way for her words. She implor'd <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limpia</hi> to acquaint her, if through any inadvertency, ſhe had offended to that degree, as to loſe the honour of
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:151648:56"/>
her Friendſhip, and be baniſh'd that dear Boſom, where all her Happineſs and Delight were Center'd; Adding, with a World of ſweetneſs and real trouble, how willingly ſhe would abate, participate; or, if poſſible, take off thoſe griefs, ſhe ſaw o'er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm her beloved Princeſs, might ſhe but know the cauſe. <hi>Olimpia</hi> lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up her head, anſwer'd very ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly; my Affliction will perhaps oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion your rejoycing; I mourn the Prince <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> whom as a Friend I lov'd. Your inclination caus'd him to be your averſion; and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his Miſeries will move no Pity; which made me forbear relating them.</p>
               <p>Alas, Madam! (replies <hi>Melora</hi>) wherein has your Highneſs diſcover'd that averſion, you are pleas'd to charge me with? I have receiv'd the Prince's Addreſs, with all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placency imaginable, at any time, or any hour. If this is hatred, I am miſtaken; and muſt beg directions,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:151648:56"/>
how to expreſs my Eſteem to my Lord <hi>Alphonſus;</hi> both as to his own merit, and what's yet more, a Perſon recommended by you, (en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſhe, bowing.)</p>
               <p>With ſuch a height of Paſſion, ſuch an exceſs of tenderneſs (returns <hi>Olimpia</hi>) the Prince adores you, that your fatal Coldneſs hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd him. Signore <hi>Franciſco</hi> acquaints me, that, ever ſince his laſt parting from you, he hath Languiſh'd of a Fever; which his Phyſicians ſay, is deſperate; whilſt he, Foe to himſelf, and Friend to his Diſeaſe, gives way to that, and ſlights all their Applications.</p>
               <p>Let me dye (cry'd out <hi>Melora</hi> eagerly; frighted with the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſuch a Perſon's Death) rather than have a guilt like this, imputed to me; Ah Madam! (went ſhe on) if you have any ſparks of that generous love remaining, which you beſtow'd on this Ungrateful; teach me a way to expiate my Crime. I own what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e'er
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:151648:57"/>
my inclination was, I err'd, to an extremity, in diſobeying your Commands; and to attone, I'll Viſit him, I'll write, do what my nature hath moſt abhorr'd; ſo my Princeſs will again receive me into favour.</p>
               <p>Do nothing againſt ſtomach (An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers <hi>Olimpia</hi> coldly) and though I know a line or two might ſave his Life, yet a diſſembl'd kindneſs is but a Reprieve; and to relapſe into de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, is irrecoverable, therefore I'll not ask it; 'tis to deſire a preſent Cordial, that carries with it, a future Poiſon. When ſhe had ſaid this, ſhe left <hi>Melora</hi> in the Cloſet, and went to Company, that ſtay'd to kiſs her hand.</p>
               <p>Nothing was more glorious, than the Friendſhip of Donna <hi>Olimpia;</hi> who enjoy'd it, participated of all the pleaſures and grandeur of <hi>Rome.</hi> Then, to be a Princeſs! Attractions, which may excuſe <hi>Melora,</hi> if ſhe committed an indecency in writing
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:151648:57"/>
to the pretended Duke. For after many ſtruglings with her native reſervedneſs, ſhe reſolv'd it, and wrote thus.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>To the Duke <hi>Alphonſus.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>MY belov'd and ever honour'd Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs tells me your Highneſs is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunately ſeiz'd with Sickneſs; and unkindly makes me the occaſion of it. If I have that power over you, which my want of Charms perſwades me I am only flatter'd with; I charge you, uſe your beſt endeavours to recover Health, and haſten to us that I, through your medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation may be re-eſtabliſh'd in the heart of my dear Princeſs. Which Obligement can never ſufficiently be acknowledg'd, or return'd by</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Your Servant</hi> Melora.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>Olimpia</hi> in haſte diſpatch'd her Viſitants, thoſe of Ceremony, and
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:151648:58"/>
thoſe of Buſineſs. Coming back to the Cloſet, ſhe found <hi>Melora</hi> reading; having left the Letter open upon the Table. <hi>Melora</hi> ſtood up as <hi>Olimpia</hi> came in, and begg'd ſhe would pleaſe to peruſe that ſhe had written; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſhe was wholly ignorant of thoſe ſort of Letters, and humbly pray'd her approbation. When <hi>Olimpia</hi> had read it; ſhe, ſmiling, ſaid; you have plaid the pretty Sophiſter, my dear, and ſo kindly expreſs'd your obliging ſentiments of Friendſhip, that I know how to reſent your Cruelty, in diſcovering ſo little Love to a Prince, who perhaps may want Life to receive it. <hi>Beatrice</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes the conveyance, and with needful caution hath it deliver'd to the Cardinal; who began already to think of ſpeedily leaving his Chamber, and this favour added to his health, and his deſires. He, all night, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trives the kindeſt Anſwer, words could frame, and the next Morning ſends it to <hi>Olimpia;</hi> who, with her
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:151648:58"/>
uſual cunning, preſented it; firſt bewailing his weakneſs, then won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering at Love's Power, which had given ſtrength to anſwer her Letter ſo quickly. <hi>Melora,</hi> bluſhing, took it; and to <hi>Olimpia</hi> read as follows.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Alphonſus</hi> to the Divine <hi>Melora.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>WEre I dying, I'd force my trembling hand to write <hi>Melora</hi> thanks, but I am better, returning from the grave. The charming Mandate, which brought me your Commands to live, brought likewiſe power to obey them. Yes my Adorable Miſtreſs, I own you have ſav'd my Life; and 'tis a mighty act of mercy. Yet Pardon me, fair Saint, if I preſume to ſay, there's Juſtice in it too; for 'tis but just my Angel ſhould preſerve that Life, which is wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to her ſervice.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>How think you, Madam, cries <hi>Olimpia</hi> haſtily; does he not write, as well as he ſpeaks; I own him
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:151648:59"/>
Excellent at both, Anſwers <hi>Melora;</hi> therefore ſhould not I be guilty of Vanity, to imagine my ſelf bleſt with perfections great enough, to Merit his endleſs Love?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Olimpia</hi> reply'd, in Compliments of her worth, and careſs'd her with new Indearments. A few days after the Cardinal's Phyſicians advis'd him to the Country Air, for the perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his recovery; and he let his Friends know, that being weak, he deſir'd privacy without Viſiters, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning to ſpend this time at <hi>Olimpia</hi>'s <hi>Villa,</hi> (attended only with <hi>Franciſco</hi>) inſtead of his own; though the World was made believe he lay there retir'd.</p>
               <p>Aſſoon as <hi>Olimpia</hi> underſtood the matter, according to the Cardinal's wiſhes, ſhe asks <hi>Melora</hi> to leave <hi>Rome</hi> a ſecond time with her; telling her alſo, that the Duke of <hi>Modena</hi> was advis'd to the Air for his Health; and ſhe had given him an invitation to her <hi>Villa;</hi> where he might remain
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:151648:59"/>
undiſcover'd. I let you know this, ſaid <hi>Olimpia;</hi> that you may not ſeem ſupriz'd or diſpleas'd at his coming to us. <hi>Melora</hi> receiv'd the News of his Company very agreeably; and they with much pleaſure began their Journey. Soon after the Cardinal ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives, and 'twas then, and not till then, that Pity, Loves ſure Forerun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ſeiz'd the Compaſſionate Heart of that young ſoft Maid; when ſhe beheld <hi>Antonio</hi> look as pale as Death, and tremble, as he mov'd, with weakneſs. This, ſhe thought, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Love had been the only cauſe of, and that the World would Tax her of Barbarity, ſhould ſhe refuſe to apply Cordials of Kindneſs, to ſuch a conſuming Languiſhment. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe receives him with ſmiles; and ſays obliging things, that beyond meaſure charm'd the Prieſt. They Supp'd together in <hi>Olimpia</hi>'s Cloſet; and being all pleas'd, their Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation was extraordinary. <hi>Barbarino</hi> had formerly been imploy'd in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:151648:60"/>
Negotiations, to the Courts of Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Princes; he had good natural parts, and all the Acquirements of Learning, that great Men are able to receive. No wonder then his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany was agreeable to <hi>Melora;</hi> who was ingenious, and therefore under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the wit he deliver'd in pleaſant relations and diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>While they were at Supper, <hi>Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice</hi> brought <hi>Olimpia</hi> word, that there was a Benedictine of the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Monaſtery, waited to deſire the honour of her Highneſſes Preſence at the Feaſt of their Patron; which was to be Celebrated on the Morrow. I ſhall incur your diſpleaſure, ſaid <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limpia</hi> ſmiling, my Lord Duke, if I take <hi>Melora</hi> with me; yet I would willingly have her ſee the Solemnity, becauſe I believe it will be very fine. I ſhall mourn your Abſence, replies the Cardinal, but ſhould grieve more to hinder the fair <hi>Melora</hi> participating the pleaſure of beholding the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony. We will endeavour to make
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:151648:60"/>
my Lord amends, at our return, with a full relation of our Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſaid <hi>Melora.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Deſcription from ſo ſweet an Oratrix will charm me far beyond the gaudy ſhow, anſwers the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal. Thus they talk'd away the Evening; and the next Morning, the Ladies roſe early, to prepare for the Feſtival. When they were dreſt, <hi>Barbarino</hi> was admitted to pay them a Viſit in <hi>Olimpia</hi>'s Chamber. <hi>Melora</hi> lookt ſurprizingly beautiful, and the Cardinal expreſs'd his admiration, in laviſh Commendations; ſeeming to come nearer to view her: he, in a moment, fix'd a Crociate of valuable Jewels upon her Breaſt. She went immediately to take them of; but <hi>Olimpia</hi> coming up forbade her; and ſhe, bluſhing, let them remain.</p>
               <p>That Night ſeveral Perſons of Quality conducted the Princeſs <hi>Olim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia,</hi> from the Monaſtery home. The Ladies were oblig'd to ſtay and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain them, ſo that they could not
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:151648:61"/>
ſee the Cardinal. The next day <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limpia</hi> reſolv'd to have to her ſelf; and gave her Servants order to ſay ſhe was indiſpos'd, and would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive no Viſits. They choſe a retir'd Grotto to ſpend the day in. This cool retreat was very delightful; for 'twas with wonderous pains cut in a Rock, the Lights were all cover'd with Vines; which look'd very a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable. One ſide of the Grotto was hang'd with Foreſt Tapeſtry, the other moſt artificially adorn'd with Moſs-work, which glitter'd with ſhining Shells and Pebbles; whoſe Luſtre equal Diamonds. The Couch and Canopy was green Florence Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenet; at the end, oppoſite to the Door, a full Curtain of the ſame hung down to the ground: along the ſide of the Rock that was covered with Moſs, a ſmall Rivulet ran, whoſe pleaſing Murmur was able to inſpire the moſt ſtupid, with tender Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Whilſt <hi>Olimpia</hi> ſaid ſomething to the Cardinal, <hi>Melora</hi> fixt her Eyes
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:151648:61"/>
upon the purling Stream; whoſe tranſparent clearneſs ſhow'd the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, ſtow'd with the Rock's Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Shells, and Pebbles. The Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal turning, obſerving her ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, ſtoop'd nearer; and with an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graving Pen, upon the Marble Pave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wrote thus:
<q>
                     <l>Should ſome ſmall Water Deity to day</l>
                     <l>Be ſporting here, and thoſe bright Eyes ſurvey,</l>
                     <l>With eager haſte he'd fly to <hi>Neptune</hi>'s Court,</l>
                     <l>And tell the God the Place of your Reſort.</l>
                     <l>Then, turn away thoſe All-Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Eyes,</l>
                     <l>Leſt this ſmall Rill, ſhould to an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean riſe;</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Neptune</hi> vanquiſh'd by thy kill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Charms,</l>
                     <l>Should bear thee hence within his Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Arms.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>See, Madam! ſaid <hi>Olimpia,</hi> when
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:151648:62"/>
ſhe had read 'em: the Prince's Paſſion penetrates the obdurate Marble; yet your harder heart ſtill denies acceſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Melora</hi> was amaz'd to behold the lines at her Feet; thinking they had ſtill been diſcourſing. She had, with bluſhes, juſt perus'd what was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, when from behind the Curtain, they heard the agreeable charming found, both of Vocal, and Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Muſick. Ha! cry'd <hi>Olimpia,</hi> ſeemingly ſurpriz'd, you mention'd the Watry Deity, and I believe he has ſent his Mermaids, to entertain you. I rather ſuſpect an Earthly Goddeſs, reply'd <hi>Melora,</hi> ſmilingly, looking upon <hi>Olimpia;</hi> and the beſt way to expreſs our thanks for the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, is ſilence. Whilſt the Italian ſongs, with the moſt exquiſite Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, was perform'd, they din'd; and after <hi>that,</hi> the Princeſs <hi>Olimpia</hi> gave her Commands the Muſick ſhould retire. The Curtain was drawn up, and the delicate Organs diſcover'd; which, from the Water
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:151648:62"/>
receiv'd their incomparable Muſick; and all the glorious painted ſeats, which held the tuneful Maſters, whom they had heard before.</p>
               <p>In vain, cry'd <hi>Melora,</hi> in a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing tranſport, we hunt the World for pleaſures, when ranſackt <hi>Italy,</hi> can never equal, what my charming Princeſs's <hi>Villa</hi> gives. Ay but, my Life, return'd the Cardinal, I expect the diſcharge of your Promiſe, in deſcribing the Entertainment you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd Yeſterday.</p>
               <p>Indeed, went the fair one on, ſmiling, I think theſe Saints Feſtivals are fuller of diverſion, than devotion. To ſee a fat Abbot walk in ſtate, cover'd with Embroideries, and looking as great, as if the Triple Crown adorn'd his Head; and all their Ornaments ſet forth in the greateſt Pomp and Luſtre imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; doth it not reſemble Pride, and Vanity? Be cautious, my dear, interrupted <hi>Olimpia,</hi> leſt you incline to the errour of the Hereticks; who
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:151648:63"/>
care not how fine their Houſes are, nor how plain their Churches; tacitely diſcovering they love, and eſteem themſelves, better then the Deity, they Worſhip.</p>
               <p>I ſubmit, ſaid <hi>Melora,</hi> and will admire their glories. But to what end ſhould I deſcribe vaſt Banquets of Sweet-meats, and delightful Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick; which is here every day excell'd. That only which deſerves perpetual remembrance, was the Lovely Duke and Dutcheſs of <hi>Parma.</hi> Such a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming tenderneſs he expreſs'd, ſuch a ſympathy of Souls there ſeem'd, as if one cou'd not do, what the other did not like. How can you praiſe, what you refuſe to practice, cry'd the Cardinal in a Rapture; ſo would I gaze all day on thoſe lov'd eyes; but then the Night; the Night; burning, raging, ſighing, claſping! Oh forbear my Lord! (<hi>Olimpia</hi> ſtops him;) leave theſe ſtrong extaſies; till that happy Night arrives: ſee how <hi>Melora</hi> bluſhes. Indeed ſaid the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:151648:63"/>
Cardinal, cooling himſelf with a ſigh, I ought to have patience, ſince that Duke, you mention'd, waited long for one, leſs fair, and through many hazards, at length was bleſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Olimpia</hi> knew, <hi>Melora</hi> took delight in nothing more, then hearing the Hiſtories of Perſons, where the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricio's of Fortune had been moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident: and to oblige her, ask'd the Cardinal, if his Highneſs was acquainted with the particulars of their loves? He anſwer'd her that he could procure them a full relation, if they deſir'd it; for <hi>Franciſco</hi> was bred, from a Child, in the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi>'s Court; &amp; inform'd of each minute cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance. <hi>Melora</hi> expreſs'd great joy at the propoſal; and <hi>Franciſco</hi> being call'd, the Cardinal commanded him to ſit down, and to the Ladies relate the Adventures of <hi>Emilius,</hi> and <hi>Loviſa,</hi> Duke and Dutcheſs of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma. Franciſco,</hi> after a moment's recollection, with a ſubmiſſive reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, began thus.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="history">
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:151648:64"/>
               <head>THE HISTORY OF <hi>Emilius</hi> and <hi>Loviſa.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Shall not attempt (moſt Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Auditors) to deſcribe the Perſons of this Prince and Princeſs, becauſe my words cannot reach the height of their Perfections; as your own Eyes may be witneſs; but muſt of neceſſity go ſo far back, as to take a view of the late Duke and Dutcheſs, Parents to this. <hi>He</hi> was a great Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, and a great Politician, which of conſequence render'd him a great Man; yet of a humour ſo poſitive and abſolute, that neither Sons nor Subjects durſt ever contradict his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution. Whilſt the Dutcheſs was all
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:151648:64"/>
ſweetneſs and affability, as oft as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible mitigating the ſternneſs of her Lord, and obliging all the World with Offices of Kindneſs.</p>
               <p>He had two Sons, one elder than the preſent Duke <hi>Emilius,</hi> over whom he exercis'd an Authority, wherein very little of the Father appear'd; whomſoever they favour'd he frown'd upon, always denying them whatever they coveted with eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Few therefore durſt make their Court aſſiduouſly to the young Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, leſt they incur'd the anger and jealouſie of the Old Duke. Only Count <hi>Bileront</hi> broke all theſe Rules of Policy, and openly profeſt an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Service, and humble unfeign'd Friendſhip for the Prince <hi>Emilius,</hi> with whom he had been nurtur'd. The Duke often ſtorm'd at that, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten chid the Lovely Youths for their ſo ſtrict amity; and often Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Bileront</hi>'s Father to ſend him farther from Court. Yet all theſe ſhocks they ſtood; for <hi>Emilius,</hi> who
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:151648:65"/>
had a large ſhare of his Mother's ſweet nature, drooped ſo when they went to part them, that before he reach'd at Manhood, they cou'd not do it, without viſible danger to the Prince's Health. By that time <hi>Emili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> had paſt his Eighteenth Year, he grew quite tyr'd of the Court; the harſhneſs of his Father's temper abridging him of all thoſe Injoyments, whereunto his Inclinations led him. He ſets all Engines at work to obtain leave, that he may join the <hi>Venetians,</hi> as a Noble Voluntier, and ſee a Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paign; hoping to raiſe his Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the World, and quit, for ſome time, a place that diſguſted him. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter much oppoſition, <hi>Emilius</hi> accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh'd his deſires; but the Old Duke not finding in his heart to prove too indulgent, orders <hi>Bileront</hi> to ſtay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind; and perceiving notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that faithful Youth, covertly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd to follow him, he without hearkening to the intreaties of his Friends, Impriſon'd him under a
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:151648:65"/>
ſtrict Guard. If <hi>Emilius</hi> reſented this ill, he was very likely to meet with the ſame treatment. So that being aſſur'd no other harm was deſign'd him but to hinder his Accompanying him; he ſmother'd his ſmarting griefs, and went on with his inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Several young Sparks, in whom the love of glory had kindled a Warlike Fire, forſook the ſoft pleaſures of the Palace, and waited on the Prince. This Noble Cavalcade having left <hi>Parma,</hi> directed their courſe towards his Holineſs's Galleys, where they deſign'd to imbark, after ſtaying ſome time at the Port, till the Fleet were ready to ſail. As the Prince, having all his things Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bark'd, was walking on the ſhore, he felt ſomebody take him by the Cloak, and turning, he ſaw one in the garb of a Common Souldier; but looking more heedfully, Oh how pleas'd was he to behold his lov'd <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leront;</hi> ſuch Joy fill'd their delighted Souls, there was no room for words.
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:151648:66"/>
At length, a hundred Queſtions throng together, which as confuſedly are anſwered. <hi>Bileront,</hi> whoſe ſweet Eloquence cou'd move things almoſt inanimate (for next to that I account the ſtupid ſort of Men) had with his Promiſes and Preſents prevail'd upon a Centry to let him have his Cloaths, in which he dreſt himſelf, the Fellow putting on the young Lords, and over them his own Cloak, and thus they both eſcap'd. Now <hi>Emilius</hi>'s wiſhes were compleat; and the faithful happy Friends went in all haſte aboard. I will not trouble your Honours with a deſcription of the War, only ſay of theſe, they were a ſecond <hi>Pylades</hi> and <hi>Oreſtes;</hi> always fighting by each other, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways undertaking the greateſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; and always Crown'd with Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. The Campaign ended, they with ſeveral of the French Nobility, Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntiers likewiſe, went to <hi>France;</hi> and in that Court ſpent their Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. In the mean time, the Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſs
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:151648:66"/>
of <hi>Parma</hi> long'd to ſee her Darling Son; and having at length, obtain'd <hi>Bileront's</hi> Pardon, ſhe writes earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to her dear <hi>Emilius,</hi> that he would return. He obeys his indulgent Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's reiterated deſires, and again, with his Favorite <hi>Bileront,</hi> graces the Court of <hi>Parma.</hi> His Travails had extreamly added to his natural per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and though he was not Heir Apparent, yet his eminent accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhments drew all admiring Eyes towards him. Nothing now was to be ſeen in the Palace, on the Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe's ſide, but Balls, Maſquerades, and ſuch other demonſtrations of Royal Pleaſures. At one of the Balls, a young Lady, having danc'd in a Perſian Habit, with a particular mien and charming ſmoothneſs; <hi>Emilius</hi> ask'd who ſhe was, ſaying, he had not obſerv'd her amongſt the Beauteous Train before, though he thought ſhe excell'd them all. He was ſtraight inform'd her name was <hi>Loviſa,</hi> Daughter to <hi>Don Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rique,</hi>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:151648:67"/>
and <hi>Donna Elvira,</hi> who were, as he knew, both great Courtiers and had, Dying, left this their only Child, to the care of the Dutcheſs; that her Fortune was very opulent, and her Perſon very taking. For his not ſeeing her, the reaſon was, ſhe had been ſome days in the Country, and return'd but the night before. This, adds the Prince's Informer, is an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the fair <hi>Loviſa,</hi> who is call'd the Dutcheſſe's Ward; and ador'd by all. <hi>Emilius,</hi> getting near her, told her in a whiſper that ſhe was unjuſt, her Beauty being enough to fix all Eyes upon her, ſhe ought not to excel ſo tranſcendantly in Dancing too; but let ſome more indifferent do <hi>that,</hi> and obtain a glance. <hi>Loviſa,</hi> bluſhing at the Prince's praiſes, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd him; we muſt expect your Highneſs full of the French Gallantry, and whatever Object you are pleas'd to rally is oblig'd to bear it. That place was too publick, for a longer Conference, but the Prince was
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:151648:67"/>
wonderfully pleas'd with her, and talk'd of nothing elſe all the night, to his dear <hi>Billeront.</hi> Soon after, he paid <hi>Loviſa</hi> a viſit; and finding her Converſation as full of charms, as her lovely Face, he was never ſo well pleas'd, as when with her. His Mother the Dutcheſs, ſaw this growing Friendſhip, but hating no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than venturing <hi>Emilius</hi> in another Campaign; and conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Loviſa</hi> was a great Heireſs, whoſe Anceſtors ſprung from a Branch of the Royal Family, he alſo being the ſecond Son; ſhould he fall in love with her, the match would not be ſo diſproportionable. Theſe reaſons made the Dutcheſs not only connive at his often Viſits; but alſo conceal them from the Duke. <hi>Loviſa</hi>'s A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment lying through the Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe's, the Duke thought he had been with his Mother, whilſt he and <hi>Bileront</hi> ſpent their time more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly.</p>
               <p>They had form'd a Party for their
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:151648:68"/>
particular Converſation, which they call'd the Friendly Society, and made ſeveral pretty Laws amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, with ſuitable Penalties, if they infring'd them. One was, to communicate to all the Campany, every Letter they receiv'd, be it Love, or Gallantry. Nay if it was buſineſs, ſome Perſon was to inſpect it curſorily over, and witneſs to the reſt, that it afforded no diverſon. Happy was he, that could partake the ſatisfaction of this ingenious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; which was compos'd of the higheſt young Quality. Their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe was made up of pithy relations; or viewing the neweſt works of the writing Wits; Cenſuring, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolling thoſe labours of the brain, according to their Merit. <hi>Emilius,</hi> coming one day, before the uſual hour for their meeting, ſurpriz'd <hi>Loviſa</hi> alone, reading a Letter, which ſhe bluſh'd at, and haſtily put up, when the Prince came in. Ha, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam! cry'd he, eagerly running to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:151648:68"/>
her, have I caught you break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of our greateſt Laws? She bluſhing ſtill anſwer'd, 'twas buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. This augmented the Prince's curioſity; and he ſaid very gravely, you know, Madam, our Statutes are, that if Letters are full only of buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, one is juſt to overlook that, and report it to the whole Body of our Society. Now I being here firſt, claim the privilege of ſeeing it, and ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the reſt. She inſiſted, 'twas in her power, to chuſe the Perſon, ſhe deſir'd ſhould ſee it; but finding the Prince really earneſt, unwilling to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe him, ſhe gave it him, which he read thus; (for ſaid <hi>Franciſco,</hi> I having the happineſs to know each particular of this Intrigue, took Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies of all the Letters to help my Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory.)</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="126" facs="tcp:151648:69"/>
                     <head>Don <hi>Alvarez,</hi> to Donna <hi>Loviſa.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Madam, My Dear Niece,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Hope you will eſteem the propoſal I here ſend you, as a teſtimony of my Kindneſs; and believe, that my conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual ſtudy is for your Advantage, and Honour. The young Count <hi>Lodowick</hi> is now preparing to kiſs the Duke's hand, and make a handſome appearance at Court, his Eſtate is large; and the World juſtly calls him a Gallant Man. He is already in love with the report Fame brings us of you. I don't Queſtion but your Sight ſecures your Conqueſt; pray let me hear your Opinion of him. I am, <hi>My Dear Kinſwoman,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Yours</hi> Alvarez.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The Prince ſigh'd, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> as he read this Letter; and giving <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:151648:69"/>
                  <hi>Loviſa</hi> again, ſaid, I don't like this Marrying, 'twill ſpoil our Society. I'll give my Vote, that it ſhall be High Treaſon, for any of our Ladies to Marry. Nay then, returns <hi>Loviſa,</hi> laughing, we ſhall have a very pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Character Twenty Years hence, a Company of Old Ill-natur'd Maids; better forſake the World quite, and become holy Nuns. Well, anſwers the Prince, I find all my Joys are at an end. You muſt be in Love now, and we bear all thoſe abſences of Mind, ſo frequent in Lovers, Silent whole hours; or if you talk, Count <hi>Lodowick</hi> muſt be brought in, by head and ſhoulders, at every Paragraph. You were the glory of our little Select World: your Wit and Eloquence gave Life to all was ſaid; now you forſake us, I'll forſake the reſt, and leaving an inſipid Court, i'th' Camp forget <hi>Loviſa;</hi> if that be poſſible; (ended he with a ſigh.) My Lord, replies <hi>Loviſa,</hi> I have indeavour'd to be rude, and interrupt your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:151648:70"/>
you talk, as if I was to be Marry'd to Morrow. The World (went ſhe on, with a Majeſtick Air) knows little of <hi>Loviſa</hi>'s Heart, if they imagine it ſo eaſily gain'd; and that but hearing of a Man, is likely to fall in love with me, I ſhould begin firſt to be ſo with him. More of the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Friends coming in, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation became general; yet ſtill <hi>Emilius</hi> was harping on this (to him) ungrateful ſtring, Count <hi>Lodowick</hi>'s coming. He ask'd <hi>Loviſa,</hi> whether ſhe thought ſhe ſhould fancy him, and what ſort of Man ſhe could like, begging her to expreſs what Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations ſhe expected in the happy Slave, whom, amongſt her numerous Adorers, ſhe wou'd bleſs with her Smiles.</p>
               <p>My Lord, ſaid that charming Maid, were I to behold a Man Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culine, yet Beautiful, Great, yet truly Brave; A Prince whoſe Virtues, brighter than his Diadems, appear; one more glorious than boundleſs
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:151648:70"/>
Fancy can to the thinking Mind de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paint; and, not convinc'd by ſignal proofs, his heart inclin'd, his paſſion forc't him to my feet: I might gaze on ſuch a Maſter-piece; but my Eyes ſhould let him no farther in: He ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhou'd diſturb my Mind. You may, reply'd the Prince, love where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoe'er you look; nor need to fear they'll not ſigh for you; at leaſt, if I may judge the Soul of others by my own. <hi>Loviſa</hi> took this for raillery, and pleaſantly return'd, ſuch Hearts as yours will be moſt glorious Trophies, and I ſhall grow exceeding proud, but that, to humble me, I know Prince <hi>Emilius</hi>'s way, and my own Imperfections.</p>
               <p>That night <hi>Bileront,</hi> whoſe Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments joined the Prince's, heard him, after all was gone to reſt, walking about his room. Fearing he was not well, he roſe and went to him. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, ſaid <hi>Bileront,</hi> if I intrude, and fly uncall'd, to learn what diſturbs my Lord. Oh my Friend! (Anſwers
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:151648:71"/>
the Prince) I'm ſick at heart, the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper revels there; and gives me pains that I ne'er felt before. <hi>Bileront,</hi> who was really frighted, began to call the Servants for the Phyſicians; when <hi>Emilius</hi> haſtily ſtops him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it lay not in the power of Art. None, none could heal his wounds, but the fair Cauſer. Then bluſhing, and hiding his Head in the Boſom of his dear Friend, he told him he lov'd the glory of her Sex, the ſweet <hi>Loviſa.</hi> I miſtruſted long ago (went on the Amorous Prince) but durſt not exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine my heart on that point, till Ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday diſcovering another like to poſſeſs her: love and deſpair at once ſeiz'd me; broke the ſoft Chains of ſleep, and ſet me here upon the Rack. <hi>Bileront</hi> ſaid all, exceſſive Friendſhip prompted, to calm the diſtemper'd Mind of his lov'd Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; but he, witty to torment him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, ſtudy'd impoſſibilities that might ariſe, to bar his wiſhes, out of meer Chimera's: though indeed obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:151648:71"/>
there were enough. Thus ſpent the reſtleſs Prince the tedious Night. Next day, he long'd till the fatigue of Ceremonious Duty, buſineſs, all was o'er; that he might find his darling Miſtreſs, where all his thoughts were fix'd. He ſaw her; thought her more charming than ever ſince to himſelf he had own'd he lov'd her. Then he gave no bounds to his admiring Eyes; but helping forward his diſeaſe ſet every thought at work; what Happineſs, what Raptures ſhe could give. When he came near her, tremblings and ſighs turn'd him pale; then a riſing heart cover'd his face with bluſhes. He try'd to tell his love in whiſpers, but his courage fail'd him, for he, who truly loves, beholds his Miſtreſs ſtamp'd with ſuch divinity as awes his preſumption. Nor dares he truſt his tongue, leſt that too boldly ſhou'd offend; leaves to his Eyes the ſad ſilent Tale; and hopes the Charmer will read it there. <hi>Loviſa,</hi>
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:151648:72"/>
who thought the minds of others like her own, free and gay, was brisk as Air; and often chid the Prince for his unuſual Melancholy; nor could ſhe forbear asking <hi>Bileront</hi> if he knew the cauſe. He anſwer'd her ambgiuouſly; ſuppoſe ſhe her ſelf was, wou'd ſhe promiſe a remedy? That's ſo unlikely, ſaid ſhe 'tis not worth my anſwering; for I never was chearfuller in my Life; and I hope my mirth is not ſo ridiculous, as to work juſt the contrary on the Prince. <hi>Bileront</hi> fear'd to ſay more; leſt he ſhou'd incurr the danger of diſpleaſing both.</p>
               <p>A few days after, this expected Count <hi>Lodowick</hi> came, was very well receiv'd by the Duke, the Eldeſt Prince, and indeed all the Court, except <hi>Emilius;</hi> who notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his natural ſweetneſs, could not forbear looking cold on this young Nobleman; whilſt <hi>Lodowick's</hi> only care was to dreſs well, and make a Figure anſwerable to his Quality.
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:151648:72"/>
Finding <hi>Loviſa</hi> the handſomeſt La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; he was moſt particular to her though he had a general complacency for all the young and fair. Mean time <hi>Emilius</hi>'s melancholy ſo viſibly increas'd that every body took notice of it. He complain'd to his faithful <hi>Bileront,</hi> that he thought <hi>Loviſa</hi> took more care in dreſſing, ſince the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival of <hi>Lodowick;</hi> and he fancy'd ſhe gave him favourable glances; then would he burſt into a Paſſion, and ask that fond Friend, wherein <hi>Lodowick</hi> deſerv'd more than he? Thus, this impatient Prince nurſt up groundleſs terrours, till they rob'd his days of Joy, his Nights of reſt. When <hi>Bileront</hi> could get leave to ſpeak, he told the Prince, that for his part, he diſcover'd no ſuch al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration in the dreſs, or looks of <hi>Loviſa;</hi> then you talk (went he on) of her preferring <hi>Lodowick</hi> before you: when alaſs, ſhe is wholly ignorant, knows not the vaſt honour her Eyes have won; think you, my Lord,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:151648:73"/>
being poſſeſt of your Illuſtrious Heart would not ſatisfy her Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and were ſhe aſſur'd of it, I dare believe <hi>Loviſa</hi> wou'd preferr you in her eſteem, not only to <hi>Lodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> but even to all the World. Yet ſtill either a favourable opportunity was wanting, or his fears how <hi>Lovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa</hi> might receive a Declaration of Love prevented him; and poor <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milius</hi> languiſh'd on.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bileront</hi> met, one day, <hi>Loviſa,</hi> in a private Garden, belonging to the Palace, in queſt of a Favourite Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Friend; who, ſhe was told, was gone to walk there. Meeting <hi>Bileront,</hi> ſhe ask'd him if he had ſeen her; <hi>Bileront</hi> had juſt left the Prince <hi>Emilius</hi> alone, in a Grotto; and ſtraight reſolv'd, without much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, to ſend his Miſtreſs to him. Accordingly he directed this fair Lady thither; tells her very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently, her Friend was there. The Prince ſtarted as ſhe enter'd the Grot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and <hi>Loviſa</hi> leapt back, with the
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:151648:73"/>
ſurprize; both bluſh'd at this unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Rencounter; till <hi>Loviſa,</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it only for a trick of that young Lord; recollected her ſelf, and ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling told <hi>Emilius;</hi> ſhe wou'd be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veng'd on <hi>Bileront;</hi> nay, ſaid ſhe, pleaſantly, your Highneſs ought to join with me, ſince he occaſion'd this interruption of your thoughts. Madam (return'd he bowing) you you might much more properly call it, an Elevation of thoughts, for I aſſure they were full of you, in Courts, in Camps, in Cells, in Grotto's. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd that fair one, in a pretty He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick tone: <hi>Emilius</hi> is ſtill the ſame; all Compliment; all Rhetorick. Yet not ſo to all, replies the Prince, looking paſſionately upon her, 'tis only <hi>Loviſa</hi> merits more, much more, then I can ſay were my tongue immortal and Tun'd to nought but praiſe. Ah! ſit <hi>Loviſa,</hi> and hear the State of poor <hi>Emilius</hi>'s Heart leſt you find too late how fatally I was in earneſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:151648:74"/>
                  <hi>Loviſa</hi> ſtill ſmiling, ſaid; <q>Ha! it ſeems the Plot lyes deeper than I imagin'd. I am to believe your Highneſs is in love, am I not, to help the Jeſt?</q> The Prince vex'd to ſee the real Language of his heart turn'd into raillery: threw himſelf at her feet; and ſpoke with a moving Air, thus. <q>If to have you the perpetual Image of my waking thoughts; or when I ſleep the charming Viſion of my Dreams: if it be greater pleaſure to hide me from the inquiring World, that I may ſhut out all but you, to fancy joys in you beyond the Crowns the united Univerſe cou'd give: to draw it Hell without you: to ſigh, and wiſh, and tremble, when I hear you named; if this be love, I'm ſure I am in love.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Loviſa</hi> riſing, and viewing the kneeling Prince, with a becoming Majeſty, ſaid, <q>Remember, Sir, as you are born a Prince, ſo I deſcend from the ſame Line; my Soul as
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:151648:74"/>
great as yours; therefore, if you vainly think, depending on your Birth, the conqueſt eaſie; and I with open Arms muſt receive your offer'd love: I ſay you are much deceiv'd; for whilſt there are Monaſteries, or diſtant Kingdoms, to the Earth's Verge I'll fly, rather then meet with Arrogancy, inſtead of that reſpect, which humble Love Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates. Am I arrogant? (reply'd the paſſionate Prince) when proſtrate at your feet I Lye? Carry theſe dying Eyes a look of pride? Blaſted be the Honours of my Birth unleſs it helps me forward in my Love! And for yours to me, you are a Queen, a Goddeſs.</q> Riſe, my Lord, <hi>Loviſa</hi> interrupts him; I have heard enough. This is a ſtrange Theme; forget it Prince; indulge not ſuch deſires, deſtructive to your Peace, and never like to be fulfill'd. 'Were I, ſaid the Prince (as he lead her out of the Grove) <q>ſo wretched; convinc'd <hi>that</hi> deſtiny muſt attend me; Life
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:151648:75"/>
ſo, tormenting I wou'd not bear too, long.</q> They had walk'd but a few paces, when they met <hi>Bileront,</hi> and the Lady <hi>Loviſa</hi> wanted, whom <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leront</hi> had entertain'd, that ſhe might not diſturb <hi>Emilius.</hi> The Count ſoon read in both their Faces, the Minutes had not been ſpent in common talk. Many Weeks this Amorous Prince employ'd in trying to perſwade <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſa,</hi> that he lov'd her above all Earthly things; yet had obtain'd no more than a bare permiſſion to tell her this, whenever opportunity fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd.</p>
               <p>The Court was, all this while, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the Amour; they knew there was a Cabal of Wits, and thought <hi>Emilius</hi> only went often for the ſake of the Converſation. Love's an unexhauſted Spring; and ſtill hath ſomething more to ſay; nor cou'd the Prince be ſatisfy'd with ſhort Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, ſtollen at Windows, or got ſome moments, before other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany came. He long'd for whole
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:151648:75"/>
hours, and fancy'd, if he had time enough, he might move her heart to pity. To that end, he ſent <hi>Bileront</hi> (whom <hi>Loviſa</hi> had given him leave to make his Confident) with this Letter (ſaid <hi>Franciſco,</hi> pulling out the Copy:)
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <head>
                           <hi>Emilius</hi> to the fair <hi>Loviſa.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>IF you have not Cruelly reſolv'd my Death (thou dear unequall'd Charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er) grant me an hour when my longing Eyes may gaze without Controul; where I may throw me at the feet of my adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and ſay a thouſand thouſand tender things, that Love, like mine, inſpires. I do not ask a pitying word, or a kind look, in anſwer to my ſighs; I only beg a hearing, that ſure the niceſt Vertue will allow; ſince Virtue guides, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour dictates every Wiſh that fills the heart of your poor wounded Slave</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Emilius.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="140" facs="tcp:151648:76"/>
                  <hi>Loviſa</hi> was hard to be prevail'd on, for this private interview; but the faithful Count pleaded, with ſo much Zeal, for his Amorous Friend, that the fair one almoſt compell'd, yielded; and gave <hi>Emilius</hi> leave, after his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal good night, to return with <hi>Bile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ront</hi> a back way; into her Cloſet. <hi>Loviſa</hi> alſo brought the Partner of her heart, a dear lov'd Friend. When the Prince came, the Lady and <hi>Bile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ront</hi> retir'd to the farther end of the Cloſet. Cou'd any Man win a heart only with the ſilent Language of the Eyes, ſure 'twas <hi>Emilius;</hi> for, in his, <hi>Loviſa</hi> might plainly read Sparkling Joy, for the permiſſion ſhe had given him to ſee her; yet intermix'd with ſo much awe, and fear; that the charming confuſion ſhow'd, her love had taught him, to forget he e'er was born a Prince. And Ambition's Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons prompted him no farther, than to become her Slave. His words were ſoft as flakes of falling Snow, his perſon lovely; who then can
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:151648:76"/>
blame that charming Maid, if ſhe forgot her rigour, and heard, with pleaſure. He kneel'd, and ſnatch'd her beauteous hand, and printed theſe his Vows. <q>He ſaid, he lov'd her more, much more than Life. Oh! (went he on) were all the pleaſures of my paſt Years cramm'd into one happy hour, 'twould not reach the leaſt part of the Raptures, this bleſt Moment gives; this dear important <hi>Now.</hi> If then to have but one Minute, when I dare call you Mine, fills my Heart with ſuch Content; what would a Week, what would a Year, an Age? Oh I fear the Cordial wou'd prove too ſtrong; and I ſhou'd dye with Joy. Theſe Imaginary Viſions (returns <hi>Loviſa</hi> gravely) exceed Love's real Joys. Love, like a Courſe Picture ſet in an advantageous light, at di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance we admire, and gaze with wonder, but when nearer to our view, a hundred unthought of faults appear; and the imperfect
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:151648:77"/>
daubing's ſeen. Ah! No; there's nothing but perfection here, cry'd he tranſported, and graſping her hand) I long, (ſaid he, looking earneſtly on her) to break Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. I promis'd not to ask a look or word of pity, yet my Soul is on the Rack, to know how your heart is towards me. If conſtant love can ever gain admittance there; if you can ever feel a warmth; I do not hope that it will burn and rage like mine. I muſt not, dare not hear you (<hi>Loviſa</hi> ſtops him) yet I am well; but who knows not, 'tis dangerous, Prince, liſtening to words like theſe. Why (ſaid <hi>Emilius</hi> in a moving tone;) where lies the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger? Heaven grant they prove in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectious; and you Catch but the ſame pleaſing Fever poſſeſſes me. If I ſhou'd (returns <hi>Loviſa</hi> bluſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) if I ſhou'd (not that I do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline my Ear, to the ſoft ſtory of your Love) place you firſt in my eſteem, and ſuffer my Virgin
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:151648:77"/>
thoughts ſometimes to be employ'd on you; and after this, an offer'd Princeſs (ſtate intereſt) takes you from me: where ſhou'd I hide my bluſhing face? For then, not An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels Eloquence ſhou'd e'er perſwade me to behold falſe men again. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milius</hi> anſwer'd with Vehemence, By all my hopes, were there an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, who brought the conquer'd World her dower; and beautiful as painted Deity; me ſhe wou'd not move. You do not know <hi>Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> nor Puniſhments, nor Pleaſures prevail, when I am reſolv'd.</q> 
                  <hi>Loviſa</hi> wou'd hear no more, nor cou'd ſhe force him from her, till he obtain'd a Promiſe, in a little time, to receive the ſame favour, ſuch another Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and that procur'd another. In ſhort, the Prince, a thouſand ways, ſo tenderly expreſs'd his Love, that <hi>Loviſa</hi> was content he ſhou'd diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his Paſſion was not diſagreeable, that her Sentiments were kind; though Nicety deny'd her words to expreſs it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:151648:78"/>Mean time, Count <hi>Lodowick</hi> laid cloſe Siege; the Dutcheſs thought it a good Match; her Uncle preſs'd her hard on his behalf; but ſhe was deaf to all; nor had ſcarce Patience to obey the Dutcheſs, in letting him ſee her; Yet this diſturb'd <hi>Emilius;</hi> he hated, <hi>Lodowick</hi> ſhou'd view her, with ſuch greedy Eyes; or have the privilege to Viſit her alone. As he was one Night in <hi>Loviſa</hi>'s Cloſet, complaining of this, that fair one chid him, and ſaid, <q>She fear'd he was naturally Jealous; ſince he ſaw <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowick</hi> was her averſion, and that all ſhe did was by compulſion, yet ſtill he was diſpleas'd. 'Tis that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion, anſwer'd the Prince, with a ſigh, I fear; if you ſhould be forc'd to Marry him (Heaven avert that thought!) what would then become of wretched me? No, No, My Lord (return'd <hi>Loviſa</hi>) though I am not a Man, yet I am Miſtreſs of ſuch reſolutions, that I'll never Marry <hi>Lodowick.</hi>
                  </q> There is one way
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:151648:78"/>
(ſaid the Prince kneeling, and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pale, for fear of Angring her) one way ſecures my fears, and makes me bleſt above all humane kind. What's that, ſays <hi>Loviſa,</hi> ſurpris'd? I dare not tell you'll promiſe not (returns the Prince) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you'll promiſe not to be diſpleas'd, nor think that I preſum'd too far, and make too bold a Suit, incourag'd by the favours I to your pity owe. Since I know, ſaid <hi>Loviſa,</hi> (with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd look) Prince <hi>Emilius</hi> will not ask, but what's within the ſtricteſt Rules of Honour; I give you free li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to ſpeak. <hi>Emilius</hi> trembled as he ſpoke, and claſping her lov'd Knees, <q>Wou'd you, ſaid he, but let the Prieſt before theſe two (pointing to the aforemention'd Lady and <hi>Billeront,</hi> who were in the Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet) join our hands, knit that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Knot, which only Death un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; then all my fears wou'd be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd. Know you the raging tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Duke (ſaith <hi>Loviſa,</hi> rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him) and ask you this without
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:151648:79"/>
his conſent, or knowledge? No, let it ſuffice, I ne'er will be anothers; and let us wait till fate will ſmile, and Crown our Wiſhes without danger.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Then my fair Life will venture nothing on the ſcore of Love, when I'd forego a Crown for her (ſaid he paſſionately) Oh! ſatisfy my fears; give me but the Marriage Vow; I'll beg no more: At this awful di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſtill remain; nor offer at the Crown of all my Joys, your Bed, till the Fate, you ſpeak of, ſmiles; till there's not the leaſt ſhadow of a danger. <hi>Loviſa</hi> told him, ſhe durſt not reſolve on a thing of ſuch a Conſequence, leſt he, or ſhe, or both hereafter ſhould repent; but againſt the next meeting ſhe would conſider, and bad him reſt aſſur'd, all <hi>Lodowick</hi>'s Efforts were vain.</q> A few days after this there happen'd a ſad accident which alter'd the face of all things, in that Court; the Eldeſt Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> dyed ſuddenly, of an
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:151648:79"/>
Impoſthume. You may imagine the fright and confuſion the Court was in; and that decency confin'd <hi>Emili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> to his Cloſet; yet in the midſt of his Grief, he was not unmindful of his Love; but ſent <hi>Bileront,</hi> with a Letter, which contain'd theſe words.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Emilius</hi> to his Deareſt Life <hi>Loviſa.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THE Lamented untimely Fate of the departed Prince, my Brother, fills my Soul with Grief; and that I may not have a Glimpſe of Joy; I dare not yet ſee my faireſt Mistreſs. But, Oh! Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, <hi>Loviſa,</hi> no viciſſitude of Fortune has power to leſſen Love. My Death only ends the Paſſion vowed by</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Yours</hi> Emilius.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>A ſhort Poſtſcript beg'd a line to bleſs his Solitude: She taking her Pen, while <hi>Bileront</hi> ſtaid, wrote thus:
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <pb n="148" facs="tcp:151648:80"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>Loviſa</hi> to the Prince <hi>Emilius.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>AH! Prince! why do you ſtill perſiſt in my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndoing: the diſtance was too great before, now the Ducal Crown hangs near your Brow: Court Glory, that's the Brighter Mistreſs; and gives Reward beyond the Power of</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Poor <hi>Loviſa.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>The Prince was tenderly touch'd with the kind Doubts of his Beloved, and in a ſhort time viſited her, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed his ardent Vows of Conſtancy, and Endleſs Faith. Whilſt <hi>Lodowick,</hi> whoſe Glaſs told him he was not Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handſome; who Danc'd well, Dreſt well, had all the Perfections of a Young, Empty, Airy Courtier; and Maſter of a vaſt Eſtate; raged to be Repuls'd in his firſt Amour. One day he grew ſo importunate to know the Cauſe of her Averſion; that ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented it; and told him ſharply, he
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:151648:80"/>
was Troubleſome; and were it not for the Commands of thoſe, whom Reverence taught her to Obey; ſhe had, long e'er that, forbid him her ſight. He Anſwer'd warmly, with an Air too haughty for a Lover: I ſee too well your ſcorn; but I fain would find (what 'tis ſaid, we can't in Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man) a Reaſon for't. Is your heart made of that impenetrable Mould, that Sighs and Prayers are vain Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries; or doth ſome hidden happy Youth rob me of my deſir'd Prize? She bluſht at that, and he obſerv'd it. Ah! 'tis ſo; (went he on) your conſcious Bluſhes reveal it. If I bluſh (return'd ſhe, with a look full of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and Diſdain) 'tis at your Rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Go— You are Inſolent! Durſt your conceal'd Lover call me ſo (ſaid he, throughly nettl'd;) I cou'd An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer him. As he ſpoke the laſt words <hi>Emilius</hi> enter'd, and hearing 'em ſo loud, he ſtopt. When <hi>Lodowick</hi> turn'd to go away, <hi>Emilius</hi> came up to him, and looking fiercely on him,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:151648:81"/>
ſaid, <q>Is this like a Man of Honour, to be Noiſy in a Ladies Chamber! I ſay 'tis Inſolent, and Brutal.— Now your Anſwer you threaten'd— Not to my Country's Heir (return'd he, Bowing) nor dare I contend for a Jewel, my Prince lays Claim to.</q> Soon as he had ſaid this, he went out. <q>Ah! what have you done? (Cry'd <hi>Loviſa,</hi> looking with a Melancholy ſweetneſs on him) this flies like Lightening, through the Court, and I muſt never ſee you more! Never ſee me more (anſwer'd he eagerly) Oh! I muſt ever ſee you; nor can it be conceal'd! My Eyes, my Tongue betray it. How often, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares, I ſtart; miſtaking every Name for yours! My longing looks devour your Charms; my Sighs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>double at your ſight; and every Motion ſhows the Fires of my Soul! Oh! I'll caſt me at my Obdurate Father's Feet; nor leave his Sacred Knee, 'till he has given you to my Wiſhes. Flatter not your ſelf with
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:151648:81"/>
vain Idea's (ſaid ſhe, ſadly;) The Duke, I know, will never yield; and my Foreboding Heart whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, this is the laſt time we e'er ſhall meet in Peace.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Am I thus Bleſt (cry'd the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported Prince) to perceive ſuch a concern at the deteſted Thoughts of Parting! My, once ſevere, but now more Charming Fair! What ſhall I ſay, or how Expreſs my Joys! <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſa,</hi> who had haſtily diſcover'd more of her Heart, than ſhe deſign'd; felt her lovely Face glow with Bluſhes; and walking from the Prince, a great Glaſs more plainly ſhow'd her this diſorder. <hi>Emilius</hi> following, ſmil'd to ſee the becoming Confuſion that Excellent Maid was in. And forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that it was the publick Room of State, and the hour of Viſiting; Caught her hand, and kiſt it with a happy Lover's Ardency; whilſt two or three Ladies enter'd. The equal ſurprize of that Amorous Pair, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd it to be more than a common
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:151648:82"/>
piece of Gallantry. However the Ladies, out of Reſpect, took no notice of it there; but once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd, the Blaze was ſet abroad which <hi>Lodowick</hi> began; and it was grown the only News the Court was full of. Every Body had got the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Prince <hi>Emilius</hi> Ador'd <hi>Loviſa;</hi> and happy was ſhe could firſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate it to her Friend. The Duke was laſt inform'd, becauſe all lov'd the Prince, and fear'd his being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleas'd. At length an old Courtier, one who had liv'd even paſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of his Youth, thought this Match inconvenient, and poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickly reſolv'd to tell him. He heard the Relation with a fierceneſs beyond that which his own rugged nature gave. <q>Unthinking, Unambitious Boy! ſaid he (juſt as the other finiſht) have I, for this, with pains obtain'd to bleſs his Nuptial Bed with <hi>Iſabella,</hi> the wealthy Princeſs of <hi>Mantua;</hi> and doth the idle Slave to his Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, worſhip the fading Beauties of a
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:151648:82"/>
Bauble; whilſt the choiſeſt Jewel of a Crown is offer'd?</q> With this, he flew to the Apartment of the Dutcheſs. His Eyes carried Rage, that every cringing Courtier ſhrunk into a Corner; and durſt not meet their Fury. The mild, and ever gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Dutcheſs, trembled at his ſight, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe heard the ſtory. When with Frowns uſhering in his words, he thus began: <q>You, Madam, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, have fondl'd up your Son to this, like a true Mother; but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like my Wife indulg'd his humours, 'till inevitable ruine has got within his graſp. Nor wou'd you yet cry hold! rather than your Child ſhou'd grow uneaſy, give it the Poyſon. I thought your Son haunted your A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partments not to learn the Rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Honour; they are ſeldom to be found amongſt the Women! Alas, my Lord! (interrupts him the Affrighted Dutcheſs) I know not what you mean! No, no; (went he on) you have not conniv'd, nay,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:151648:83"/>
perhaps, deſir'd that Rebellious Boy <hi>Emilius,</hi> to make Love to your fair Favourite <hi>Loviſa!</hi> But, mark me, Madam! For by Heaven I ſwear, let this be remedy'd, or you will find the conſequence will give you cauſe to tremble! I know the Maid is Virtuous (ſaid that good Lady, with all imaginable Mildneſs;) her Birth is Noble, ſince her Blood is mixt with yours: but, that my Son, or <hi>Loves,</hi> or Courts her, witneſs the Heaven you ſwore by, I know not. My Blood! (replies he, all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag'd) the ſtream has run too far; and all that's Royal is loſt! But were ſhe my Brother's Daughter, and a Bar to my deſigns made me retrench my words, or promiſe gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: Cloyſter, or Death ſhou'd force the ſtubborn Girl; and ſet the way clear before me. Therefore I charge you, School your Son, and diſpoſe of her; elſe I, who have been the Partner of your Bed theſe Thirty Years, will ever after prove
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:151648:83"/>
a Stranger and a Foe!</q> This ſaid, he left the weeping Dutcheſs.</p>
               <p>Poor <hi>Emilius</hi> was juſt going to his Mother, there to open all his heart; and beg her kind Aſſiſtance to mollify his Father. He ſent <hi>Bileront</hi> before humbly to pray the Dutcheſs; ſhe wou'd, in her Cabinet, hear him on a ſubject, that was to him important. <hi>Bileront</hi> ſtreight return'd, and told the expecting Prince, the Duke was gone thither with an angry Brow. <hi>Emilius</hi> fear'd the worſt, and ſtaid conceal'd till the Duke return'd; then going to the Dutcheſs, in her melting Eyes, he reads his Fate; and ſtood a while immoveable. That ſweet Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs no ſooner beheld her Son look ſo pale, and deeply ſad, but her Tears increas'd. For the Duke had rightly charg'd her in that particular: She excelling moſt Mothers in Fondneſs. The Prince firſt broke ſilence; and reſpectfully askt her, if he might know what his Father had done, to cauſe thoſe Sorrows? Firſt Anſwer
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:151648:84"/>
me (ſays the Mourning Dutcheſs) are you ſo Unhappy to love <hi>Loviſa?</hi> Pardon me, my Mother (ſaid <hi>Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> in a moving tone) nor call me Unhappy, in loving, and being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lov'd, by that Virtuous, all-deſerving, Nobleſt Maid! This Declaration touched the Dutcheſs nearly; and ſhe, word for word, told that deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing Prince, what his Incenſed Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had ſworn. <q>Therefore (added that Wiſe, yet tender Mother) quit thou thy unauſpicious Love, before the threatn'd ſtorm comes on: it hangs juſt breaking o'er our Heads; and if thou perſiſt, falls upon all. Quit my Love! (anſwers the Prince paſſionately) Ah! Madam! E'er you reſolve to be obey'd, pleaſe to hear, how great a Villain you wou'd make your then abject Son! <hi>Loviſa,</hi> moſt perfect of her Sex, by nature reſerv'd and cold, unapt to Love; One, who lays not out her wondrous ſtock of Charms, to catch at Hearts; but declines
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:151648:84"/>
her modeſt Eyes; nor Triumphs, nor rejoices in her Conqueſts. This I ſaw, and lov'd her for't; purſu'd her with a Paſſion violent and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feign'd: I ſigh'd, I kneel'd, I pray'd; nay, quite Unmann'd, I even Wept before her. She ſaw, I joy'd in nothing but her ſight: My alter'd Face ſhow'd the pangs, my aching heart indur'd. Mov'd at laſt, ſhe kindly heal'd my Suffering with gentle pity. And ſhall I quit the dear relenting Saint? I, who drew her to love's bewitching Miſchiefs, againſt her Inclinations, almoſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing her tender heart, guarded with an averſion to Mankind, now ſhall I quit her? Oh! never! ſooner I'd quit my Birthright, turn Lunatick, Naked travail the inhoſpitable World; feel firſt the diſtracting grief needs muſt ſeize my Dear one, ſhou'd I prove ſo baſely Wicked to forſake her? Leave me (ſaid that tormented Mother) for this but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes the Woe, that my heart is
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:151648:85"/>
already too full of.</q> The Dutcheſs ſeeing the Prince thus obſtinate, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves to try a gentler ſubject. He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gone, ſhe ſent a Page of Honour, to call <hi>Loviſa</hi> to her. That Noble Maid had heard nothing of theſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbances; and readily obey'd; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering the Cabinet with a chearful Countenance. But when ſhe ſaw the Dutcheſſes ſorrow, her heart ſunk downwards, and ſhe appear'd juſt ſuch another Statue, as the Unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate <hi>Emilius</hi> did before. <q>Come near, my Charming Charge (ſaid the Diſconſolate Dutcheſs;) thy dying Mother left thee to my Care. Have I not been careful of thee? Speak boldly, <hi>Loviſa,</hi> and accuſe me if I utter any untruth! Royal Madam (anſwer'd the kneeling fair) were I to recount the Favours you have done, and I receiv'd, long hours wou'd unheeded paſs; and yet the obliging ſtory not half be finiſhed. Here, near your own Apartments, Lodg'd, Honour'd, Lov'd, and
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:151648:85"/>
ſmil'd upon, as if I had been your Daughter. Riſe (reply'd the Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſs) and if your Soul is grateful, now's the time that you, by one great Act, may Cancel all theſe Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations, and leave me eternally your Debtor. Then conclude it done (return'd <hi>Loviſa</hi>) were it to Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice the quiet of my future days, I'd live my ſelf in Torment to give my Princeſs Eaſe. My Son — Nay bluſh not my <hi>Loviſa,</hi> I know it all, nor, were I diſpoſer of his Fate, wou'd hinder the Alliance. Thy Beauty, and Brighter Virtue, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves a Crown; deſerves <hi>Emilius:</hi> But, Oh! his Father, whoſe Rage like Madneſs, curſt with Power, knows no Bounds; whilſt the poor Youth fixt to thy Charms, and fond to Death of Thee, never will Obey. Think then the end of this Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on's Murder; thy ravag'd Country's Bowels torn; Thou the fatal <hi>Hellen</hi> that ſets the World on Fire. Reply not (went the Dutcheſs on) I know
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:151648:86"/>
you did not foreſee all this, when firſt <hi>Emilius,</hi> with a Lover's Eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, breathed his warm ſighs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>round you, woed to the ſweets of Love—Thou Weepſt, <hi>Loviſa,</hi> and I pity thee; I my ſelf have felt thy Sorrows; torn from my Virgin Wiſhes; Compell'd by Parents to wed this Duke; I took my reaſon to aid, and time o'ercame it; ſo may you, if you will hotly ſtrive. Inſtruct me, Madam, (all drown'd in tears, <hi>Loviſa</hi> cry'd) Inſtruct me, Madam, for I am at a loſs. The Heart of my <hi>Emilius</hi> is Heroick (ſaid the Dutcheſs) and force is loſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him: 'tis you only have Power to charm him to Obedience. Take then your choice, be greater than a Soveraign Princeſs; Rule your Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, let your looks deny what's acting in your heart; and tell <hi>Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> that your alter'd Soul abhors his Love; elſe unite with my Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Son, and meet deſtructive ruine both. <hi>Loviſa</hi> wiping her fair
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:151648:86"/>
Eyes, and looking as if ſhe cou'd accuſe the cruel Powers: No — the Prince ſhall not for me be ruin'd; at leaſt I'll do my beſt, he ſhan't (ſaid ſhe.) To morrow, with your Highneſſes leave, I'll ſee him; and after that, I hope, you'll have no juſt cauſe to blame me. Go, my beſt Girl, (return'd the Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſs) and as an earneſt of thy truth, ſee not my Son to night; I know he'll long to tell thee all his Woes, but liſten not to the ſad ſtory, 'twill melt thy beſt reſolve, and leave thee Spiritleſs.</q> 
                  <hi>Loviſa</hi> took her leave, and promis'd the Dutcheſs what ſhe deſir'd. At the uſual hour, Diſtreſs'd <hi>Emilius</hi> ſent Count <hi>Bileront</hi> the well known way to gain admittance to his Beloved; but was ſurpriz'd when he brought him back word, ſhe was not to be ſeen; not well, and gone to Bed. Not well; and gone to Bed (repeated the Prince) return, my Friend, and tell her I have Buſineſs of Importance. Oh! ſhe has heard
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:151648:87"/>
the Unlucky Story; and now, in Anger will not ſee me! Tell her I am Innocent; tell her I cannot live beneath my Griefs, unleſs the dear ſight of her ſupport me. To pleaſe the Prince, that faithful Friend went, and came again with the ſame An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. The Prince was vex'd, only he comforted himſelf, that, if ſhe wou'd not ſee him privately, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the World, reſolv'd to profeſs his Endleſs Love. Next day, as he and <hi>Bileront</hi> were walking in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Grove, his ſurprize was aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, when <hi>Loviſa</hi>'s Page accoſted them, and ſaid his Lady deſir'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to ſpeak with them both. As they croſs'd the Court which leads to <hi>Loviſa</hi>'s Lodgings, the Prince ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd her Coach and Attendance ſtand ready. His Heart miſgave him, though he knew not why. When they came up, they found her ſitting in her Cloſet, with her fair Friend, who was always her lov'd Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; both dreſs'd in Habits for a
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:151648:87"/>
Journey. <hi>Loviſa</hi>'s Eyes were full of Majeſty and Reſolution. Love, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aw'd durſt not peep, nor ſhow a beam of pity. <q>I ſent for you (began the Life of all <hi>Emilius</hi>'s Joys, in a tone far different from the uſual ſweetneſs:) I ſent for you here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe two the conſtant Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of all our Follies paſt; to give you back your Vows, to free you from the luckleſs Chains you choſe. Recal your ill-plac'd Love, the haſty errour of your Youth, and think of it no more.</q> 
                  <hi>Emilius</hi> view'd her with a piercing air, and falling at her feet; the poſture his humble Love had often us'd him to: <q>In vain, ſaid he, in vain you give me back, what I can never take. What have I done? Why am I doubly puniſh'd, with my Father's frowns, and yours? When I, but in thought, conſent to what he offers, may ſome God to you reveal that thought; and may you then for ever, juſtly look as cruelly as now. I ſtand prepar'd
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:151648:88"/>
(ſaid <hi>Loviſa</hi>) for all that you can ſay, foreſeeing the horrid ills that may accrew, if we ſhould follow the blind track, raſh, inconſiderate Love wou'd lead us. Therefore, obey your Father, Eſpouſe the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs <hi>Iſabella</hi> — Ha! (begun the Prince) I beg you — interrupt me not (went ſhe on) If you'll do this, I inſtantly will go and remain with my Uncle, <hi>Don Alvarez,</hi> till this diſcourſe, which buzzes thus in every buſy Mouth, is huſh'd. I'll ſtill preſerve you in my heart; I'll ſee you when I may with honour; and my Friendſhip ſhall excel vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Love — Yet I have not done (ſhe perceiving him go to ſpeak) if you agree not to what I've ſaid, at leaſt conſent; then I, this very moment, will drive directly to St. <hi>Clare,</hi> the next adjacent Monaſtery, be ſtraight immur'd, Probation year and all; nor will I ever hear, ſee, or, if poſſible, think of <hi>Emilius</hi> more. Do not hope Prayers or
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:151648:88"/>
Tears can ſtir me — May Poverty, Diſeaſes, loſs of Fame attend me, if one jot I vary or change from what I've vow'd! This is not ſure, the ever gentle Goddeſs, I thus long have Worſhipt (ſaid the Prince with Eyes all languiſhing) ſome Tygreſs hath uſurpt the Face of my Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and form'd thoſe cruel words, I laſt have heard!</q> 
                  <hi>Loviſa</hi> riſing, and making a ſign to the other Lady, who was to go with her, to be ready, haſtily catching hold of her Gown, <q>
                     <hi>Loviſa,</hi> (ſays he) my Life! See, <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leront!</hi> See! How have I Dreamt! not worth a Look! a Sigh, a part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Word to think upon! Ah, Prince! (return'd that Self-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining Maid) ſhou'd I give the Deluge way, it would o'erwhelm me! Go, inexorable, go; (ſaid the Prince, letting looſe his hold) my Death I'm ſure you'll bear as Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concern'd as this! For I feel greater Pangs, than bittereſt Death could bring; though dreſt in new inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:151648:89"/>
Tortures; exceeding all the old. Oh! Wrong me not (ſaid ſhe paſſionately) to that degree! Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveſt thou I am unconcern'd? Oh! No! I ſhare thy Agony, my Dear; my lov'd <hi>Emilius!</hi> Take from my Arms, the firſt, the laſt Embrace, that e'er you'll receive from your <hi>Loviſa!</hi>
                  </q> He claſpt her to his heart, and wou'd have ſpoke, but ſtifling Joys o'ercame, and left him almoſt Breathleſs on her Boſom: When, ſhe, fearing her Virgin Modeſty had yielded too far, work'd by the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce's Sorrows, and her Love; ſtart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from his Arms; and, ſwift as an Arrow, paſs'd the Chambers towards the Coach. Scarce cou'd <hi>Bileront,</hi> and 'the Lady o'ertake her.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Loviſa</hi> left the Court of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> and went directly towards the Palace of her Uncle <hi>Don Alvarez,</hi> which was many Leagues from thence. When <hi>Bileront</hi> had put her into the Coach, he return'd to the Prince; who, like one ſtupify'd,
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:151648:89"/>
leant againſt a Cabinet. <hi>Bileront</hi> rous'd him, and begg'd he'd go; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Servants wou'd obſerve him. He, by his Friend's perſwaſion, almoſt inſenſibly remov'd from her Cloſet to his own; then throwing himſelf upon the Floor, he ſaid all a violent deſpair cou'd prompt. <q>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces harder brook to have their wiſhes croſt than other Men; their Birth, their Education flatter 'em; the World was made for them. <hi>Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milius</hi> was young, his deſires fierce, his Miſtreſs fair; and, what pierc'd deepeſt, willing, on Honourable Terms, to grant the long'd for Bliſs.</q> The old Duke, who thought a great point gain'd in <hi>Loviſa</hi>'s being remov'd; left him to himſelf a while, in hopes he'd Conquer theſe Relu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctancies, and prove Obedient: but he, wholly given up to Melancholy, found the Paſſionate Thoughts, that poſſeſs'd his Love ſick Mind, too en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining to be diſmiſs'd. His Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net and Cloſet-walks, where none
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:151648:90"/>
but Faithful <hi>Bileront</hi> gain'd admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, took up moſt of his hours. When he was forc'd to appear, his Eyes carry'd the marks of his diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; his words were few, and ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, as if his Mind was ſtill on ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe.</p>
               <p>The Duke perceiving <hi>Emilius</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulg'd his Paſſion, and yielded to his Bonds, inſtead of ſtrugling to get looſe, ſent for him, and beginning mildly ſaid, <q>I well hop'd, my Son, that before this, reduc'd by reaſon, you wou'd have acknowledg'd your Failings; rendr'd me juſt Gratitude, in a thankful Obedience. — Open your blinded Eyes, and view the dazling glory of an Illuſtrious Birth, and Royal Fortune. Is a ſubject to be prefer'd to Her? Far be it from me (reply'd the Prince, reſpectful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) to derogate from the Princeſs of <hi>Mantua:</hi> She may be, for ought I know, a Miracle. Wou'd my Royal Father permit me not to injoy my Wiſhes, that were too mighty for
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:151648:90"/>
my hopes; only leave me but free from others, as I am debarr'd from her I love: That's the humble All I ask!</q>
               </p>
               <p>This was not what the Duke ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected; and as it was conſtraint on him, to make uſe of Mildneſs, like a Bow bent backwards, he impetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly returns to Rage. <q>Says he (looking ſternly) Am I to be thus dallyed with, Fooliſh Boy? Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare to Execute what I Command, with readineſs; leſt my Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, great as thy Folly, reach thee! An Extraordinary Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour is now diſpatching, with my laſt Orders for the Court of <hi>Mantua;</hi> I'll ſend the Articles to be by you perus'd, and expect your Letters; Letters fit for <hi>Emilius</hi> to write, and <hi>Iſabella</hi> to receive. 'Command my Life, (Anſwers that Afflicted Prince, kneeling) and without a murmur, I'll Obey. Alas! Sir, I reſpect the Princeſs <hi>Iſabella</hi> more than you; I wou'd not betray her to Faithleſs
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:151648:91"/>
Arms, where ſhe muſt ever meet with Coldneſs, Neglect, nay Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, inſtead of Conjugal Affection. Thou ſtubborn Fool (retorts the Duke, in a furious tone) born for my Curſe, and thy own Undoing!— but I ſhall find a way, at leaſt, to Plague thee, if thou darſt refuſe the offer'd Bleſſing. By Heaven! — I'll have thy Miſtreſs Poyſon'd, or elſe try'd for a Witch, and ſo Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd! Her Sorceries have ruin'd thee! Doſt thou not fear me! As I am a Man, (reply'd the Prince, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and looking with a becoming Bravery) and (what'd yet more) your Son; my Soul has ſtill a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger been to fear! heap tortures on my diſobedient Head! Caſt me from your ſight, and Throne: nought that's Unmanly; nought that's Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious ſhall appear in all my Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings. With Patience, I'll renounce all the glorious Honours that my Birth provides; forſaking all at your Command: all but my Unhappy
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:151648:91"/>
Love; whom I am ſure, what e'er you have ſaid, you will not wrong. Princes ſhou'd not extend their Power to hurt the Innocent, or force their Laws Interpreters to find out Crimes where there are none; and puniſh where they ſhou'd reward! Go from my ſight (cries the Angry Duke!) Blot and Contagion of my Blood! — And if thou doſt not Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and with my Will comply; unheard of Curſes o'er take you! — You, and your dear Deſtruction, <hi>Loviſa!</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The Lords, that ſaw the Prince paſs through the Anti-Chambers, from his Father, perceiv'd additional Vexations in his Face. Many, who lov'd him, wou'd have follow'd; but he forbad them all, and enter'd his Cabinet alone.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bileront</hi> no ſooner heard of his new Diſcontents; but making uſe of what the Prince's Favour had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd, a Key he had of the Cloſet; without Commiſſion ventur'd to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:151648:92"/>
him. Good Heavens! what ſorrows touch'd that Compaſſionate Lord; when he beheld the ſame Hero, whom he had ſeen foremoſt Charge the Turkiſh Troops, and laſt Retreat; now extended on the ground; giving way to Griefs ſcarce fit to be recited of the great <hi>Emilius!</hi> See here (ſay'd he, caſting his ſad Eyes on <hi>Bileront</hi>) the deſtin'd Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom! the deſtin'd ſlave! the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple's Property! Who for their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Intereſt, and a cruel Father's Arbitrary Will, muſt be, for ever, join'd to what he hates; and loſe the Brighteſt Bleſſing, the ſofteſt Good, that e'er Adorn'd the World! Many, and tender were the Complaints <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milius</hi> pour'd into the Boſom of his lov'd Friend; who comforted him with all the ſweetneſs faithful Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip cou'd Inſpire.</p>
               <p>Next day, the Duke ſent the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Marriage to his Son; with Command that he ſhou'd examine them, and return his Anſwer. But
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:151648:92"/>
                  <hi>Emilius</hi> abſolutely refus'd to look upon 'em. This gave freſh Rage to the already Incens'd Duke; and he reſolv'd the Dutcheſs ſhou'd not loſe her ſhare of the vexation. Again he ſtorms at her; reiterates the cruel Vows of deep Revenge; whilſt that Diſtreſs'd Lady ſeeks to her lov'd Son in vain; who only Anſwers her In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaties with far fetch'd Sighs, and looks of wild deſpair. She writes to <hi>Loviſa;</hi> and conjures her to ſtudy ſome means to oblige <hi>Emilius</hi> to yield.</p>
               <p>The retir'd <hi>Loviſa,</hi> who poſſeſs'd her fill of Melancholy (though her Indulgent Uncle, fond as a Father, ſtudy'd to divert her) receiv'd this Letter, as the extended Malice of her Fate, that knew no end. And, far from joying at the Prince's Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, wept at the Miſchiefs her reſiſtleſs Eyes had caus'd. <hi>Loviſa</hi> knew <hi>Emilius</hi> was not naturally ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born or Diſobedient; therefore in the movingeſt terms her Soul cou'd di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate;
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:151648:93"/>
(her deſire and wiſhes for his real Good o'ercoming Love) ſhe writ to him.</p>
               <p>The Prince might more properly be ſaid to be Immur'd, than Retir'd. For he permitted none to ſee him, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>Bileront,</hi> and Servants, juſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to wait on him. The Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſs firſt receiv'd <hi>Loviſa</hi>'s Letter; and having perus'd it was pleas'd. She Seal'd it again, and gave it <hi>Bileront</hi> to deliver.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Emilius</hi> ſaw <hi>Loviſa</hi>'s hand, he kiſs'd it eagerly; and tranſported, cry'd, <q>What Summons hath my Goddeſs ſent? Has ſhe kindly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers'd my Doom; and given me leave to ſhare her Baniſhment? Oh! <hi>Bileront</hi> (went he on, his Eyes ſparkling with the ſame Paſſion, his heart was full of) Methinks I cou'd do wonders for my Love, wou'd ſhe conſent! With her, fly the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>urs of an Inexorable Father! Fly Ungrateful <hi>Parma!</hi> And in ſome peaceful Corner of the Globe, fix my
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:151648:93"/>
unimitable Fair; whilſt for the loſs of Crowns, Glory, Ambition, All, bewitching, dear, delightful Love makes up, and far excels.</q> He open'd the Letter, and <hi>Bileront</hi> ſaw his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance alter, as he read it; that ſhort Beam of Joy which ſo lately ſhone through his Face, Eclips'd with blacker Clouds of ſadneſs, than before. <q>Read, my Lord, ſaid the Prince, for ſure my Eyes, only us'd to ſorrow, transform the words of Kindneſs into Cruelty; even from her.</q>
               </p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Loviſa</hi> to the Prince <hi>Emilius.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>WHen will my Malignant Stars have ſhed their Baneful Venome? Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſleſs Heaven! Muſt I with Justice complain of <hi>Emilius?</hi> Muſt he become my greateſt Perſecutor? And, by his cruel Obſtinacy, draw down the Curſes of late Posterity upon me? Will no Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment but a Monastery, though never ſo remote, prove an <hi>Aſylum</hi> for this Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur'd
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:151648:94"/>
Wretch? I've cauſe to think you wiſh me in a Cloyster! Now Prince, you ſhall have your deſire! Conclude, within few days, I am a Votareſs! Since you diſlike the offers I made at parting; ſince my Eternal Love promis'd as far as Honour wou'd allow, on the Condition of your Obedience, is not acceptable: My next Task ſhall be, to baniſh you my Heart! This is the last unalterable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve of</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>The Unfortunate</hi> Loviſa.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>After <hi>Bileront</hi> had ended the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Prince remain'd half an hour ſilent; then riſing haſtily from the Couch, where he had thrown him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he took his Pen and wrote; and giving it to his Favourite, bid him carry it to the Dutcheſs; ſaying, he ſuppos'd <hi>Loviſa</hi>'s Letter came by her Approbation; and he hop'd ſhe wou'd like the Anſwer. <hi>Bileront</hi> did as Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and the Dutcheſs found theſe words.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="177" facs="tcp:151648:94"/>
                     <head>Emilius <hi>to</hi> Loviſa.</head>
                     <p>BAniſh'd <hi>Loviſa</hi>'s Heart! That's a puniſhment I cannot bear: Believe me, Madam, I'd ſooner choſe to Reign Abſolute Monarch there, than over half the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe. But ſince the unrelenting Fates deny, rather than be totally Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd, give me that cold Corner allow'd for Friendſhip. Change your unjuſt Deſign of Quitting the World, as I muſt do the happy Name of your Adorer; to that of</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Your Eternal Friend and Servant,</hi> Emilius.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Think you my Son is real in this, ſaid the Dutcheſs; I know not, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, (anſwer'd that young Lord) Indeed, in my Opinion, his looks diſcover a new Reſolution. The Dutcheſs diſpatch'd away her Letter; and ſtraight put the Duke upon ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Articles again to the Prince;
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:151648:95"/>
which he did; and <hi>Emilius</hi> imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ſign'd them; and ſaid his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to the Princeſs, ſhou'd be ready, in a day or two. He appear'd pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly, look'd pleaſantly; and all, except <hi>Bileront,</hi> thought the Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unfeign'd. The eyes of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, next to Love, are the moſt Pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>Bileront</hi> alone obſerv'd his ſtolen Sighs; and thoſe Abſences of Mind, which ſo oft poſſeſs'd him. And meeting him opportunely, he with a concern'd obliging Air, began. <q>What Breach of Faith have I been guilty of; wherein offended, that my Lov'd Royal Maſter hides from me his Soul; conceals from me, as well as all the World, the Griefs that Prey upon his Noble Heart! Griefs (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd the Prince Ironically) I've none; Am I not to Marry the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanta!</hi> There, Beauty, Wealth and Merit join to Bleſs my future Reign. Ah! Prince (return'd <hi>Bileront</hi>) why will you uſe your Faithful ſervant thus? I wou'd not preſs, nor wiſh
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:151648:95"/>
to know your ſecret thoughts, but only in hopes to aſſiſt, to ſerve you. Be ſatisfy'd (ſay'd the Prince, going towards ſome Company, he ſaw:) I conceal nothing from you, or if I do; 'tis becauſe I'll not In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volve my Friend in the inevitable Woes, ordain'd for me.</q> 
                  <hi>Bileront,</hi> cou'd not anſwer then; but he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to Watch him. That night Letters for <hi>Iſabella</hi> were to be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd to the Duke; on the Pretext of writing them, <hi>Emilius</hi> diſmiſs'd his Attendance; and ſhutting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf up in his Cloſet, ſaid, when his writing was over, he'd ſleep the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining part of the Night, upon his Couch. <hi>Bileront,</hi> who heard theſe Orders, hid himſelf behind a looſe piece of hanging, till the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants were all gone. Then ſteal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing along, he ſoftly Unlock'd the Cloſet Door. The Prince was wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, though not to <hi>Iſabella;</hi> he heard <hi>Bileront</hi> ſtir and turning with a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Aſpect, ask'd who was there!
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:151648:96"/>
That Faithful Lord, affrighted to ſee his Prince look ſo ſtern, caſt himſelf at his Feet; and, with Tears, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plor'd he might ſhare his Fate. For (ſaid he) I'm ſure you have deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd to abandon <hi>Parma,</hi> rather than your Fair Miſtreſs. The Prince cou'd not but be ſenſibly touch'd to ſee the ſincere Affection of the Count; and Raiſing him, ſaid with a ſigh, why wilt thou not with Fortune, leave the Wretched loſt <hi>Emilius?</hi> I am a Barque, that's Bound for ſure De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction! All near muſt ſhare the Tempeſt; and meet the Face of horrid Ruine! Did I like a Coward, (Anſwer'd <hi>Bileront</hi>) ſtart from your ſide in War; that I am now Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carded? No, No! (return'd <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milius</hi>) nor did I then Deny thy Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Alas, Alas! It is not now the Field of Honour, <hi>Emilius</hi> ſeeks! Lethargick Love hath ſeiz'd my Soul; and in a Cell I mean to Dream away my Life! Endeavour not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading me (went he on) ſhowing
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:151648:96"/>
him a <hi>Cordelier</hi>'s Habit; near theſe, the only Robes, that I ſhall ever wear, a Dagger lies; if I'm preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that ſends me to a long Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Sleep! Therefore, if, out of Zeal to my advantage, as thou think'ſt it, this gets air, before I am paſt their reach, they take me dead, my <hi>Bile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ront,</hi> unalterable truth is in my words; thou may'ſt believe me. <q>I do believe (ſaid that Troubl'd Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident;) and only beg to partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate. I can brook the ſolitude of a Cell, as well as my dear Lord; nay the Court wou'd ſeem to me a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart, were you abſent. No; by our paſt Friendſhip, I conjure you, ſtay (returns the Prince) on that condition, I'll, to you alone, unfold what I've deſign'd. I'm inform'd, near the Palace of <hi>Don Alvarez,</hi> there ſtands a Monaſtery of the <hi>Cordelier</hi>'s, thither I direct my ſteps; ſpeak once to my <hi>Loviſa;</hi> then leaving <hi>Parma,</hi> Imbarque for <hi>France;</hi> and in ſome Cloyſter, I beſt ſhall like,
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:151648:97"/>
end my wretched Days. I tell you this (continu'd he, with a reſolv'd Countenance) and you know, what I have ſworn, if you diſcover it. I am not us'd to faulter or break my word, therefore, Dear <hi>Bileront,</hi> now retire. I'll ſend you word of my abode in <hi>France;</hi> and ſhall accept a Viſit kindly.</q> 
                  <hi>Bileront</hi> ſaw it then in vain to diſwade him, and having learnt where he went, deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to follow him, ſaid nothing againſt it; only ask'd him, how he thought to get admittance amongſt the Fathers. That Contrivance is Comical enough (returns the Prince; forcing a ſmile) for I have here (ſhowing him a Letter) with my own Hand and Signet, recommended my ſelf, as a Fryar of my Acquaintance. I have alſo a Compound to turn my Complexion Yellow; and a Powder to black my Eye-brows. All is ready; the Letter for the Duke my Father, and the Dutcheſs; whoſe troubles for this concern me neareſt. Once
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:151648:97"/>
more, my Faithful Friend, Farewel, ſaid he, Embracing <hi>Bileront;</hi> who unwillingly left him; ſatisfy'd in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but his deſign to ſee him again before he parted from the Monaſtery of the <hi>Cordeliers.</hi> He gone, the Prince, about three a Clock in the Morning, taking the Habit with him, leſt any of the Centry, ſeeing him like a <hi>Cordelier,</hi> ſhou'd give Information, when the hunt was made for him. He paſs'd unobſerv'd; or if any did ſee him, he was ſo us'd to walk ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and alone, that there was no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice taken of it. The firſt Thicket he reach'd, he pull'd off his own Upper Cloaths, and put on the Veſtments of a Fryar, and tying a ſtone to his Coat, threw it into an adjacent River. You know, my Illuſtrious Auditors, (ſaid <hi>Franciſco) Emilius</hi> is a very Fair Man, his Eyes ſweet, and his Hair very light; to alter which, he took his Compound, and waſhing his Face, and delicate Hands in it; appear'd juſt of a Sun-burnt Yellow. Then
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:151648:98"/>
blacking his Eyebrows, he lookt ſo chang'd, his moſt intimate Friends cou'd not have known him. He had put up a conſiderable quantity of Gold; ſo, the firſt conveniency of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding he met with, he made uſe of; and paſs'd ſecurely; not ſo much as hearing any inquiry made after him. Being arriv'd at the Cloyſter, and ſhowing Prince <hi>Emilius</hi>'s Letter, the good Fathers receiv'd him with infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Civility. They obſerv'd him Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, and unwilling to ſpeak; and, out of Reſpect; askt him few Queſtions. He ſaw the Turrets of <hi>Don Alvarez</hi>'s Palace; and after a repaſt had refreſht him, he cou'd not forbear asking one of the Fathers to walk. He choſe to go that way; and when near the Houſe, the Palpitation of his Heart inform'd him how <hi>Dear Loviſa</hi> was. He ask'd the Father, who that Palace belong'd to; and being an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd, as he expected, to <hi>Don Alva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez:</hi> I was told (ſaid he) <hi>Don Alva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez</hi> was your Neighbour, and have a
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:151648:98"/>
Meſſage from the Prince to him, which I deſign to Morrow to deliver. We have a nearer way than this (ſaid the Fryar) which leads us from our Orchard-Walls, through his Groves of Oranges and Jeſſamin, to his door. This pleas'd the Prince, and he ſoon retir'd; all Night revolving in his Love-poſſeſs'd Mind, how he ſhou'd ſpeak with <hi>Loviſa</hi> alone. He, at length, concludes to deliver a Letter, as from <hi>Emilius</hi> to <hi>Alvarez;</hi> wherein the Prince ſhou'd deſire him to let the <hi>Cordelier</hi> ſpeak alone with <hi>Loviſa.</hi> Wiſht Morning being come, our Royal <hi>Cordelier</hi> roſe, and being by one of the Society directed, entred thoſe Fragrant Groves: whoſe ſweets, wafted by the early breeze, wou'd have Banquetted Senſes, leſs imploy'd; but <hi>Emilius</hi> thought on nothing but <hi>Loviſa.</hi> When he was got pretty near the Gates of the Houſe, he heard a Clock ſtrike Four; which as it were awak'd him out of his Contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and made him conſider, how
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:151648:99"/>
improper a time it was, to diſturb a Nobleman's Family. This thought turn'd him again into the Grove, and ſeeking out of the direct path, ſome Grotto ſuitable to his Melancholy, he obſerv'd a part of the Grove in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clos'd; which lookt extream ſhady; he, without much trouble, got over this Incloſure, and found the thick gloomy ſhade, dark as he cou'd wiſh. Vaſt aged Trees form'd the grand Walk; whoſe high meeting tops, and ſtrait Trunks, lookt Majeſtick; and a Myrtle Hedge grew thick and even about their Roots, which added to the Beauty of the Place. Behind this Hedge, upon high Graſs, <hi>Emilius</hi> threw himſelf along. His Anxious Thoughts, thoſe uſual Torments, a while imploy'd him; till Nature's Reliever, ſoft refreſhing ſleep, the effect of reſtleſs Nights, ſeiz'd him. This prov'd the very walk <hi>Loviſa</hi> lov'd; nor had the Prince repos'd long, before the Voice of that perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Object of his Soul wak'd him.
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:151648:99"/>
He found 'twas ſhe, and her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion: Love made him curious to liſten if their diſcourſe related to him; and concealing himſelf, he heard the Lady, that was with her ſay, When, Madam, will theſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Griefs leave your diſconſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late hours. You ſhun the fond Indear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of your Uncle, that you may take your fill alone of heart-breaking ſorrow: Your Eyes have loſt their wonted Vigour; and your lovely Cheeks, like gather'd Roſes, Fade; and in their prime, forſake their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Luſtre. You promis'd, when the Prince obeyed his Father, and inſtead of burning Love, embrac'd cool Friendſhip: You wou'd mourn no more. His Letter aſſures you this is done; yet I behold no alteration. Still the days are tedious, and the Nights are worſe. <hi>When</hi> (I beg to know!) will your Woes have End? <q>With my Life (anſwer'd that Sigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Afflicted Fair.) Though, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ye Powers (ſaid ſhe, looking
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:151648:100"/>
up;) who, with eaſe can view the inmoſt Receſſes of my Soul; and plainly ſee what's Acted there: Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, I ſay, if I not rejoice, that Prince <hi>Emilius</hi> to Duty, and to Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon yields; quitting the Weight, the Burthen inſupportable of Blind im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuous Paſſion; that ſinks <hi>Loviſa</hi> down to Ruine. Mutual Love cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates a pleaſing Habitude of Joy; wherein the Mind tranſcendently is Bleſt: and which Time, that with Oblivion buries all things, can ſcarce blot out. 'Twas not with eaſe the Uſurper got Poſſeſſion here (went ſhe on; pointing to her Heart) nor will he be with eaſe diſlodg'd. All the Sighs and Tears it coſt <hi>Emilius</hi> to gain this Virgin Heart, to bind it in the Inchanting Chains of Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick Love; I muſt, with Intereſt, pay back, e'er I can ſet the Throb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing Priſoner free. Perhaps i' th' Conflict too the Rebel, ingag'd too far, may break. I have alſo a part of Falſhood to Act: Think'ſt thou
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:151648:100"/>
continu'd ſhe, looking on her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion;) I deſign never to ſee <hi>Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> more? No, no: ſpight of the Promiſes, wherewith I've flatter'd him; ſoon as he is happy in the Arms of <hi>Iſabella;</hi> the Cloyſter, to which I've only ſeem'd averſe, hides me for ever.</q> The Prince, who cou'd no longer bear his Miſtreſs ſhou'd think him guilty of breaking Vows, he left a Crown to keep, met her at the end of the walk, and fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at her Feet, he Embrac'd her Knees, and ſaid, <q>If <hi>Loviſa</hi> never became a Recluſe, till <hi>Emilius</hi> is happy in the Arms of <hi>Iſabella,</hi> the Church will loſe its Faireſt Votary.</q> Who can expreſs the ſurprize of <hi>Lovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa</hi> and the other Lady! The Voice was the Prince's, but the Face, the Habit, contradicted that thought. <q>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens! (cry'd <hi>Loviſa,</hi> in raiſing him) it cannot be Prince <hi>Emilius!</hi> Why ſhou'd my Life (ſaid he; looking paſſionately on her) wonder at the Metamorphoſis? Was this the
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:151648:101"/>
hardeſt Task my cruel Love injoin'd; My Fate revers'd, I ſhou'd only talk of Joys and Bleſſings. Ah! Prince, (ſaid <hi>Loviſa</hi> in a moving tone and air) was this well done? Didſt thou fear I ſhou'd too ſoon forget thee. Cruel Man, thus to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt the Peace I am ſtriving for! Go to the Royal Nuptials, thy Fate prepares; and leave me! Leave me <hi>Emilius,</hi> to my Belov'd, and choſen Solitude. I do deſign to leave thee, (reply'd the Prince,) Thou Dear, thou only Charmer! Excellent Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man! The Firſt, the Laſt, that e'er poſſeſt <hi>Emilius</hi>'s Heart! I'm for ever going; puſh me not from thee, with precipitated haſte; Let me but gaze a moment, graſp thy lov'd hand, and bear it to my trembling Lips; print my laſt Kiſſes there: I'll then purſue what, ſure as Death and Fate, I have reſolv'd. What, dear Bewitching Talker, (returns <hi>Loviſa,</hi> her Eyes ſwimming in Love and Tears) What haſt thou reſolv'd?
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:151648:101"/>
Even in theſe very Weeds to be for ever ſhrowded (ſaid <hi>Emilius</hi>) and far, far hence removed; at once forſaking, what to Death I loath; and what more than Life I lov'd! This muſt not be (<hi>Loviſa</hi> interrupts him): Rob not the World, and your Unhappy Country, of Virtues, which as they are Exemplary, ſhou'd be Conſpicuous: that the Great Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may incourage a degenerate Age; and make the Subject bluſh at Vices which his Prince abhors. Ah! Do not vainly waſt the laſt, and only precious moments of my Life (cry'd <hi>Emilius.</hi>) Death, or a Cell, I've ſwore, by all that's Sacred! There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no more, my Love; look on me, as a Wretch that's dying, as one Condemn'd; without the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of a Reprieve; with gentle pity ſooth the rugged'ſt blow of Fate, Eternal Parting. And for the Eaſe of my divided Heart, which with unbated Paſſion ſtill will heave and ſwell, and pant at thought of
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:151648:102"/>
thee, give me thy Promiſe to keep thy Faith inviolate. When, I, low as the Duſt, ſhall grovel in my di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant humble Cell; let me hug this thought; not Crowns, nor Youth, or Beauty, tempts <hi>Loviſa</hi> to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain another Love; and blot the loſt <hi>Emilius</hi> from her conſtant Mind. Is this all, thou dear Deſerver (ſaid <hi>Loviſa,</hi> looking on him with the kindeſt aſpect in the World?) Ah! poor return for ſo much worth; for ſo much Love, I'd be laviſh in my Proteſtations, were there need; but ſure <hi>Emilius</hi> neither knows himſelf, nor me, when he requires one. You are for a Cell, and where, think you, I am to be diſpos'd? Not in a Court, I'll promiſe ye! Diſtant, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, our Cells will be; but the thinking Mind can travail, in one moment, many Leagues. I'll beg of Heaven, it may be no Offence to dedicate, each Day, ſome lov'd pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar hours to thee. I'll think of every tender word, and look, and
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:151648:102"/>
Bluſh, as it were Acting o'er again. This ſhall be the Banquet of my Mind, all Times, beſides thoſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted to my Sighs, and Sadneſs! Oh! unequal'd Charmer (anſwer'd the Tranſported Prince) why doſt thou talk thus? Why did I beg for Kindneſs, when my fooliſh nature cannot bear it! That I cou'd now, this inſtant, fall a Victim at thy Feet; and thereby Eternalize the greateſt Flame, that e'er poſſeſt the Heart of Man! But I will live; and ſuffer for thee! Yes, my Fair Saint! Judge thou thy ſelf, if 'tis not grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Pain to live than dye; to live without the <hi>Wretched'ſt</hi> laſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, <hi>Hope;</hi> to rave; to love like me; even to Madneſs Love. And in all theſe heights, to leave Thee! Parted by Seas, and Wilds, and Alps, and what's yet a greater Bar, a Father's Curſe! Thou Cold Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numming Hand of all-deſtroying Death, ſeize me. Embalm'd by my <hi>Loviſa</hi>'s Tears! At her Feet Expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:151648:103"/>
is a quick Conveyance to a qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et Grave; a Bleſſing I wou'd court with the ſame Eagerneſs, as others ſhun approaching Fate.</q> His looks, which the very Image and Impreſs of unartificial ſorrow bore, gave terror to his words, and wou'd have pierc't Souls more inſenſible than <hi>Loviſa</hi>'s, or her fair Friend's. That Friend, a ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful Spectator of this diſmal Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, told <hi>Loviſa</hi> ſhe heard the Gates open; and believ'd it was for <hi>Don Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varez,</hi> who was coming to ſeek her. <hi>Loviſa</hi> Conducted <hi>Emilius</hi> away, to avoid her Uncle, out of this Inner Grove. At parting, Grief grew too big for Words: A ſtrict Embrace, and mingl'd Tears, conclude the cruel Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration. Not that <hi>Loviſa</hi> fear'd <hi>Don Alvarez</hi>'s knowing the Prince in his Diſguiſe: only the mutual Trouble, and Confuſion they were in, was too viſible, and of neceſſity muſt have been perceiv'd. This occaſion'd her to haſten him away, before her Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle reacht the Place.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="195" facs="tcp:151648:103"/>Diſconſolate <hi>Emilius</hi> return'd to the Monaſtery, inwardly bewailing his Condition; eſteeming himſelf the moſt deplorable of human kind. His Body yielded beneath the Fatigues of theſe perplexing Inquietudes; ſo that he was taken very ill. The careful Fryars did their beſt to comfort, and refreſh him. He deſir'd to be left alone to his Repoſe; though, in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, 'twas only to enjoy the Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly Cogitation, his diſappointed Love ſuggeſted.</p>
               <p>In the Evening, one came and told him, a Gentleman inquir'd for the <hi>Cordelier,</hi> that came the night before. This put the Prince upon his Guard; he bid 'em Conduct the Stranger to him; and contriv'd his Fatal Dagger in a readineſs, to give him liberty, if they offer'd to ſeize him. But he found thoſe Thoughts needleſs, when he ſaw <hi>Bileront</hi> enter. <hi>Emilius,</hi> with a ſad Air, turn'd from him; and ſaid, Why doſt thou follow me? Thy of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficious Love is grown troubleſome of
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:151648:104"/>
late. Condemn me not, till you have heard what I have to ſay (reply'd <hi>Bileront:</hi>) <q>Alas! there's an altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a fatal wondrous ſort, ſince your Departure. Our Duke—Cruel though he be (interrupted <hi>Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi>) Heaven preſerve him ever from approaching Danger</q> — The Prince ſilent, <hi>Bileront</hi> reaſſumed his Diſcourſe. <q>The Morning your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs left the Court, the Duke pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd to hunt, and inquiring for you, was told, that out of reſpect to the Princeſs <hi>Iſabella,</hi> with your own hand, you had been moſt part of the night writing. This pleas' him, and he ſaid, you ſhou'd not be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb'd. He had not rode far, before his Horſe unfortunately threw him, and he receiv'd a dangerous wound in his Head. He was brought back to the Palace, juſt as the Dutcheſs was inform'd of your being gone. This Completion of Misfortunes o'er-whelm'd her. The Duke fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſeveral times at the dreſſing of
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:151648:104"/>
his hurt; yet knows not of your Abſence; though, when he cou'd for his intolerable pain ſpeak, he has often ask'd for you.</q> 
                  <hi>Emilius</hi> lookt earneſtly in <hi>Bileront</hi>'s Face; trying to diſcover whether this ſad Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was Truth. <hi>Bileront</hi> perceiving his Doubts, with earneſt Aſſeverati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons confirm'd what he had ſaid, and convinc'd the Prince. He alſo told him, how he had contriv'd to leave ſome Servants, with Cloaths for him, and directed him the way to enter the place privately; and get ſhifted without diſcovery. <hi>Emilius,</hi> though indiſpos'd, prepar'd to ſee his Dying Father; his Nature was Tender; and notwithſtanding Almighty Love, this ſad accident toucht him nearly. Yet wou'd he not forget his Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Fair, but contriv'd a Letter, which being of neceſſity to be ſent by one of the <hi>Cordelier</hi>'s, he wou'd not uſe his own hand or name, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd <hi>Bileront</hi> to write the following words.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="198" facs="tcp:151648:105"/>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Madam,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>THE <hi>Cordelier,</hi> you ſaw to Day, in the Garden, begs you wou'd defer all haſty Reſolutions. An Affair of weighty moment calls him back to Court; in a few Days this ſhall be Explain'd. What I have ſaid, is by directions from the— What remains, is only that I am</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Your moſt Humble, and Obedient Servant,</hi> Bileront.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>Emilius</hi> gave a Fryar this Letter, and charg'd him to deliver it that Night. Then he took his leave of thoſe Hoſpitable Fathers; ſaying, he was ſent for in great haſte, to Court; and promis'd that he wou'd acquaint the Prince, how Courteous, upon his Account, they had been. <hi>Emilius</hi> fancy'd his Deportment ſo odd in the Convent, that their Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity might prompt them to open
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:151648:105"/>
the Letter; which caus'd him to have it writ ſo ambiguouſly. But they, without the leaſt thought of ſuch rudeneſs, accompliſht his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Loviſa</hi> had, the remainder of that Day, been diſcourſing with her Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of her reſolution to enter the Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nery of St. <hi>Clare.</hi> That good Man us'd all the Arguments, a tender Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection cou'd Inſpire, againſt it. Told her, that being Childleſs, he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd her for his Heir; which, ſaid he, added to your own Fortune, will, as to Eſtate, render you a Match for any Prince in Chriſtendom. And Beauty, Virtue, or whatever Graces elſe adorn your Sex, the World, that is, the Happy World which knows you, with Juſtice, owns you, in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, Miſtreſs of.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alvarez</hi> ſaid this, and a thouſand more kind things, to no purpoſe. Gratitude and Love poſſeſt her Noble Soul; nor cou'd ſhe in honour act leſs; when brave <hi>Emilius</hi> ſet the
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:151648:106"/>
great Example. The Arrival of the <hi>Cordelier,</hi> with the Letter of <hi>Bileront,</hi> ſurpriz'd her extreamly; and for the time deſir'd, ſhe remain'd in won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous Expectation; framing many Conjectures wide of the matter.</p>
               <p>Prince <hi>Emilius</hi> and <hi>Bileront</hi> reacht the Court, juſt as the old Duke had been in another ſwooning Fit. <hi>Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> went directly to the Dutcheſs; who almoſt Diſtracted with her Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expreſſible Sorrow, beheld him as a Viſion. After the Dutcheſs had chid him for his Diſobedience; ſhe, in Mourning Terms of real Concern, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated the Misfortune and Danger his Father lay under; adding, that he had been, that Day, ſo earneſt to ſee him; that they were forc'd to own his Abſence. Which News the Duke receiv'd with leſs Paſſion than was expected. The next Interval, when his fainting Spirits were a little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triev'd, <hi>Emilius</hi> enter'd his Chamber, and going towards the Bed, he kneel'd. Silence and a ſadneſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feign'd
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:151648:106"/>
ſtampt his Face, with hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Duty; and pleaded more in his Excuſe, than if he had offer'd at ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuating words. The Duke beheld him, but with no ſigns of Rage, and with a weak Voice, ſaid, <q>
                     <hi>Emilius,</hi> I know my paſt Severity, rough U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, and my poſitive Commands, thy tender Nature cou'd not kindly brook. Believe me, Son, 'twas well meant; I wou'd have form'd thee, Youth, a perfect Souldier; but thy Mother's ſoftneſs hangs about thy Soul; and ſhe hath ſtampt thee all a Lover. And ſince I'm going to the Land of Peace; I will not ruffle the Calmneſs I've ſo late obtain'd, in ſtrugling with Deſires violent as yours. With my Bleſſing Poſſeſs the Miſtreſs, you with ſuch an Eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs have Lov'd; and do not hate the Memory of your Departing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who only for your Intereſt, oppos'd this Paſſion: too great, it ſeems, to be remov'd. Oh! Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens! (cries the poor Prince, o'er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:151648:107"/>
with Filial Sorrow) muſt I ne'er aim at Joys ſincere! Live, my dear Father, live; though to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue Cruel, divided ever from my Unhappy Fair, I fancy I cou'd bear it now! No more, no more, (the Duke ſtops him) on this Theme! Come nearer, receive and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the laſt Inſtructions of thy Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Father.</q> The Prince, being ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by him, he gave him ſuch Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Rules, as he, by long Practice had found moſt uſeful; the conſtant obſerving of which, has inlarg'd his Dominions, and augmented his Power.</p>
               <p>That Night the Duke Expir'd, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milius</hi> was immediately Proclaim'd, according to his Right, Succeſſor. The Young Duke manag'd his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs with a moſt uncommon Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; being Affectionately Dutiful to his Weeping Mother; and obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging all whom his Father had lov'd, and favour'd. <hi>Loviſa</hi> was, by his Order, acquainted with all theſe Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars;
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:151648:107"/>
yet ſo fearful was he of committing any undecency, that he deny'd himſelf the ſatisfaction of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her, for three Months. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of reciprocal Love, being the higheſt Abſtract of Joy, he juſtly judg'd it improper to poſſeſs at a time, which in Duty, he ought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate wholly to Affliction.</p>
               <p>All the Court look'd on <hi>Loviſa,</hi> as a Perſon ordain'd for their Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſs; and already gave her a profound Reſpect. <hi>Don Alvarez,</hi> who lov'd her entirely, was ſo pleas'd with her Exalted Fortune, that he ſettl'd all his Lands and Lordſhips on her, after his Deceaſe. This render'd it Policy as well as Pleaſure, for the Duke to Eſpouſe her; the Eſtate being too Opulent for a Subject, without dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, to injoy. The Dutcheſs Dowager prevails with <hi>Loviſa</hi> to return to Court, and the time of ſtrict Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing being over <hi>Emilius</hi> conſtantly Viſits her; his Love, if poſſible, ſtill ſeeming to Increaſe. At length, the
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:151648:108"/>
Nuptials are concluded; and with great Solemnity perform'd. <hi>Billeront</hi> deſervedly remaining his deareſt end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Favourite.</p>
               <p>I think, I ſafely may affirm (added <hi>Franciſco</hi>) Prince <hi>Emilius</hi> a happy Man. His publick Affairs are Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous, his Beauteous Dutcheſs Fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in Iſſue, as well as Charms; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dearingly kind to him; and naturally good to all. Whatever progreſs he undertakes, ſhe, by his deſire, ſtill accompany's him, except to the Camp; where he hath done won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, ſince his Acceſſion to the Throne. Demonſtrating that a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Lover may be a compleat Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier.</p>
               <p>Thus ends <hi>Franciſco;</hi> By the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of your Highneſs (bowing to <hi>Olympia:</hi>) I have, to the utmoſt of my knowledge, diſcover'd each par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular relating to the Loves of that Incomparable Pair.</p>
               <p>The Ladies were liberal in their thanks to <hi>Franciſco;</hi> and infinitely
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:151648:108"/>
pleas'd with the Narration; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <hi>Melora;</hi> her Sentiments were Delicate; and by a Sympathetic Power, the Misfortunes or Bleſſings of others ſenſibly mov'd her Paſſions. This the Cardinal obſerves, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves by a thouſand new Proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of everlaſting Fidelity. <hi>Melora</hi> was ſo full of the foregoing Hiſtory, ſhe did not ſeem to liſten much to the Cardinal's Complements. <hi>Olympia</hi> took notice of it, and ſaid <q>My Dear, you are mightily delighted with <hi>Loviſa;</hi> but I don't perceive you intend to follow her Example: She did not maintain her rigour half ſo long. True (added <hi>Barberino) E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milius,</hi> in all his Sufferings, had the rich Cordial of <hi>Loviſa</hi>'s Love for his ſupport; but I pay all my Vows to an obdurate Rock; to a fair Marble Statue; Deaf to my Prayers, and with my Sighs unmov'd. I thought reply'd <hi>Melora,</hi> (Bluſhing and look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on <hi>Olympia</hi>) my Royal Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs wou'd have chid me, as diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:151648:109"/>
my Weakneſs too far: and I aſſure you, my Lord (went ſhe on ſmiling) you cannot oblige me more than in comparing me to Rocks and Marbles, and ſuch impenetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſtuff: for I have a great vanity to be thought Inexorable.</q> 
                  <hi>Melora</hi> deliver'd this with an unuſual chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful air; infinitely charming the amorous Prieſt. He ſnatcht her lovely Hand, and moulding it with burning Kiſſes, cry'd paſſionately, this warm ſoftneſs is, I'm ſure, no Kin to Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <p>Unavoidable Buſineſs call'd <hi>Olym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia</hi> next Day to the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi> For this Politick Niece of the Pope's was as buſy in the Eccleſiaſtical Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, as any Favourite Nephew, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, or ſince. Moſt part of the laſt Night at the <hi>Villa,</hi> they ſpent in wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Melora,</hi> that the next Journey to this convenient Solitude ſhou'd com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete the Happyneſs of the pretended Prince <hi>Alphonſus.</hi> Reiterated Prayers prevail'd; and that Fair Sacrifice, by
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:151648:109"/>
her ſweet bluſhing ſilence, gives con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. Tranſported with their Fatal Succeſs, they all return to <hi>Rome;</hi> the Ladies by themſelves, and the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal another way.</p>
               <p>Fate, as if not fully reſolv'd to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy ſuch Perfection and Innocence as ſweet <hi>Melora</hi>'s, made offers at a Diſcovery; offers only they prov'd, and the black contrivance went on. The firſt Proſpect of undeceiving her, was <hi>Franciſco</hi>'s falling in love with her. His being privy to the Deſign, gave him often Opportunities of her Converſation. And you may as well ſuppoſe it eaſy to dwell in Flames and not be ſcorch'd; as to be often near <hi>Melora,</hi> hear her talk, and view her Charms, yet feel no warmth. Stifl'd Fire can never be long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd; much leſs the Hotteſt Flame, <hi>Smother'd Love.</hi> Cunning <hi>Olympia</hi> catcht his unwary Eyes Rivetted to her fair Face; obſerv'd his frequent Sighs, his Tremblings, and his change of Colour, when ſhe talk'd to him,
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:151648:110"/>
or he, by accident, was near. This in the firſt beginnings of his Love, <hi>Olym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia</hi> informs the Cardinal. He conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd it as dangerous, and being ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſpatches into <hi>Spain,</hi> makes him the Chief Commiſſioner, and hurries him away; giving him no opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity again to ſee <hi>Melora.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Franciſco</hi> gueſs'd the Cauſe of this new Employ, and was upon the rack. He knew ſhou'd he diſobey, or give <hi>Melora</hi> caution of her approaching Ruine; if there were Daggers or Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to be bought in <hi>Rome,</hi> his Life muſt ſatisfy the revengeful Cardinal. Then, he juſtly thought <hi>Melora</hi>'s hate would fall on him, as well as all the reſt of her Deceivers. He vainly hop'd, diverſity of bus'neſs wou'd efface her Charming Image from his Breaſt. He knew his Fortunes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd for ever, ſhou'd he forſake a Prince Cardinal, whoſe Power was ſo vaſt to raiſe him. Yet againſt theſe, gentle Compaſſion, increas'd by Love, pleaded ſtrongly; and always whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per'd
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:151648:110"/>
him to ſave ſuch Matchleſs In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence. But e'er he had determin'd, the Impatient Cardinal forces him on Board. When <hi>Melora</hi> ask'd for him, <hi>Barberino</hi> told her he was gone to <hi>Modena,</hi> by his Order. <hi>Olympia</hi> now began to preſs her earneſtly, for this deſign'd Journey to the <hi>Villa. Melora</hi> knew what they expected from her there; and her Virgin Fears repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Marriage, without her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Knowledge, terrible ſtill, caus'd her to put it off, delaying with many excuſes. <hi>Olympia</hi> had procur'd a Prieſt, ſhe having a hundred of them at her ſervice; Preferment lying ſo greatly in her Power. The Prieſt knew not the bottom of the deſign; was only told it was two Friends of <hi>Donna Olympia</hi>'s, who deſir'd to be Marry'd privately.</p>
               <p>Whilſt things remain'd thus, with no other ſtop, but <hi>Melora</hi>'s delays; ſhe happen'd, paſſing through her Father's Hall, to drop a Letter of the Cardinal's; which her Father, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:151648:111"/>
her, took up, and read theſe words.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Divine Princeſs,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>Each moment, that I ſee you not, ſeems to drag a heavy Chain. To live another Day and Night without you, wou'd be a Torment wholly Inſupportable. When I ſee you next, to read a little An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in your lovely Eyes, for my long ſtay, will pleaſe me more than the ſmiles of Empreſſes. So much is every word and look priz'd by the Humbleſt of your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The Embaſſadour ſtrait calls for his Daughter, and ſhowing the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in his Hand, ask'd her from whom that Piece of Gallantry came? It is obſervable that Women are ſo ingenious and quick at nothing, as the Affairs of Love. And the moſt ignorant and illiterate, commonly have cunning enough to manage an Intrigue. I believe, the Reaſon is, Love being the moſt agreeable Paſſion
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:151648:111"/>
of their Minds, employs every Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of their Soul readily; no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then <hi>Melora</hi> was ſo quick at an excuſe. For ſhe, without any heſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, anſwers her Father, it was a Letter of her own compoſing, and deſign'd for <hi>Olympia.</hi> He ſuddenly returns upon her, but how comes it then in a Man's hand? I have it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways drawn over by one of her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges (replies <hi>Melora,</hi> without any vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible diſcompoſure) to divert her the more. Though this ſounded a little ſtrangely, yet ſo unblemiſh'd was the Carriage and Converſation of this Young Lady, that her Father gave her back the Letter, without the leaſt miſtruſt. Glad was <hi>Melora</hi> thus eaſily to recover it, and going to <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lympia</hi> acquaints her with the ſtory. Who, thereupon preſſes her again for the Marriage; aſſuring her that the Duke's Bus'neſs went on ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully; and that ſhe wou'd quickly be Proclaim'd Dutcheſs of <hi>Ferrara</hi> and <hi>Modena;</hi> will you then (adds ſhe
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:151648:112"/>
earneſtly) neglect the opportunity of this proffer'd Glory; and by back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs delay time, till ſome ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter accident occur, that may fruſtrate all our deſigns? Theſe Arguments, deliver'd by ſo faithful a Friend, as <hi>Melora</hi> took <hi>Olympia</hi> to be; mov'd her to yield.</p>
               <p>This joyful News is communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Cardinal, who came that Night, and expreſſes his tranſports by a thouſand Extravagancies of Fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Now the third Journey is made to the <hi>Villa,</hi> where theſe Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Nuptials are Celebrated; at which <hi>Hymen</hi> ought to have hid his Face; and only <hi>Portentous Omens</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Melora</hi>'s Genius ſtill whiſpers ſhe has done ill; which foreboding Thoughts take from her Eyes their chearful Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre. Innumerable were their Prayers before they cou'd obtain a full Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation: at length powerful im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity overcomes; and the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal has ſacrific'd to his Luſt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture's
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:151648:112"/>
Maſter-piece. Who, if her Fate had equall'd her Beauty, and other rare Indowments, might juſtly have expected in reality, as much Greatneſs, as <hi>Olympia</hi> only flatter'd her with.</p>
               <p>Six Months this Inſatiate Prieſt Revels on that Luxurious Banquet, Blooming Youth, and yielding Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. By which time his fierce deſires begin to cool in that certain Cure for Love full Enjoyment. Then he, with vexation reflects on the almoſt unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable ſums, this ſhort-liv'd Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure hath coſt him; beſides <hi>Melora</hi>'s Pregnancy; which, ſpight of their utmoſt indeavours, wou'd, in a ſhort time, appear; adds infinitely to his Terrors. Theſe Thoughts take from his Converſation that Vivacity and Livelyneſs which before made it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. <hi>Melora</hi> quickly perceives this alteration; and ſenſibly reſents it. Her demeanour was replete with Duty and Love; nor can ſhe but with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expreſſible regret, indure this cold
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:151648:113"/>
return. He excuſes it with the croſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Affairs; which <hi>Melora</hi> in part believes: for by the publick Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe at her Father's, ſhe under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands the real Duke of <hi>Modena</hi> was near a Rupture, with the Pope; and that a War was like to follow. She repreſents this to <hi>Olympia;</hi> who puts her off with fair words only.</p>
               <p>Whilſt theſe unhappy things were Acted in and near <hi>Rome,</hi> the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mention'd <hi>Franciſco,</hi> whoſe Soul was agitated with a hundred different Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, arrives in <hi>Spain.</hi> But nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Sea, nor diſtant Climates, can Efface <hi>Melora</hi> from his Memory. Slight Wounds, Abſence and Time may heal, but this Charming Beauty gives no ſuch; and his pains aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Then he Curſes his Cowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, and calls himſelf a thouſand Villains, for leaving the Lady ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd; firſt to the Luſt, and then the Cruelty of the Cardinal. For he knew <hi>Antonio</hi>'s Temper too well, to doubt Barbarity would follow his ſatiated
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:151648:113"/>
Love. Theſe Apprehenſions diſtract him to that degree, that he reſolves to leave unfiniſh'd all his Bus'neſs, and return diſguis'd to <hi>Rome;</hi> and reſcue, if poſſible, the Guiltleſs Maid from the Jaws of Ruine.</p>
               <p>Purſuant to this deſign, he imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately goes on Board; but is unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunately, by contrary Winds, kept on the Seas, till the time is Elaps'd for his doing any ſervice to <hi>Melora.</hi> At length, he lands, comes to <hi>Rome</hi> in the Habit of a Pilgrim; diſcolour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Face to that degree, that 'twas impoſſible any Body ſhou'd know him. He rejoices in his ſafe Arrival at <hi>Rome;</hi> and vainly hopes, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing hath hitherto diſappointed the Cardinal's Conſummating his Wiſhes. Then Love preſents him, with the falſe flattering Joy (it being natural for that Paſſion to deceive us:) that he, ſaving <hi>Melora</hi> from the dire Fate that hung over her; ſhe might, in recompenſe give him leave to own his Flame. Not then conſidering,
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:151648:114"/>
that, when <hi>Melora</hi> was convinc'd of the Treachery deſign'd againſt her, ſhe muſt needs deteſt every Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Treaſon. Now the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty that remain'd, was the getting an Opportunity to ſpeak with <hi>Melora,</hi> ſhe being perpetually almoſt at <hi>Olym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia</hi>'s, where he not daring to venture, was in a great Perplexity. He lurks in the Evening near <hi>Olympia</hi>'s Houſe; diſcovers the Cardinal go in, by an uſual door of the Garden, and reſolv'd to watch his return; but was amaz'd to find it not till the Morning's ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach. Then his fears began to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form him, all help was paſt; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever delays muſt certainly make it ſo. Therefore he deſigns the next time <hi>Olympia</hi> went to the Pope's Palace, to ask boldly for <hi>Melora,</hi> and truſt to his Diſguiſe. But he was prevented in this, by ſeeing <hi>Melora</hi> take Coach in the Afternoon, accompany'd only by <hi>Olympia</hi>'s Woman; and inquiring whither the Coach was going, he was inform'd to <hi>Olympia</hi>'s <hi>Villa.</hi> He
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:151648:114"/>
immediately follows them; and the next day, with a Key he had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, got into the Garden; hoping he might find <hi>Melora</hi> there; if he did not, he knew his Habit would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect him from Violence, ſhou'd any of the Family ſee him. But here his Wiſhes were anſwer'd; for e'er he had ſearcht far, he beheld that ſweet Lady lying on a Bed of Graſs, near a Fountain, whoſe murmurs joining with her own Sorrows, had lull'd her into a ſlumber. For ſorrowful he perceiv'd ſhe had been, by the rich dew which wet her Handker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, and yet hung upon her fair Cheeks. He cou'd ſcarce view this Mourning Fair, without joining in the Womaniſh Grief. After he had gaz'd, and ſigh'd, and talkt things, ſad as deſpair cou'd utter; he ſpies her Table-Book open; where ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſeem'd to have been juſt writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. Taking it up, finds theſe lines.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="218" facs="tcp:151648:115"/>
                  <l>Happy's the Nymph born in a homely Seat,</l>
                  <l>Nor knows the troubles of the rich and great.</l>
                  <l>Wrapt in th' Embraces of her faithful Swain,</l>
                  <l>Feels ſtill new Joys with no allay of pain.</l>
                  <l>Ambition ne'er diſturbs their gentle Love,</l>
                  <l>Nor Cares, nor Fears, their harmleſs Mirth remove.</l>
                  <l>In Huts as humble as their Minds they lye,</l>
                  <l>And lofty Roofs deſpiſe that reach the Sky.</l>
                  <l>To theſe alone does Heaven true Joys di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpence,</l>
                  <l>And with content rewards their Innocence.</l>
                  <l>Content a Jewel that is ſeldom known</l>
                  <l>To bleſs or beautify a Regal Crown.</l>
                  <l>Ah! How have my unwary Footſteps ſtraid,</l>
                  <l>While noiſe and glory my ſoft hours be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray'd.</l>
                  <l>My purchas'd Pomp my Happyneſs has coſt,</l>
                  <l>So in purſuit of Toys the Gem is loſt.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Alas! Unhappy Beauty, ſaid he, with a ſigh: (as he had done reading) if thou art already ſad, how wilt thou mourn with endleſs Wailings, when the bottom of thy Fate is known! all the woful truth diſcover'd. This, <hi>Franciſco,</hi> Tranſported with his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:151648:115"/>
ſpoke ſo loud, that he wak'd the ſleeping Fair; who ſeeing a Man ſo near her, ſtarts up and cry'd, who art thou, that thus rudely preſſeſt on my ſolitude, and diſturb'ſt my quiet Moments? A Wretch (he anſwer'd, putting one Knee to the ground) that's born to Curſe himſelf; nay worſe, one whom you are bound to Curſe, with direſt Imprecations purſue, nor ever mention, but when an Invective of the bitter ſort muſt follow. Sure (replies <hi>Melora</hi> calmly) you take me for ſome other Perſon, ſince I dare boldly ſay, my Conſcience, my Soul's faithful Regiſter, does not accuſe me with ſo much Injuſtice, as ever to have an Inclination to Curſe a Stranger, much leſs one who bears the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Show; which I, in all Perſons, venerate. Is this Voice wholly a Stranger to you (he return'd paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately.) Oh that it were; or that the Name of <hi>Franciſco</hi> had been blotted with Eternal Oblivion, rather than have reacht the Ears of the Ador'd
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:151648:116"/>
                  <hi>Melora!</hi> Or that an avenging Bolt had ſtruck me to the Center, before I had been made the deteſted Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of deceiving you! Why do you perplex me thus with Riddles, (ſays <hi>Melora;</hi> the Blood beginning to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake her Cheeks) if you are <hi>Franciſco,</hi> my Lord's Chief Favourite, whom he ſent to <hi>Modena:</hi> what means this Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit? And why this ſtrange Addreſs? Your Lord (anſwers this feign'd Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grim haſtily)—then all my fears are true; and you muſt prepare to hear a ſtory, at which my Bleeding Heart ſinks down, and my faultring Tongue almoſt denies me power to relate. What does <hi>Alphonſus</hi> then deſign to abandon me? (interrupts the fearful Creature, falling upon a Bank, her trembling Knees not being able to ſupport her:) has he cruelly reſolv'd (went ſhe on, all in Tears) to deny his Marriage, and expoſe me, and his Off-ſpring to endleſs Infamy? Oh! haſte! Deliver me from theſe Fears; or ſee me dead! And is (ſaid
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:151648:116"/>
ſhe, before he cou'd ſpeak) <hi>Olympia</hi> join'd with him, in my undoing? Why do you not anſwer me, and eaſe my Throbbing Heart? If the Duke and ſhe are both falſe to Love, and Sacred Friendſhip, pronounce my Doom, at once; let me not linger long in Torments. Since Providence has Ordain'd you ſo unkind a Fate (replies <hi>Franciſco</hi>) take to you, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, the reſolution, your Innocence affords: Let your Injuries diſrobe your Soul of Tenderneſs: Arm your ſelf with a noble ſcorn; and make your juſt Reſentments overcome your Sorrows. Oh! Do not pauſe (cries that weeping Fair) go on; though it give me Death. Heaven is my Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs (ſays he, ſtill delaying) I wou'd not undeceive you, ſo ſad's the task, did not I fear a farther Miſchief. But, to prevent that, know, Madam, your Husband is not <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> nor Duke of <hi>Modena;</hi> but <hi>Antonio Barbarino,</hi> the Pope's Nephew. He aſſumes moſt unjuſtly, the Title of Cardinal Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron;
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:151648:117"/>
when in reality he is a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer of his Country, and an utter Enemy to all Goodneſs. As <hi>Franciſco</hi> was about to proceed, he perceiv'd a deadly paleneſs to o'erſpread <hi>Melora</hi>'s Beauties; and after ſome Efforts of ſtrugling Nature, ſhe fell into a Swoon. Never any perplexity equall'd this poor Lover's; he was unwilling to call any of the Houſe to her aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, becauſe he had not finiſh'd his Diſcovery; nor given her a Caution of <hi>Barbarino</hi>'s Cruelty. He runs to the Fountain, ſprinkles ſome of it's Waters on her Face, bows her Body gently forwards; at laſt ſhe revives. Caſting her lovely Eyes, o'erwhelm'd with Sorrows, upon him, ſhe ſaid with a Sigh: <q>Ah! Cruel Man! why have you brought me back to this deteſted Light; which, I muſt never more view with Chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs! Yet, how know I (adds ſhe, recollecting her ſelf:) but you may be an Impoſtor, and forge this Story, to abuſe my Friend, and
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:151648:117"/>
Lord. On that condition I wou'd part with my right hand replies this guilty Informer: No, Madam; what I averr, is too ſad a Truth: <hi>Antonio</hi> is the Man: I can bring you, where you ſhall ſee him in his Scarlet Robes going to the Conſiſtory. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold here (went he on, pulling Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers out of his Pocket) Diſpatches written with his own hand; which, I believe you know. <hi>Melora</hi> cou'd not but own ſhe did; having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd a hundred Billets-Doux's, in the ſame Character. Fly then Madam, (proceeds <hi>Franciſco</hi>) from this moſt abhor'd of Men, and Baſeſt of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, whoſe degenerate Souls cou'd Betray ſuch Matchleſs Virtue, to Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parallel'd Ruine. I am certain their wicked deſigns will not end thus. For when the Cardinal who knows not to put a true Eſtimate on Beauty, has ſatiated his Luxurious Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite: your Death (Ah diſmal Thought! cries he, in a Tone wholly Paſſionate) your Death will follow:
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:151648:118"/>
I have heard them ſo reſolve. Whither ſhall I fly (replies the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolate Lady) with this Guilty Load! Not to my Incens'd Father; he will upbraid me with my Diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and ſay, my Puniſhment is a juſt Reward for my crime. Oh! Heavens! (ſay'd ſhe) may I not murmur, may I not Complain: that theſe Probations are too ſevere for my Frailer Sex to bear! Conſider, Madam, (replies the truly Afflicted <hi>Franciſco</hi>) Parents are Indulgent; and when he ſhall hear the Truth; which I will alſo, with my Life at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt; your Innocency, and Nature pleading in your behalf; will force him to receive you with Paternal Tenderneſs: Therefore haſten from this Diſſolute Prieſt; whoſe many Luſts and Impieties to relate, wou'd die your cheeks in a modeſt Crimſon: <hi>La Cecca Buffona</hi> was once his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, and Glory'd in her ſhame. Then to a Courteſan, who dwelt in the <hi>Julian-ſtreet,</hi> he gave, to
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:151648:118"/>
ſatisfy his Luſt but once, a Thouſand Crowns: not to mention the more than Brutal Paſſion he hath oft had for his own Sex.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>My Soul ſickens at theſe Black Relations; (ſay'd <hi>Melora</hi>) and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Innocence Dy's in my Womb.</q> As ſhe was ſpeaking; a Page enters the Garden, and tells her <hi>Donna O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limpia</hi> was juſt Arriv'd; at which <hi>Melora,</hi> compoſing her ſelf as much as poſſibly ſhe cou'd, prepares to go and receive her. But firſt ſhe deſires <hi>Franciſco</hi> to make her Father's Houſe his Sanctuary; and tells him ſhe will Eſcape thither, if by none of their ſtratagems prevented, the next Day; adding, that till ſhe came, he ſhou'd not mention any thing of theſe Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Circumſtances. <q>I will, in every particular, obey you, (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers that Dejected Man) but e'er I go, I wou'd, on my Knees, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore what will, in you, be an Act of Mercy, almoſt above a Mortal; and bring to my deſpairing Soul, the
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:151648:119"/>
only Balſam, that can heal it's ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corous Wounds, and deter my Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate Hand, from Committing on my Body the Violence, my Guilty Thoughts ſuggeſt: I mean, Forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Madam, if from your fair Mouth I hear my Pardon Seal'd, I ſhall embolden'd grow, and look towards Heaven for Mercy; elſe, I muſt ſink to the diſmal Grave, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd o'er with trembling horror, and never hope with Joy to riſe.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Bear Witneſs Heaven (replies that lovely Creature; her intermingling Tears almoſt hindering her Speech) I forgive you, and may that bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſtore, from whence Eternal Mercy flows, forgive you too! Yet give me leave, <hi>Franciſco</hi> to add, it was unkind, mighty unkind, thus to betray a harmleſs Maid; who never ſo much as in thought har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour'd a wrong to you. 'Twas Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous; — 'twas ſomething worſe than I can give a name to (replies her Idolater, almoſt-raving).</q> 
                  <hi>Melora</hi>
                  <pb n="227" facs="tcp:151648:119"/>
interrupts him, and Commands him to riſe, and fly to his intended refuge: ſaying, ſhe knew <hi>Olympia</hi> wou'd im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately be there. He obeys, and departs with the ſaddeſt aſpect in the World. Aſſoon as <hi>Olympia</hi> had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers'd with <hi>Melora,</hi> ſhe diſcover'd the preſſure upon her Spirits; and plainly ſaw ſhe put a great conſtraint upon her ſelf, to appear chearful. At firſt <hi>Olympia</hi> imputed it only to the Cardinal's Abſence, and told her, in a gay ſtrain, ſhe muſt not be ſo fond; but however to ſatisfy her longing, the Duke would be there that Night. Will he, Madam, (Anſwers the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with an Air of ſcorn) and when ſhall we injoy this glorious Splendor, my dazl'd Eyes have but in Fancy ſeen? Methinks I wiſh my Lord wou'd quit his pretenſions to <hi>Ferrara,</hi> and be content with <hi>Modena;</hi> that will ſatisfy my Ambition. <hi>Melora</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd this in a tone ſo different from that ſhe us'd to diſcourſe of his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs in, that the cunning <hi>Olympia</hi>
                  <pb n="228" facs="tcp:151648:120"/>
fixing her Eyes upon her, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately gueſs'd, ſhe had ſome Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Deceit; and making her a ſlight Anſwer, goes to inquire who had been there; and underſtands by the Page that went into the Garden, a Pilgrim was ſeen talking with her. Whilſt ſhe was buſy'd in this Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, her Woman brings her word the Cardinal was in her Cloſet, and deſir'd to ſpeak with her before he ſaw <hi>Melora. Olympia</hi> flies to him, but e'er ſhe cou'd deliver her News, <hi>Barbarino</hi> greets her with this: <q>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam (ſays he) I have this day had Intelligence from <hi>Spain,</hi> that <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſco</hi> has quitted the Negotiation, I imploy'd him in there, in a diſguiſe.</q> Nay then the Riddle's Explain'd, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies <hi>Olympia,</hi> and relates all the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Paſſages. Upon this, they both agree to ſend a couple of Truſty Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants in ſearch of this Feign'd Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grim; who ſhould ſeize him, and lay him faſt; rightly conjecturing his deſign was to publiſh their Crime.
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:151648:120"/>
Theſe Fellows o'ertake the wretched Man, before he was got half way to <hi>Rome;</hi> his Afflictions hindering his ſwift travelling: They ſtraight bind, gag, and hall him back to <hi>Olympia</hi>'s; where he is committed cloſe Priſoner to a remote Chamber. Now theſe two wicked ones, the Cardinal and <hi>Olympia,</hi> begin to conſult farther, and take <hi>Melora</hi> into their Conſideration. After a thouſand Arguments and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons urg'd backwards and forwards, her doom is ſeal'd.</p>
               <p>Thus this Lovely Roſe, the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful exceſs of extravagant Nature, whoſe blooming ſweetneſs wou'd have given years of Rapture, to an honeſt, honourable Husband: is <hi>now,</hi> by the very Poſſeſſor, Condemn'd to Fade, and wither in the Thoughtleſs Duſt. Nor cou'd her Pregnancy, even by <hi>him</hi> (which wou'd have made Barbarians to have Melted;) move this Inhuman Cardinal. No; his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation is concern'd, and ſhe muſt dy. That enſuing Night accordingly
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:151648:121"/>
                  <hi>Olympia</hi> deliver'd to this moſt Cruel Man a Powder, whoſe fatal Power wou'd, in Twelve hours time, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly diſſolve that well appointed Union of the Soul and Body. At Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per they conclude to give it her in a Glaſs of Wine and Water; they three always eating in <hi>Olympia</hi>'s Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, without Attendance, except <hi>Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice,</hi> becauſe the pretended Duke was not to be ſeen by the Servants.</p>
               <p>Full of theſe Helliſh Reſolutions <hi>Olympia</hi> goes to ſeek the intended Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctim; finds her in her Cloſet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly kneeling, directing her Pious Prayers to a place, where Perſons guilty of <hi>Olympia</hi>'s Crimes, muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver enter. A ſight, one wou'd have thought, ſhou'd have ſtruck that Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Woman with remorſe. But ſhe, unmov'd, proceeds, and with a ſeeming chearfulneſs, asks <hi>Melora</hi> to go with her to the Duke. This diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolate Lady's Face was deckt in Sorrow's chiefeſt Robes; yet, through all that Clouded Sadneſs, ſuch a
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:151648:121"/>
World of Beauty ſhone, as wou'd have turn'd a Tyrant's Rage; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arm'd the Fury of Irrational Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and preſerv'd her in the very Paws of Lyons. But the Bloody <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barino</hi> views her with relentleſs Eyes; and with his own hand preſents her the poiſonous Draught, which the trembling Lady drinks: For every thing ſhe fear'd; yet hop'd they were ignorant of her Information. Now, the Plot for the Cardinal's re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval to <hi>Rome</hi> muſt be Executed. To that end <hi>Olympia</hi>'s Woman brings her a Pacquet, ſaying a Gentleman, in great haſte, had juſt brought it. In this Pacquet, there is a Letter direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Duke of <hi>Modena;</hi> which he reads with ſhow of great concern, and tells the Ladies he muſt needs leave them inſtantly, and poſt back to <hi>Rome.</hi> Poor <hi>Melora</hi> inwardly rejoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces at his deſign; having reſolv'd to deny him her Bed, which ſhe fear'd might betray her knowledge of their Treachery. He takes his leave with
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:151648:122"/>
ſeeming Reluctancy, and returns to <hi>Rome,</hi> jocund that his Luſt is ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd, and his Crime like to remain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcover'd. <hi>Melora</hi> retires to her Chamber betimes; deſigning to make her Eſcape early the next Morning; and then thinking her ſelf out of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, ſhe reſolves to leave a Letter, that ſhall accuſe <hi>Olympia</hi> of that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidious dealing ſhe hath us'd towards her. She writes the following Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and lays it upon her Table in the Cloſet; and intends to leave, the next day, the Key in the Door.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>
                        <hi>To</hi> Donna Olympia.</head>
                     <p>IF Providence favour my Innocence, before this come to your hands, I ſhall have eſcaped your Power. Think then, Madam, how the judging World, when they know my Wrongs, and hear my Story, will Condemn you of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nexam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pl'd Perfidy, that you muſt for ever hide your guilty head; lest, as you paſs, the Virgins Curſes catch you, and bring
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:151648:122"/>
down ſwift Deſtruction. You have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray'd the moſt truſting Maid Breathing: one, who wou'd willingly have laid down that Life you ſo unkindly purſue, for your ſervice; and for that Luſtful Satyr, whoſe Crimes no Age can parallel. Tell him, when I appear, his conſcious Cheeks ſhall outvy his Scarlet. But if that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auſpicious Fate, which has led me to this heavy Misfortune, ſhou'd ſtill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue its Malignity; and let your Crimes Center in my Death: know, I can meet that with undaunted Bravery; being aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd at the laſt day, I ſhall appear in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſs'd with Myriads of glorious Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; whilſt I behold you, and your black Accomplice, rouling beneath in Sulphu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Flames; howling out dire Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, for the Cruelties practis'd on the moſt Injur'd</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Melora.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The next Morning <hi>Olympia</hi> goes into her Chamber, and finds the young Creature, according to her wiſh, dead; ſhe makes a diſmal
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:151648:123"/>
Outcry; and having drawn all the Houſe about her, Counterfeits Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows almoſt to a Frenzy. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs of <hi>Cour,</hi> her Father, is immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately ſent for; to whom ſhe continues her Grief at ſuch an immoderate rate, that he is forc'd to neglect his own Sorrows, and turn Comforter. Soon after is <hi>Melora</hi>'s private Interment; where the poor Embaſſador left all his Joys; Mourning to that Exceſs, as wou'd have mov'd a heart of ſtone. She being his only Daughter, and a Perſon of that Beauty and Parts, I muſt leave Indulgent Fathers to judge the Sorrows I cannot deſcribe.</p>
               <p>Now the Cardinal's next Buſineſs is to diſpoſe of <hi>Franciſco,</hi> which he does to the Galleys; where he may tell his deſpair, and prate of <hi>Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi>'s Cruelty, to the Winds and Seas for they aſſoon will hear him, as his Robuſt Companions. The unuſual Toils, and the intolerable Baſtinado's which the Cardinal orders to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him, quickly end his days.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="235" facs="tcp:151648:123"/>Yet theſe dark Practiſes are doom'd to be brought to light, and that by one of the Actors, <hi>Olympia</hi>'s Woman <hi>Beatrice;</hi> who taking ſome deep diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt, flies to the Embaſſador, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to that Diſconſolate Father, each particular of this ſad ſtory. The un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Marqueſs then remembers a hundred circumſtances, that convince him of the diſmal Truth. He imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately Petitions the Pope, lays open plainly the Fact, brings the Maid to atteſt it; but all in vain. <hi>Antonio</hi> and <hi>Olympia</hi> are Perſons too Great, for him to obtain Juſtice againſt, in the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi> So that he is forc'd to leave the laſt mention'd to the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of her own Conſcience for her Puniſhment, and enter himſelf a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier in the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi>'s Army; who then made War againſt the Houſe of the <hi>Barbarino</hi>'s; to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veng'd of the firſt. But Heaven's Vengeance ſlept not long; the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Pope Baniſhing <hi>Olympia</hi> to <hi>Orvieto,</hi> a City Twenty Leagues
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:151648:124"/>
from <hi>Rome;</hi> where ſhe dy'd miſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably of the Plague, abandon'd even by her own Domeſticks; and the Cardinal ſoon after, loaded with Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, and Infamy, ſunk to the Grave; by all unpity'd.</p>
               <p>Thus, Ladies, you are brought to the deplorable end of the Beauteous <hi>Melora.</hi> And as her Misfortunes muſt raiſe Compaſſion in the tender Boſoms of the Young and Fair; ſo they may ſtand a laſting Caution to beware the Inſinuations of the deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing part of your own Sex; who hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves loſt that ineſtimable and never to be recover'd Jewel, <hi>Reputation:</hi> endeavour to deſtroy Blooming Innocence. Beauty, as we may call it, is but the Paint of Nature; which, though it outlaſt the Lilly and the Roſe; yet, ſure as they, muſt Fade: whilſt a Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant Fame never dies. <hi>Melora</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not juſtly be taxed with any Miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, but venturing to Act weighty things, without her Father's Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:151648:124"/>
Yet her hard Fate may fright all from Entertaining Motions of a Marriage, how ſpecious ſoever they appear; till they have taken the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Conſent of thoſe, whom God and Nature have appointed their Governors and Directors.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:151648:125"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>Richard Wilkin,</hi> at the <hi>King's-Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-Yard.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Propoſal to the Ladies for the Advancement of their true and greateſt Intereſt. By a Lover of her Sex, 12<hi>o.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Letters concerning the Love of GOD, between the Author of the Propoſal to the Ladies, and Mr. <hi>John Norris;</hi> wherein his late Diſcourſe, ſhewing that it ought to be intire and Excluſive of all other Loves, is far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther clear'd and Juſtified, 8<hi>vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Eſſay toward a natural Hiſtory of the Earth and Terreſtrial Bodies, eſpecially Minerals: As alſo of the Sea, Rivers and Springs. With an Account of the Univerſal Deluges. And of the Effects that it had upon the Earth. By <hi>John Woodward,</hi> M. D. Profeſſor of Phyſick in <hi>Greſham</hi>-Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege,
<pb facs="tcp:151648:125"/>
and Fellow of the Royal So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, 8<hi>vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Vindication of the Truth of Chriſtian Religion againſt the Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of all Modern Oppoſers. By <hi>James Abbadie,</hi> D. D. 8<hi>vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond Part of the Enquiry into ſeveral Remarkable Texts of the Old and New Teſtament, which contain ſome difficulty in them: with a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable reſolution of them. The ſecond Edit. 8<hi>vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe concerning the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, Style, and Perfection of the Books of the Old and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; with a continued Illuſtration of ſeveral difficult Texts of Scripture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hroughout the whole Work. Both by <hi>John Edwards,</hi> B. D. ſometime Fellow of St. <hi>John</hi>'s <hi>College</hi> in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> 8<hi>vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Glorious Epiphany, with the Devout Chriſtians Love to it. <hi>The Second Edition</hi> 8<hi>vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Search the Scriptures. A Treatiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hewing that all Chriſtians ought to
<pb facs="tcp:151648:126"/>
read the Holy Books; with Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to them therein.</p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe concerning Prayer, eſpecially of frequenting the daily Publick Prayers. All three by the Reverend <hi>Sym. Patrick,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>The Old Religion demonſtrated in the Principles, and deſcribed in the Life and Practice thereof. By <hi>J. Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> D. D. <hi>The Second Edition.</hi> 12<hi>o.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>The End of the Catalogue.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:151648:126"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
